<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Lords Report of 7 January 1807</title>
    <dateCreated>Sun, 07 Jan 1807 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='1847' text='The Malt and Pension Duty bills were read a third time, and passed.&amp;#x2014;The Speaker informed the House, that as the Horsham Election petition was to be taken into consideration to-morrow, he would come down to the house at halfpast three, and proceed to count the house at a quarter-past four precisely.&amp;#x2014;Mr. Vansittart brought in a bill for granting to his majesty 10,500,000&lt;i&gt;l&lt;/i&gt;. to be raised by Loans or Exchequer bills, which was read a first time.&amp;#x2014;Mr. Hobhouse brought up the Annual Qualification Indemnity bill, which was read a first time.&amp;#x2014;Lord Ossulston reported to the house, that his majesty had been waited upon with the Address voted unanimously the 5th instant, and that his majesty was graciously pleased to return the following answer:&amp;#x2014;" Gentlemen, "I thank the House of Commons for their loyal and dutiful Address; and receive with satisfaction the assurances of their full conviction, that the restoration of Peace has been prevented only by the ambition and injustice of the enemy. I&#x000A;&lt;image src="S1V0008P0I0225"&gt;&lt;/image&gt;&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;423&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;rely with entire confidence on the effectual support of my faithful people in the prosecution of a contest, manifestly continued, on the part of the enemy, with the hope of destroying the power and independence of the British empire.' title='MINUTES.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1807/jan/07/minutes'></outline>
    <outline id='1848' text='The house having resolved itself into a committee of supply, Mr. Calcraft moved, that the Estimate of the charge of the office of ordnance for Great Britain and Ireland, for the year 1807, be referred to the said committee.&lt;br/&gt;Mr. Calcraftthen rose. He said, that, on moving the Ordnance Estimates, he felt much satisfaction, that it would not be necessary for him to detain the committee by observations of any length; that if, however, there were any topics that required further explanation, or any questions that gentlemen might deem it necessary to propose to him, he should willingly answer such questions, and, if he could, adequately. He had an additional satisfaction in being enabled to inform the committee that there was a considerable reduction in the Estimates he had now to submit to them, compared with those of last year: he did not mean, in stating this, to claim any extraordinary acknowledgement of merit as due to the present Board of Ordnance; he rather thought that the present reduction might more justly be imputed to the adequate supplies of former years, which, in facilitating the progress of the public works, had lessened the grants of money necessary to support them. If the Board of Ordnance had any claim to merit, it was for the uniform zeal with which the Board resisted all the projects of expenditure that had been submitted to them, and consulted upon all occasions the most practical economy. The principal reductions were owing to the completion of those great works in Kent, and upon the coast of Sussex, which, while erecting, were productive of an expence of no inconsiderable magnitude. The sum now required would be found to be 600,000&lt;i&gt;l&lt;/i&gt;. less than that voted last year, and this too, notwithstanding the increase of 1,400 men in one battalion of foot artillery; the increased expence of the establishments of engineers, and the augmentation of pay to the artillery, granted by his majesty. This threefold addition to our expenditures would amount to 150,000&lt;i&gt;l&lt;/i&gt;. so that had there not been a reduction of 600,000&lt;i&gt;l&lt;/i&gt;. the increase now required would be 750,000&lt;i&gt;l&lt;/i&gt;. As to the Ordnance Estimates for Ireland, the dimi-&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;424&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;nution would be found to be in the same proportion, and to be ascribed to the same cause; and in general he could say, and it was great satisfaction to him that he felt warranted in saying, that whoever should have the honour of discharging, next year, the duty he was now called upon to perform, would yet have a more pleasing task, as the reduction would, by that time, be still greater, as the lines of Chatham, and the great works now carrying on at Dover and the Coast, would, by that time, be completed. He had but one observation more to make, that since the estimates had been laid upon the table, an advance upon the vote of credit had been made to the amount of 400,000&lt;i&gt;l&lt;/i&gt;.; he would therefore, from the sum originally required, make a deduction to that amount. He did not think, it necessary to detain the committee further than by stating, that he was very willing to give every information in his power to any gentleman, and should listen with respect to any suggestion the hon, gentlemen opposite should think it necessary to offer.&amp;#x2014;The hon. gent. concluded with moving, "1. That a sum, not exceeding 2,278,197&lt;i&gt;l&lt;/i&gt;. 0&lt;i&gt;s&lt;/i&gt;. 10&lt;i&gt;d&lt;/i&gt;. be granted to his majesty, for the charge of the Office of Ordnance for Laud Service for Great Britain, for the year 1807.&amp;#x2014;2. That 479,246&lt;i&gt;l&lt;/i&gt;. 19&lt;i&gt;s&lt;/i&gt;. 7&lt;i&gt;d&lt;/i&gt;. be granted to his majesty, for the charge of the Office of Ordnance in Ireland, for the year 1807.&amp;#x2014;3. That 301,406&lt;i&gt;l&lt;/i&gt;. 9&lt;i&gt;s&lt;/i&gt;. 8&lt;i&gt;d&lt;/i&gt;. be granted to his majesty, for defraying the expence of services performed by the Office of Ordnance for Land Service for Great Britain, and not provided for by parliament in the year 1805.&amp;#x2014;4. That 262,365&lt;i&gt;l&lt;/i&gt;. 14&lt;i&gt;s&lt;/i&gt;. 2&lt;i&gt;d&lt;/i&gt; be granted to his majesty, for defraying the expence of services performed by the Office of Ordnance for Land Service for Great Britain, and not provided for by parliament in the year 1806." The report was ordered to be received to-morrow.' title='ORDNANCE ESTIMATES.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1807/jan/07/ordnance-estimates'></outline>
  </body>
</opml>
