<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Lords Report of 25 March 1925</title>
    <dateCreated>Wed, 25 Mar 1925 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='2280631' text='Committee for Privileges met: Counsel heard on behalf of the Petitioner Richard Harold St. Maur: Claims considered: Resolution agreed to by the Committee: Report thereof to be made to the House.&lt;br/&gt;Report from the Committee for Privileges:&amp;#x2014;&lt;br/&gt;That the Dukedom of Somerset was created by Letters Patent of King Edward VI, dated 16th February, 1546&amp;#x2013;7, granted to Edward Earl of Hertford, Viscount Beauchamp of Hache and Baron Seymour with the limitations therein specified; that Edward Duke of Somerset was executed 22nd January, 1551&amp;#x2013;2, was attainted and all his honours forfeited; that the said Dukedom of Somerset and the said Barony of Seymour with the limitations specified in the Letters Patent of creation were restored to William Seymour, great-grandson of the said Edward, 1st Duke of Somerset, and that the said William was summoned to the House of Lords in the said Dukedom of Somerset; that the said Dukedom descended according to the limitations specified in the Letters Patent of creation to Algernon, 15th Duke, who died without issue the the 22nd October, 1923.&lt;br/&gt;That the claimant Sir Edward Hamilton Seymour has proved to the satisfaction of this Committee the extinction of the lines senior to his own, and, claiming through Lord Francis Seymour, who died 16th February, 1790, fourth son of Edward, 8th Duke, is (in the event of the validity of the marriage of Francis Compton Seymour, son and heir of the said Lord Francis Seymour and Leonora Hudson being established) the heir-male of the said Lord Francis Seymour, and of the said Edward 1st Duke of Somerset;&lt;br/&gt;That, in the opinion of this Committee, the evidence of the validity of the marriage had between Francis Compton Seymour and Leonora Hudson produced by the said claimant Sir&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;740&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;Edward Hamilton Seymour is not rebutted by the allegations and the evidence in support thereof produced by the Petitioner Henry Sydney Seymour and the claimant George Francis Alexander Marquess of Hertford, and that therefore the said marriage stands, and that the said claimant Sir Edward Hamilton Seymour ought, on the evidence produced, to be regarded as the heir-male of Edward, 1st Duke of Somerset, and by virtue of the limitations contained in the patent of creation of the said Dukedom is entitled to his writ of summons in the said Dukedom of Somerset.&lt;br/&gt;Read, and agreed to.' title='DUKEDOM OF SOMERSET.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1925/mar/25/dukedom-of-somerset'></outline>
    <outline id='2280632' text='Message from the Commons that they concur in the Resolution of this House communicated to them on the 19th instant, That it is desirable that a Standing Joint Committee on Indian Affairs of both Houses of Parliament be appointed to examine and report on any Bill or matter referred to them specifically by either House of Parliament, and to consider with a view to reporting if necessary thereon any matter relating to Indian Affairs brought to the notice of the Committee by the Secretary of State for India.' title='STANDING JOINT COMMITTEE ON INDIAN AFFAIRS.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1925/mar/25/standing-joint-committee-on-indian'></outline>
    <outline id='2280634' text='Committee to meet on Thursday, April 2.' title="LLOYD'S BILL. [H.L.]" type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1925/mar/25/lloyds-bill-hl'></outline>
    <outline id='2280635' text="ST. MILDRED'S CHURCHYARD BILL. [H.L.]">
      <outline id='2280636' text='BLACKPOOL IMPROVEMENT BILL. [H.L.]'>
        <outline id='2280637' text='Report from the Committee of Selection, That the following Lords be proposed to the House to form the Select&#x000A;&lt;image src="S5LV0060P0I0401"/&gt;&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;741&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;Committee for the consideration of the said Bills; namely:&amp;#x2014;&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;V. Chaplin,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Plunket,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Kintore (&lt;i&gt;E. Kintore&lt;/i&gt;) (Chairman);&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Raglan,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Clwyd,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/ul&gt;&#x000A;agreed to; and the said Lords appointed accordingly: The Committee to meet on Wednesday, May 6, at eleven o&apos;clock; and all Petitions referred to the Committee, with leave to the Petitioners praying to be heard by Counsel against the Bills to be heard as desired, as also Counsel for the Bills.' title='WEST HAM CORPORATION BILL. [H.L.]' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1925/mar/25/west-ham-corporation-bill-hl'></outline>
      </outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='2280638' text="&lt;b&gt;SOUTHERN RAILWAY BILL. [H.L.]&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;GREAT YARMOUTH HAVEN BRIDGE&lt;lb/&gt; BILL. [H.L.]&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;BEDFORDSHIRE. CAMBRIDGESHIRE. AND HUNTINGDONSHIRE ELECTRICITY BILL. [H.L.]&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;PORT OF LONDON BILL&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;BOOTHFERRY BRIDGE BILL. [H.L.]&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;OLDHAM CORPORATION BILL. [H.L.]&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Report from the Committee of Selection, That the following Lords be proposed to the House to form the Select Committee for the consideration of the said Bills: namely:&amp;#x2014;&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;E. Strafford (Chairman);&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Fairfax,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Lawrence,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Wyfold,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Cable,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/ul&gt;&#x000A;agreed to; and the said Lords appointed accordingly: The Committee to meet on Wednesday, May 6, at half-past eleven o'clock; and all Petitions referred to the Committee, with leave to the Petitioners praying to be heard by Counsel against the Bills to be heard as desired, as also Counsel for the, Bills." title='LEEK URBAN DISTRICT COUNCIL WATER BILL. [H.L.]' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1925/mar/25/leek-urban-district-council-water-bill-hl'></outline>
    <outline id='2280639' text='To be read 2&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt; on Tuesday, April 28 next.&amp;#x2014;(&lt;i&gt;Viscount Novar&lt;/i&gt;.)' title='LICENSING (SCOTLAND) AMENDMENT BILL. [H.L.]' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1925/mar/25/licensing-scotland-amendment-bill-hl'></outline>
    <outline id='2280640' text='To be read 2&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt; on Wednesday, April 1 next.&amp;#x2014;(&lt;i&gt;The Earl of Birkenhead&lt;/i&gt;.)' title='GOVERNMENT OF INDIA (CIVIL SERVICES) BILL. [H.L.]' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1925/mar/25/government-of-india-civil-services-bill'></outline>
  </body>
</opml>
