<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Lords Report of 25 June 1936</title>
    <dateCreated>Thu, 25 Jun 1936 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='2269179' text="&lt;b&gt;COLNE VALLEY AND NORTHWOOD ELECTRICITY BILL.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;BRENTFORD AND CHISWICK CORPORATION BILL.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;GREAT WESTERN RAILWAY (EALING AND SHEPHERD'S BUSH RAILWAY EXTENSION) BILL.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Reported, with Amendments.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;GAS LIGHT AND COKE COMPANY (No. 1) BILL.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;CIRENCESTER GAS BILL.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Reported, without amendment.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;LONDON AND MIDDLESEX (IMPROVEMENTS, ETC.) BILL.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;WOLVERHAMPTON CORPORATION BILL.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Report from the Committee of Selection, That the following Lords be proposed to the House to form the Select Committee for the consideration of the said Bills; namely:&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;E. Airlie,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;E. Hardwicke,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;V. Gough,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Saltersford (&lt;i&gt;E. Courtown&lt;/i&gt;),&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Redesdale (Chairman):&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/ul&gt;&#x000A;Agreed to; and the said Lords appointed accordingly. The Committee to meet on Tuesday next, at eleven o'clock; and all petitions referred to the Committee, with leave to the Petitioners praying to be heard by Counsel against the Bills to be heard as desired, as also Counsel for the Bills." title='Preamble' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1936/jun/25/preamble'></outline>
    <outline id='2269180' text='Report from the Committee of Selection, That the five Lords appointed a Select Committee on the Manchester Ship Canal Bill [H.L.] and another Bill do form the Select Committee for the consideration of the Gas Light and Coke Company (No. 2) Bill: Read, and agreed to. All Petitions referred to the Committee, with leave to the Petitioners&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;282&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;praying to be heard by Counsel against the Bill to be heard as desired, as also Counsel for the Bill.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;BRIDGNORTH GAS ORDER, 1936.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;NEWPORT (ISLE OF WIGHT) GAS ORDER, 1936.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;WINSFORD GAS ORDER, 1936.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;LEICESTER GAS ORDER, 1936.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;EDINBURGH CORPORATION GAS ORDER, 1936.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;CANNOCK ELECTRICITY (EXTENSION) ORDER, 1936.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Report from the Special Orders Committee, That no Petition has been presented praying to be heard against the Special Orders, and that there is nothing in these Orders to which they think it necessary to call the attention of the House:&lt;br/&gt;Read, and ordered to lie on the Table.' title='GAS LIGHT AND COKE COMPANY (No. 2) BILL.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1936/jun/25/gas-light-and-coke-company-no-2-bill'></outline>
    <outline id='2269181' text='Report from the Special Orders Committee, That they have examined the Special Order as required by the Standing Orders of the House; that in their opinion the Order raises important questions of policy and principle which have been accepted already by the House when passing the Cattle Industry (Emergency Provisions) (No. 2) Act, 1935, under which the Order is submitted for approval; that the Order is founded on precedent, inasmuch as an Order has already been submitted for the approval of Parliament under this Act; that in the opinion of the Committee the Order can be passed by the House without special attention, subject to any arguments on the merits which may arise in debate, and that no further inquiry is necessary before the House proceeds to a decision on the Resolution to approve the said Order:&lt;br/&gt;Read, and ordered to lie on the Table.' title='CATTLE INDUSTRY (EMERGENCY PROVISIONS) (EXTENSION OF PERIOD) ORDER, 1936.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1936/jun/25/cattle-industry-emergency-provisions'></outline>
    <outline id='2269182' text='Report from the Special Orders Committee, That they have examined the Special Order as required by the Standing Orders of the House; that in their&#x000A;&lt;image src="S5LV0101P0I0147"/&gt;&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;283&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;opinion the provisions of the Order raises important questions of policy and principle which have been accepted already by the House when passing the Debts Clearing Offices and Import Restrictions Act, 1934, under which the Order is submitted for approval; that the Order is founded on precedent, inasmuch as a similar Order has been submitted for the approval of Parliament under the Act, although this Order dealt with another country; that in the opinion of the Committee the Order cannot be passed by the House without special attention, but that no further inquiry is necessary before the House proceeds to a decision on the Resolution to approve the said Order:&lt;br/&gt;Read, and ordered to lie on the Table.' title='CLEARING OFFICE (RUMANIA) ORDER, 1936.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1936/jun/25/clearing-office-rumania-order-1936'></outline>
    <outline id='2269183' text='Report from the Special Orders Committee, That they have examined the Special Order as required by the Standing Orders of the House; that in their opinion the Order does not raise important questions of policy and principle; that the Order is founded on precedent, inasmuch as it provides merely for the amendment of an Order which has received already the approval of the House; that in the opinion of the Committee the Order can be passed by the House without special attention, and that no further inquiry is necessary before the House proceeds to a decision on the Resolution to approve the said Order:&lt;br/&gt;Read, and ordered to lie on the Table.' title='CLEARING OFFICE (SPAIN) AMEND- MENT ORDER, 1936.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1936/jun/25/clearing-office-spain-amend-ment-order'></outline>
    <outline id='2269184' text='Report from the Special Orders Committee, That they have examined the Special Order as required by the Standing Orders of the House; that they have received and considered a Report from the Board of Trade; that in their opinion the Order raises important questions of policy and principle; that the&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;284&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;Order is not founded on precedent, although an Order has already been submitted for the approval of Parliament under the Coal Mines Act, 1930, which was of a different character; that in the opinion of the Committee the Order cannot be passed by the House without special attention, but that no further inquiry is necessary before the House proceeds to a decision on the Resolution to approve the said Order:&lt;br/&gt;Read, and ordered to lie on the Table.' title='CENTRAL (COAL MINES) SCHEME (AMENDMENT) ORDER, 1936.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1936/jun/25/central-coal-mines-scheme-amendment'></outline>
    <outline id='2269185' text='Special Order in respect of the compulsory acquisition of servitudes or other rights for overhead main transmission lines in and over certain land situate at Portobello in the City and County of the City of Edinburgh:&lt;br/&gt;Laid before the House (pursuant to Act) for affirmative Resolution and referred to the Special Orders Committee.&lt;br/&gt;MINISTRY OF HEALTH PROVISIONAL ORDER CONFIRMATION (WEST HARTLEPOOL) BILL. [H.L.]&lt;br/&gt;MINISTRY OF HEALTH PROVI-SIONAL ORDER CONFIRMATION (PLYMPTON SAINT MARY) BILL. [H.L.]&lt;br/&gt;MINISTRY OF HEALTH PROVISIONAL ORDER CONFIRMATION (BARNSLEY) BILL. [H.L.]&lt;br/&gt;MINISTRY OF HEALTH PROVISIONAL ORDER CONFIRMATION (ST. HELENS) BILL. [H.L.]&lt;br/&gt;Reported, without amendment, and recommitted to a Committee of the Whole House on Tuesday next.' title='CENTRAL ELECTRICITY BOARD (PORTOBELLO LAND) ORDER, 1936.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1936/jun/25/central-electricity-board-portobello'></outline>
    <outline id='2269186' text='A witness ordered to attend the Joint Committee: Ordered, That a Message be sent to the Commons to acquaint them therewith and to desire their concurrence.' title='MEASUREMENT OF GAS.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1936/jun/25/measurement-of-gas'></outline>
  </body>
</opml>
