<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Written Statement of 13 October 2004</title>
    <dateCreated>Wed, 13 Oct 2004 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='2586326'>
      <outline id='2586328' text='The Lord President of the Council (Baroness Amos)&lt;p id="S5LV0665P0-09471"&gt;My right honourable friend the Secretary of State for International Development has made the following Statement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0665P0-09472"&gt;The UK will commit at least &amp;#x00A3;100 million next year for humanitarian and development assistance for Sudan provided there is early signature of a comprehensive peace agreement and the Government of Sudan live up to their commitments on Darfur. The &amp;#x00A3;100 million for next year will enable us to maintain our significant response to support for the humanitarian crisis in Darfur. It will also enable the UK to contribute to other humanitarian, recovery and reintegration needs in Sudan. We look forward to the signing of a comprehensive peace agreement before the end of the year and to working with the new administrations in Sudan to establish a development programme that contributes to eradicating poverty and building a safer Sudan for all.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Sudan: Future Aid' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/oct/13/sudan-future-aid'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='2586344'>
      <outline id='2586345' text='The Minister of State, Home Office (Baroness Scotland of Asthal)&lt;p id="S5LV0665P0-09473"&gt;The House will be aware of the review by the Security Service and Metropolitan Police of the security of the Palace of Westminster. This report is, of course, a matter for Mr Speaker, for the Lord Chairman and for the House authorities. However, it may be helpful if I update the House on the steps we have been taking to enhance the external security of Parliament and the surrounding area.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0665P0-09474"&gt;The Government have always set out clearly the nature of the threats that we face and the importance of keeping all our security measures and contingency planning under constant review. Therefore, alongside this formal review, my right honourable friend the Home Secretary asked the Intelligence and Security Co-ordinator, Sir David Omand, earlier this year to gather a small team to provide advice on protective&#x000A;&lt;table type="span"&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Title&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Details&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Target&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;KT 1a&amp;#x2014;Provision of Available Force Element Days&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The measurement of the number of days when the material condition of a vessel enables it to perform its scheduled task on that day.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;To provide Commander-In-Chief Fleet (CINCFLEET) with the target level of available force element days agreed in the CINCFLEET/Defence logistics organisation (DLO) customer supplier agreement (CSA).&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;KT 1b&amp;#x2014;Provision of Ready Force Element Days&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The measurement of the number of days when the material state of a vessel enables it to meet its required readiness category.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;To provide CINCFLEET with the target level of the ready force element days agreed in the CINCFLEET/DLO customer supplier agreement (CSA).&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;col&gt;WS 22&lt;/col&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0665P0-09475"&gt;security measures outside the Houses of Parliament and more generally in the central Westminster area.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0665P0-09476"&gt;As the House would expect, the Commissioner of the Metropolitan Police constantly reviews policing activities around the Whitehall and Westminster area. Operational police deployments have already been increased to counter the potential threat of vehicle bombs. In addition, we have already agreed further enhancements to the support for operational policing of the area including work on a new control room and CCTV.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0665P0-09477"&gt;We will also be discussing with Westminster City Council, the Mayor, Transport for London and other relevant authorities whether any further physical measures are required to provide additional protection around the Palace of Westminster. The Government recently tabled an amendment to the Civil Contingencies Bill, which will allow highway authorities to make an anti-terrorist traffic regulation order, on the application of the Chief Constable. As we indicated in laying the amendment, this is not specifically intended to control vehicle access around Parliament but it will make it easier for the police to respond to particular threats by further controlling traffic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0665P0-09478"&gt;While there are no plans for any major programme of road closures, we are determined that we should avoid a situation in which a series of steps, which may be sensible in themselves, has a wider impact on traffic and public access to this important part of London. We therefore believe that it would be helpful to undertake a wider process of consultation with the Mayor, Transport for London and other authorities and interested parties of the consequences of and options for changes to management of traffic around Parliament should further restrictions become necessary. We believe that this is essential if we are to safeguard and enhance not just the security of the area but also its economic and social well-being.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Palace of Westminster: External Security' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/oct/13/palace-of-westminster-external-security'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='2586346'>
      <outline id='2586348' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State, Ministry of Defence (Lord Bach)&lt;p id="S5LV0665P0-09479"&gt;My right honourable friend the Minister of State for Defence (Mr Adam Ingram) has made the following Written Ministerial Statement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0665P0-09480"&gt;Key targets have been set for the chief executive of the WSA for financial year 2004&amp;#x2013;05 as follows:&#x000A;&lt;image src="S5LV0665P0I0866"/&gt;&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;WS 23&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;&lt;table type="span"&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Title&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Details&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Target&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;KT 2&amp;#x2014;Timely Completion of Upkeep Periods.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The measurement of the amount by which the upkeep periods overrun.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;To meet the planned delivery dates for vessels undergoing deep maintenance and repair within the agreed upkeep factor tolerance.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;KT 3&amp;#x2014;Timely Completion of the High Priority Capability Improvement Programme&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The measurement of the number of high priority upgrades Implemented in accordance with the agreed and published installation plan.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;To fit 87 per cent. of the high priority, type A capability improvements (alterations and Additions&amp;#x2014;A and A) selected by the equipment capability customer (ECC).&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;KT 4&amp;#x2014;Provision of Single Living Accommodation&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The measurement of the increase in available single living accommodation (SLA).&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;To provide CINCFLEET, 2SL/CNH and naval base lodger units with the required quantity and quality of single living accommodation for their entitled personnel as articulated in DLO CSA.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;KT 5&amp;#x2014;Provision of Operational Support Services at the Naval Bases.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The measurement of the delivery of operational support services to a satisfactory standard.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;To provide CINCFLEET with the operational support services articulated in DLO customer supplier agreements (CSA) at the agreed ISO 9000 quality management standard.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;KT 6&amp;#x2014;Maintenance of WSA Capacity to Support the Naval Force Generation Plan&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The assurance that the agency has the capacity to contribute to the naval force generation plan.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;To achieve a satisfactory assessment against all elements of the agency&apos;s contribution to the naval force generation plan.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;KT 7&amp;#x2014;Delivering Planned Efficiencies&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The measurement of the delivery of planned efficiencies.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;To ensure delivery of 90 per cent. of the planned efficiency savings in the DLO benefits tracking tool that are scheduled to be achieved this financial year.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/p&gt;' title='Warship Support Agency: Targets 2004–05' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/oct/13/warship-support-agency-targets-2004-05'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='2586350'>
      <outline id='2586351' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State, Department for Culture, Media and Sport (Lord McIntosh of Haringey)&lt;p id="S5LV0665P0-09481"&gt;My right honourable friend the Secretary of State for Culture, Media and Sport has today made the following Written Ministerial Statement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0665P0-09482"&gt;I have today placed the independent review of the BBC&apos;s digital television services by Professor Patrick&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;WS 24&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;Barwise in the Libraries of both Houses. The report is also available electronically on the department&apos;s website &lt;u&gt;www.culture.gov.uk,&lt;/u&gt; together with a copy of the supporting report from Ofcom &lt;i&gt;Assessment of the Market Impact of the BBC&apos;s New Digital TV and Radio Services.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0665P0-09483"&gt;In response to the review, I have asked the BBC to give me its initial response to the report by the end of November. I will then consider whether further action is needed in the context of Charter review.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0665P0-09484"&gt;I will publish the independent review of the BBC&apos;s digital radio services shortly.&lt;/p&gt;' title='BBC Digital Television Services: Independent Review' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/oct/13/bbc-digital-television-services'></outline>
    </outline>
  </body>
</opml>
