<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Lords Report of 5 March 1940</title>
    <dateCreated>Tue, 05 Mar 1940 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='2297174' text='The LORD CHANCELLOR acquainted the House, That the Clerk of the Parliaments had laid upon the Table the Certificate from the Examiners that the further Standing Orders applicable to the following Bill have been complied with:&lt;br/&gt;Ely Cathedral Canonries.&lt;br/&gt;The same was ordered to lie on the Table.' title='Preamble' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1940/mar/05/preamble'></outline>
    <outline id='2297175' text="Report from the Committee of Selection, That the following Lords be proposed to the House to form the Select Committee for the consideration of the said Bill, namely:&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;V. Chelmsford,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Greville,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Holden,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Faringdon,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Kenilworth (Chairman):&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/ul&gt;&#x000A;Agreed to; and the said Lords appointed accordingly. The Committee to meet on Tuesday next, at Eleven o'clock; and all Petitions referred to the Committee, with leave to the Petitioners praying to be heard by Counsel against the Bill to be heard as desired, as also Counsel for the Bill." title='ROYAL SOCIETY FOR THE PRE- VENTION OF CRUELTY TO ANIMALS BILL. [H.L.]' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1940/mar/05/royal-society-for-the-pre-vention-of'></outline>
    <outline id='2297176' text='Report from the Special Orders Committee, That they have examined the Special Order as required by the Standing Orders of the House; that in their opinion the Order raises important questions of policy and principle; that the Order is founded on precedent, inasmuch as it provides for the further variation of an Order which has already received the approval of the House; that in the opinion of the Committee the Order cannot be passed by the House without special attention, but that no further inquiry is necessary before the House proceeds to a decision on the Resolution to approve the said Order:&lt;br/&gt;Read, and ordered to lie on the Table.' title='CLEARING OFFICE (TURKEY) (AMENDMENT) No. 2 ORDER, 1940.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1940/mar/05/clearing-office-turkey-amendment-no-2'></outline>
    <outline id='2297177' text='Report from the Special Orders Committee, That they have examined the Special Order as required by the Standing Orders of the House; that in their opinion the provisions of the Order raise important questions of policy and principle which have been accepted already by the House when passing the Czechoslovakia (Financial Claims and Refugees) Act, 1940, under which the Order is submitted for approval; that the Order is not founded on precedent; that in the opinion of the Committee the Order cannot be passed by the House without special attention, but that no further inquiry is necessary before the House proceeds to a decision on the Resolution to approve the said Order:&lt;br/&gt;Read, and ordered to lie on the Table.' title='CZECHO-SLOVAKIA (SETTLEMENT OF FINANCIAL CLAIMS) ORDER, 1940.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1940/mar/05/czecho-slovakia-settlement-of-financial'></outline>
    <outline id='2297178' text='Report from the Special Orders Committee, That no Petition has been presented praying to be heard against the Special Order, and that there is nothing in the Order to which they think it necessary to call the attention of the House:&lt;br/&gt;Read, and ordered to lie on the Table.' title='MORLEY GAS ORDER, 1940.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1940/mar/05/morley-gas-order-1940'></outline>
    <outline id='2297179' text='Report from the Special Orders Committee, That they have examined the Special Order as required by the Standing Orders of the House; that the petition against the Order presented by the Great Western Railway Company has now been withdrawn; that the Committee have considered an addition to Clause 39 of the Order, together with a modification thereof, which has been agreed between the parties, and recommend its adoption to the House; that they are of opinion that no further inquiry by a Select Committee is necessary; and that there is nothing further in this Order to which they think it necessary to call the attention of the House:&lt;br/&gt;Read, and ordered to lie on the Table.' title='CEFN AND DISTRICT GAS ORDER, 1940.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1940/mar/05/cefn-and-district-gas-order-1940'></outline>
    <outline id='2297180' text='Orders made by the Secretary of State for the Home Department, extending Section 1 of the Act to&amp;#x2014;&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;The Borough of Cleethorpes;&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;The Borough of Lowestoft:&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Laid before the House (pursuant to Act) for affirmative Resolution, and ordered Lo lie on the Table.' title='SUNDAY ENTERTAINMENTS ACT, 1932.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1940/mar/05/sunday-entertainments-act-1932'></outline>
  </body>
</opml>
