<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Written Statement of 11 November 2004</title>
    <dateCreated>Thu, 11 Nov 2004 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='2614182'>
      <outline id='2614183' text='The Lord President of the Council (Baroness Amos)&lt;p id="S5LV0666P0-09670"&gt;My right honourable friend the Minister of State for Northern Ireland has made the following Statement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0666P0-09671"&gt;As directed under Paragraph 5(2) of Schedule 7 to the Northern Ireland Act 1998, the 5th annual report of the Northern Ireland Human Rights Commission will be laid before the House on 11 November 2004.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Northern Ireland Human Rights Commission: Annual Report' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/nov/11/northern-ireland-human-rights-commission'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='2614184'>
      <outline id='2614185' text='Baroness Amos&lt;p id="S5LV0666P0-09672"&gt;My honourable friend the Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Northern Ireland has made the following Statement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0666P0-09673"&gt;The 2002&amp;#x2013;03 accounts of the Youth Council for Northern Ireland were deposited in the Libraries of both Houses on 11 November 2004.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Youth Council for Northern Ireland: Accounts 2002' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/nov/11/youth-council-for-northern-ireland'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='2614186'>
      <outline id='2614187' text='The Secretary of State for Constitutional Affairs and Lord Chancellor (Lord Falconer of Thoroton)&lt;p id="S5LV0666P0-09674"&gt;The problems dealt with every day in the magistrates&apos; courts are at the very top of the public agenda. We rely on them to be the front line in terms of dealing with crime, youth justice, and many family issues.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0666P0-09675"&gt;I have an ambition for magistrates&apos; courts that will see them more connected to their communities; more respected for what they do and their orders obeyed with the public having confidence in them; and more effective at what they do&amp;#x2014;dispensing local justice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0666P0-09676"&gt;To realise this I am working in partnership with the magistracy, the district judges and those working in magistrates&apos; courts to identify what can be done to achieve this vision and that will supplement the substantial changes already taking place in the magistrates&apos; courts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0666P0-09677"&gt;As part of this programme of work, &lt;i&gt;Supporting Magistrates to Provide Justice,&lt;/i&gt; tomorrow I am writing to every single lay magistrate in England and Wales inviting them to complete a questionnaire to give me their ideas and suggestions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0666P0-09678"&gt;The questionnaire will also be made available to the professional judiciary, all those who work in the magistrates&apos; courts and all organisations within the criminal justice system.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0666P0-09679"&gt;Further detail on the scope and objectives of this work, as well as electronic versions of the questionnaire, can be found on the Internet at &lt;u&gt;www.dca.gov.uk/magistrates.htm&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/p&gt;' title='Magistrates' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/nov/11/magistrates'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='2614188'>
      <outline id='2614189' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State, Department of Health (Lord Warner)&lt;p id="S5LV0666P0-09680"&gt;Following a public consultation earlier this year on proposals to restructure the advisory committees laid down in the Medicines Act 1968, I am pleased to inform the House of the new structure that the Government have decided to put in place. I am also informing the House of proposals to revise the code of practice on interests that will be applied to them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0666P0-09681"&gt;In summary, the new advisory committee structure will comprise:&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;a new commission that amalgamates the responsibilities of the present Medicines Commission and the Committee on Safety of Medicines and will advise Ministers direct on regulatory matters associated with medicines for human use;&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;a number of Section 4 committees which will be able to advise Ministers direct on issues for which they are responsible;&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;sub-committees and expert advisory groups (EAGs);&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;a list of experts on whom the commission and the other committees and groups can call for advice;&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;lay/patient representatives on each of the committees, sub-committees and groups.&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0666P0-09682"&gt;The new structure will closely align the advisory bodies established under the Medicines Act with the structures being established in the European medicines regulatory system. This will allow the department&apos;s Medicines and Healthcare products Regulatory Agency (MHRA) to continue to play a highly effective role in that system. There will be greater public and patient involvement in the regulatory process which will strengthen the agency&apos;s ability to take account of the public interest. As patients become increasingly knowledgeable about healthcare we want to ensure that there is a means to enable them to advise on the safety and efficacy of their medicines.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0666P0-09683"&gt;Today a public consultation is being launched on proposals to revise the code of practice on interests that applies to chairmen and members of the advisory bodies established under the 1968 Medicines Act. This is part of a wider programme of restructuring the advisory bodies that advise Ministers on matters relating to the Act, the exercise of powers under it and otherwise relating to human and veterinary medicines.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0666P0-09684"&gt;These proposals will also provide the means to comply with new EU legislation dealing with the financial and other interests of experts concerned with the authorisation and surveillance of medicinal products. Indeed our proposals go further than the requirements set out in the EU legislation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0666P0-09685"&gt;The proposals cover the financial and non-financial interests of the chairmen and members of the new commission, the Section 4 committees established under the Medicines Act (except the British Pharmacopoeia&#x000A;&lt;image src="S5LV0666P0I0852"/&gt;&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;WS 25&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;Commission), the sub-committees and expert advisory committee and any experts co-opted on to the committees. We are also proposing that chairmen and members must declare interests of immediate family of which they are aware, and any other matter that may affect, or may reasonably be perceived as affecting, their impartiality.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0666P0-09686"&gt;A wide range of bodies, representing patients, industry and healthcare professionals is being consulted. I am placing a copy of the consultation document&amp;#x2014;MLX316&amp;#x2014;in the Library, together with today&apos;s press release announcing these new measures. The consultation document can also be obtained from the MHRA website.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0666P0-09687"&gt;The Government are committed to ensuring that the MHRA operates in a transparent and open way. Because medicines form such an essential component of effective healthcare delivery, we are also committed to ensuring that patients and the public have an effective role to play in the regulatory process.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Medicines Act Advisory Committees' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/nov/11/medicines-act-advisory-committees'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='2614190'>
      <outline id='2614191' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State, Department of Trade and Industry (Lord Sainsbury of Turville)&lt;p id="S5LV0666P0-09688"&gt;My honourable friend the Minister for Industry and the Regions (Jacqui Smith) has made the following Statement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0666P0-09689"&gt;I would like to inform members of the House that, as part of a rolling programme of appointments, I have decided to appoint five new board members to the East Midlands Development Agency. The new appointees will take up their positions on 14 December 2004 and their names are set out below.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0666P0-09690"&gt;The new board members will replace members whose terms of office end in December this year, and they will bring experiences from business and local authorities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;col&gt;WS 26&lt;/col&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0666P0-09691"&gt;Decisions on the appointments have been made following open competition in accordance with the guidelines set down in the Commissioner for Public Appointments code of practice, and following consultation with key national and regional players.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0666P0-09692"&gt;EMDA (new members)&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Steve Brown&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Councillor Geoffrey Stevens&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Councillor Jonathan Collins&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Councillor Gary Hunt&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Professor Phillip Tasker&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;' title='East Midlands Development Agency' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/nov/11/east-midlands-development-agency'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='2614192'>
      <outline id='2614193' text='Lord Sainsbury of Turville&lt;p id="S5LV0666P0-09693"&gt;My honourable friend the Minister for Industry and the Regions (Jacqui Smith) has made the following Statement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0666P0-09694"&gt;I would like to inform members of the House that, as part of a rolling programme of appointments, I have decided to appoint five new members to One North-East. The new appointees will take up their positions on the 14 December 2004 and their names are set out below.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0666P0-09695"&gt;The new board members will replace members whose terms of office end in December this year and will bring experience from business, local authorities and the voluntary sector.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0666P0-09696"&gt;Decisions on the appointments have been made following open competition in accordance with the guidelines set down in the Commissioner for Public Appointments code of practice, and following consultation with key national and regional players.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0666P0-09697"&gt;ONE (new board members)&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Christopher Thompson&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Susan Underwood&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Robert Symonds&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Alison Thain&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Raymond Mallon&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;' title='One North-East Regional Development Agency' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/nov/11/one-north-east-regional-development'></outline>
    </outline>
  </body>
</opml>
