<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Lords Report of 2 March 1933</title>
    <dateCreated>Thu, 02 Mar 1933 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='2261574' text="WATFORD AND ST. ALBANS GAS&lt;lb/&gt; ORDER, 1932.&lt;br/&gt;LONDON OVERGROUND WIRES,&lt;lb/&gt; &amp;c. BILL. [H.L.]&lt;br/&gt;LYME REGIS DISTRICT WATER BILL. [H.L.]&lt;br/&gt;AMERSHAM, BEACONSFIELD AND DISTRICT WATER BILL. [H.L.]&lt;br/&gt;COLNE CORPORATION BILL. [H.L.]&lt;br/&gt;Report from the Committee of Selection, That the following Lords be proposed to the House to form the Select Committee for the consideration of the said Bills and Special Order, namely:&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;E. Dudley,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;E. Iddesleigh,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;V. Burnham (Chairman),&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Stanley of Alderley,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Annesley &lt;i&gt;(V. Valentia)&lt;/i&gt;:&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&#x000A;Agreed to; and the said Lords appointed accordingly: The Committee to meet on Thursday, the 23rd instant, at eleven o'clock; and all Petitions referred to the Committee, with leave to the Petitioners praying to be heard by Counsel against the Bills and Special Order to be heard as desired, as also Counsel for the Bills and Special Order." title='WIMBLEDON CORPORATION BILL. [H.L.]' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1933/mar/02/wimbledon-corporation-bill-hl'></outline>
    <outline id='2261576' text='Report from tie Committee of Selection, That the Lords following be proposed to the House as members of the panel of Lords to act as Commissioners under the Act, namely:&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;E. Eldon,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Redesdale:&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&#x000A;Agreed to; and the said Lords appointed accordingly.' title='PRIVATE LEGISLATION PROCEDURE (SCOTLAND) ACT, 1899.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1933/mar/02/private-legislation-procedure-scotland'></outline>
    <outline id='2261577' text='Report from, That the Standing Orders not complied with in respect of the Durham Corporation Bill ought to be dispensed with, and the Bill allowed to proceed; and that the Standing Orders not complied with in respect of the Petition for Additional Provision in the&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;1034&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;Mabelthorpe and Sutton Urban District Council Bill ought to be dispensed with: Read, and agreed to.' title='STANDING ORDERS COMMITTEE.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1933/mar/02/standing-orders-committee'></outline>
    <outline id='2261579' text='Special Order in respect of part of the Borough of Walsall and part of the rural district of Walsall in the County of Stafford:&lt;br/&gt;Laid before the House (pursuant to Act) for affirmative Resolution and referred to the Special Orders Committee.' title='WALSALL ELECTRICITY (EXTENSION) ORDER, 1933.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1933/mar/02/walsall-electricity-extension-order-1933'></outline>
    <outline id='2261580' text='Order made by the Secretary of State for the Home Department extending Section 1 of the Act to the County Borough of Portsmouth:&lt;br/&gt;Laid before the souse (pursuant to Act) for affirmative Resolution and ordered to lie on the Table.' title='SUNDAY ENTERTAINMENTS ACT, 1932 (COUNTY BOROUGH OF PORTSMOUTH ORDER).' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1933/mar/02/sunday-entertainments-act-1932-county'></outline>
    <outline id='2261581' text='EXE VALLEY ELECTRICITY (EXTENSION) ORDER, 1932.&lt;br/&gt;STRETFORD AND DISTRICT ELECTRICITY ORDER, 1933.&lt;br/&gt;Report from the Special Orders Committee, That no Petition has been presented praying to be heard against the Special Orders, and that there is nothing in these Orders to which they think it necessary to call the attention of the House: Read, and ordered to lie on the Table.' title='MACHYNLLETH AND DISTRICT ELECTRICITY ORDER, 1932.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1933/mar/02/machynlleth-and-district-electricity'></outline>
    <outline id='2261582' text='MINISTRY OF HEALTH PROVISIONAL ORDER (LEEK) BILL.&lt;br/&gt;MINISTRY OF HEALTH PROVISIONAL ORDER (RUGBY JOINT HOSPITAL DISTRICT) BILL.&lt;br/&gt;MINISTRY OF HEALTH PROVISIONAL ORDER (TAUNTON ANDDISTRICT JOINT HOSPITAL DISTRICT) BILL.&lt;br/&gt;Reported, without amendment, and recommitted to a Committee of the Whole House on Tuesday next.' title='MINISTRY OF HEALTH PROVISIONAL ORDER (BUCKINGHAM AND OXFORD) BILL.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1933/mar/02/ministry-of-health-provisional-order'></outline>
  </body>
</opml>
