<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Written Statement of 4 June 2003</title>
    <dateCreated>Wed, 04 Jun 2003 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='3543355' text='ENVIRONMENT, FOOD AND RURAL AFFAIRS'>
      <outline id='3543356' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs (Mr. Elliot Morley)&lt;p&gt;I have set VMD the following performance targets for 2003&amp;#x2013;04:&lt;quote&gt;To process Marketing Authorisations quickly and efficiently with decisions based on sound, high quality science;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;To develop and implement an effective and evidence-based policy on the regulation of veterinary medicines, under-pinned by good science, and to provide timely advice on these matters to Ministers;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;To ensure effective post-authorisation surveillance and controls on the manufacture, distribution and use of authorised medicines and effective deterrents to illegal use of unauthorised medicines;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Cost-effective service at all levels of VMD;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;To contribute effectively to the Developing DEFRA programme;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;To ensure the strategic skills are in place to achieve the objectives set for VMD.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;' title='Veterinary Medicines Directorate' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jun/04/veterinary-medicines-directorate'></outline>
      <outline id='3543358' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs (Mr. Elliot Morley)&lt;p&gt;The Department carried out a review of its five-science based agencies in 2002. It was published on 17 December. Copies of the report are available on&lt;u&gt;http://www.defra.gov.uk/agency_review/index.asp.&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of the review&apos;s recommendations was that improvements to the performance management arrangements for VLA, CEFAS and CSL should be introduced from 2003&amp;#x2013;04 including agreed outcomes, with output targets as measurable indicators for meeting those outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have set the Veterinary Laboratories Agency, the Centre for Environment Fisheries and Aquaculture Science and the Central Science Laboratory the following agreed outcomes and performance targets for 2003&amp;#x2013;2004:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;VLA&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cost effective and efficient science businesses&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Achieve full cost recovery&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Maintain the ratio of overheads against turnover.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Achieve &amp;#x00A3;525K procurement savings.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Outward looking and collaborative organisations&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Prepare an annual report on their collaborative work.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;col&gt;6WS&lt;/col&gt;&lt;p&gt;Provision of R&amp;amp;D and science services of the required quality&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Maintain current third party accreditations&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Make satisfactory progress towards meeting the deadline of June 2004 for compliance with the DEFRA policy for Quality Assurance for Research.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Provision of a high standard of service to the satisfaction of customers&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Meet 85 per cent. of ROAME&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; milestones.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Meet 95 per cent. published turnaround time for export tests.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Achieve a customer satisfaction score of 75 per cent. CEFAS&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cost effective and efficient science businesses&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;To achieve savings by ensuring that support function costs grow more slowly than income.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;To recover from government departments and agencies and external customers the full economic costs of the Agency&apos;s services&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;To manage the agency in an effective manner including pursuit of commercial exploitation of research outputs&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Outward looking and collaborative organizations&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;To prepare an annual report on their collaborative work.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Provision of R&amp;amp;D and science services of the required quality&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;To maintain a high standard of excellence, based on indicators of scientific and technical quality.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Make satisfactory progress towards meeting the deadline of June 2004 for compliance with the DEFRA policy for Quality Assurance for Research.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Provision of a high standard of service to the satisfaction of customers&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;To give satisfaction to customers in the way that outputs are provided, taking account of the relevance, timeliness and value for money of outputs and the achievement of ROAME&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; milestones.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CSL&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cost effective and efficient science businesses&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;To recover the full economic costs of operation on a resource accounting basis, recognising the normal costs of operation&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;To deliver the efficiency targets set out in the Business Plan.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;To manage the agency in an effective manner, including delivery of e-government and commercial exploitation of research outputs&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Outward looking and collaborative organisations&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;To prepare an annual report on their collaborative work.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Provision of R&amp;amp;D and science services of the required quality&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;To make satisfactory progress with the action plan for enhancing science quality resulting from the 2001&amp;#x2013;02 Science Audit&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Make satisfactory progress towards meeting the deadline of June 2004 for compliance with the DEFRA policy for Quality Assurance for Research.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;image src="S6CV0406P0I0690"/&gt;&lt;col&gt;7WS&lt;/col&gt;&lt;p&gt;Provision of a high standard of service to the satisfaction of customers&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;To achieve a minimum of 90 per cent. of project milestones in commissioned projects which support the "Developing DEFRA" objectives To achieve a mean score of 4.2 on a scale of 0 to 5 for the assessment of customer satisfaction using the revised methodology&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;Rationale, Objectives, Appraisal, Monitoring and Evaluation statement&amp;#x2014;an integrated approach to programme/project management&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;' title='Performance Targets' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jun/04/performance-targets'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3543359' text='DEFENCE'>
      <outline id='3543360' text="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Defence (Dr. Lewis Moonie)&lt;p&gt;The Government are acutely aware of the need to ensure that we have fair and appropriate terms and conditions of service for Gurkha personnel. The current arrangements stem from the 1947 Tripartite Agreement (TPA) between the Governments of UK, Nepal and India. One of the aims of this Agreement was to safeguard the cultural, religious and ethnic heritage of Gurkha soldiers in accordance with the wishes of the Nepalese Government. It also linked British Gurkha Terms and Conditions of Service to arrangements in the Indian Army.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Government recognise, of course, that not all the principles that underpinned the TPA in 1947 apply today. It is for this reason that successive Governments have regarded the TPA as having a degree of flexibility. This has enabled significant enhancements to be made to Gurkha conditions of service, particularly to Gurkha pay and pension arrangements. Indeed, Gurkha in-service remuneration is now in line with that of British personnel and Gurkha pensions, which were reviewed and at least doubled in April 2000, now compare favourably to professional salaries in Nepal, where all Gurkhas are discharged. Importantly, Gurkhas continue to be paid an immediate pension after only 15 years' service, whereas the vast majority of British personnel receive a preserved pension, payable at the age of sixty.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Government are satisfied, therefore, that these key elements of Gurkha terms anti conditions of service are tailored to the needs of Gurkhas in 2003 and in particular that the difference between the pension schemes is both necessary and proportionate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Gurkha accompanied service provisions, however, have not been reviewed since the Brigade's withdrawal from Hong Kong in 1997. It was decided at that time that married accompanied service should be introduced in the UK, but that, in accordance with the TPA, it should continue to be capped at 25 per cent. of Brigade strength. In practice, this means that family married quarters are provided for all Gurkhas holding the rank of Colour Sergeant or above. Below that rank, Gurkhas are entitled to one accompanied tour of around 3 years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Government are well aware of the problems these restrictions cause, although there are important contemporary factors that influence our current practice. These relate to the impact that any change in policy could have on the deployability and effectiveness&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;8WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;of the Brigade as well as the need to maintain links between Gurkhas and their home country. These links were of importance to the Nepalese Government when they agreed to the transfer of Gurkha units into the British Army in 1947 and remain so to this day. Our bilateral relations with Nepal are highly valued and we take our obligations to the Nepalese Government very seriously.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is important, therefore, that we strike the right balance between the aspirations and needs of our Gurkha soldiers and the effectiveness and employability of the Brigade as a whole. With this in mind, I have asked Officials, in consultation with the Brigade of Gurkhas, to undertake a thorough review of Gurkha married accompanied service arrangements. In so doing we will, of course, consult the Nepalese Government. We will also consider the implications for the Garrison Estate in Brunei, given that at any one time nearly a quarter of the Brigade is stationed there, and address the education and welfare implications of any increase in the number of Gurkha families based in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I hope to be in a position to announce my findings to the House by the end of the year.&lt;/p&gt;" title='Gurkha Married Accompanied Service Review' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jun/04/gurkha-married-accompanied-service-review'></outline>
      <outline id='3543362' text="The Minister of State, Ministry of Defence (Mr. Adam Ingram)&lt;p&gt;Subsequent to a proposal by the Agency's Owner, the Second Sea Lord and Commander-in-Chief Naval Home Command, I have today set the 2003&amp;#x2013;04 key targets for the Naval Recruiting and Training Agency, as follows:&lt;quote&gt;To deliver RN personnel to the trained strength (or to other training organisations), to the required quality standard, within 5 per cent. variance from the tasked requirement.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;To deliver RM recruits to within 2 per cent. variance from the tasked requirement.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;To maintain success rates of 95 per cent. in career training (including targeted employment modules) and 97 per cent. in examined pre-joining training.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;To increase the trained strength of the RNR to 2200 by 31 March 2004.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;To reduce the average cost of the trained recruit to 98 per cent. of the 2001&amp;#x2013;02 baseline figure.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;To achieve net benefits of &amp;#x00A3;15 million in financial year 2003&amp;#x2013;04 from the partnering arrangement with Flagship Training Limited.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;" title='Naval Recruiting and Training Agency: Key Targets' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jun/04/naval-recruiting-and-training-agency-key'></outline>
      <outline id='3543364' text='The Minister of State, Ministry of Defence (Mr. Adam Ingram)&lt;p&gt;I am pleased to announce the start of an Assessment Phase (AP) to be led by Lockheed Martin UK Ltd., with Westland Helicopters Ltd. as strategic sub-contractor, to determine how best to sustain the capability of the Royal Navy&apos;s Merlin Mk1 helicopters for future operations. Merlin Mk1 already delivers a quantum leap in capability over the aircraft it succeeded, the Sea King Mk6, and is recognised as crucial across the spectrum of maritime operations. We anticipate an upgraded aircraft entering service towards the end of the decade, building on significant operational experience and technological advances to ensure that the full potential of this versatile and capable aircraft is realised and that it continues to meet our security challenges for decades to come. The AP, costing&lt;image src="S6CV0406P0I0691"/&gt;&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;9WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;&amp;#x00A3;18 million, will investigate the most cost effective way to sustain this world beating capability and the scope for enhancements to broaden the utility and versatility of the aircraft. The partnering of Lockheed Martin as prime contractor with the world class manufacturing skills of Westland as strategic sub-contractor is believed to offer the lowest risk to the Ministry of Defence. The AP is planned to complete at the end of 2004 after which a decision will be made on the scope and programme for the Demonstration and Manufacture Phase.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Merlin MK1 Helicopters' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jun/04/merlin-mk1-helicopters'></outline>
      <outline id='3543365' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Defence (Dr. Lewis Moonie)&lt;p&gt;On 19 July 2001,&lt;i&gt;Official Report,&lt;/i&gt; columns 334&amp;#x2013;35W, my right hon. Friend the Minister of State for the Armed Forces advised the House that, in parallel with the work being undertaken on the Defence Training Review, the Royal Navy was conducting a comprehensive review of its training estate. Fundamental to this review was the creation of an integrated maritime warfare school, which would deliver all maritime warfare training on a single site at HMS Collingwood, near Fareham. Once the maritime warfare school was established, HMS Dryad, near Portsmouth, would be surplus to requirement and would close. It was envisaged that the transfer to HMS Collingwood would be completed, at the latest, by 2011.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am pleased to announce that an accelerated programme will allow the collocation to HMS Collingwood and the decommissioning of HMS Dryad, to be achieved by 2004. A small enclave, housing operations room simulators which are complex to remove, will remain on the site until the simulators are relocated or replaced, with an expectation that the site will be handed over to Defence Estates by 2007 for disposal in accordance with normal procedures.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have recommended that the proposals for the final closure programme are now put to the MOD Trades Unions for consultation in the normal way.&lt;/p&gt;' title='HMS Dryad' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jun/04/hms-dryad'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3543367' text='HOME DEPARTMENT'>
      <outline id='3543368' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for the Home Department (Paul Goggins)&lt;p&gt;Today I am publishing and placing in the Library the report of the fundamental review of death certification and coroner services. This comprehensive and thoughtful report is the work of an independent review group chaired by Tom Luce, formerly of the Department of Health.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am very grateful to Tom Luce and his colleagues for delivering such a wide-ranging and careful report. In their comprehensive analysis of this complex and difficult area, they have consulted very widely, taking into account the views of families, interest groups, and the many professions and organisations that work in this field. This is not an easy topic, nor is it an area where there are simple answers. A careful balance is required between the requirement to investigate deaths that are a matter of legitimate public concern, and the need to respect the private grief of individual families. This report recommends some very significant changes and improvements to the way in which deaths are currently&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;10WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;investigated and certified. It also highlights the good work being done by many of those working in this long neglected public service.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We do not intend to respond to the detailed proposals in the Luce Report at this stage. This is because we need to consider them alongside the Second Report of the Shipman Inquiry, chaired by Dame Janet Smith, which will focus on death and cremation certification, and police investigation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am pleased to announce that Tom Luce has agreed to do some further work on the links between the two reports. Once that has been completed, we will be able to announce plans for taking this work forward.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Death Certification and Coroner Services' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jun/04/death-certification-and-coroner-services'></outline>
      <outline id='3543371' text="The Minister for Citizenship and Immigration (Beverley Hughes)&lt;p&gt;I have made a new authorisation under section 19D of the Race Relations Act 1976 (as amended) to allow a certain proportion of the permits issued under the new Sectors Based Schemes in the hospitality and food processing sectors to be available for issue only to nationals of countries who are due to accede to the European Union on 1 May 2004.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This reflects the Government's commitment to these countries to give greater access to the UK labour markets in the period leading up to the date of their accession to the European Union.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A copy of the new authorisation, which came into force on 30 May, has been placed in the Libraries of both Houses.&lt;/p&gt;" title='Race Relations Act' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jun/04/race-relations-act'></outline>
      <outline id='3543373' text='The Secretary of State for the Home Department (Mr. David Blunkett)&lt;p&gt;I am pleased to report that the first of the Queen&apos;s Golden Jubilee Awards for voluntary service by groups in the community were announced on Monday 2 June.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This prestigious new annual Award for groups of volunteers has been given this year to 200 groups whose outstanding voluntary activity has enhanced and improved the quality of life and opportunity for others in the community. The Government actively support the work of the voluntary and community sector and are encouraging more people to participate in community activity. This Award will give some of those people the recognition they richly deserve. The details of the winning groups are as follows:&#x000A;&lt;table&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td colspan="3" align="center"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Winners of the Queen&apos;s Golden Jubilee Award for voluntary service by groups in the community 2003&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Voluntary Group&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Activity Description&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;East Midlands&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Age Concern Spalding District&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;helping the elderly of Spalding and Pinchbeck and giving respite to their carers.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Ashfield Environmental Project&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing free services to the elderly, infirm or disabled, including gardening and horticultural training opportunities.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Bakewell &amp;amp; Eyam Community Transport&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing transport for those who have no car, or cannot use public transport.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/table&gt;&#x000A;&lt;image src="S6CV0406P0I0692"/&gt;&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;11WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;&lt;table&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td colspan="3" align="center"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Winners of the Queen&apos;s Golden Jubilee Award for voluntary service by groups in the community 2003&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Voluntary Group&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Activity Description&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Buxton Mountain Rescue Team&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;preventing loss of life or injury by undertaking mountain rescue operations.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Coping with Cancer in Leicestershire &amp;amp; Rutland&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing information and practical and emotional support to people affected by cancer.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Derbyshire Gypsy Liaison Group&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;supporting Gypsies and promoting understanding of their culture.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Lincoln MS Therapy Centre&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing support, therapy, advice and friendship to Ms suffers, their family and friends.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Muslim Khatri Association&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing social and recreational activities, advancing education and relieving poverty in Leicester.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Nottinghamshire Bereavement Trust&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;comforting and helping the bereaved and assisting to develop Children&apos;s Gardens in major local cemeteries.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Green Health Partnership Volunteers&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing practical conservation activities involving people with mental ill-health to benefit both them and the environment in Derbyshire.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;11&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Pet Shop Girls Charitable Trust&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;undertaking fund-raising and other events for the local community of Ollerton and District.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Wellingborough Prison Visitors Centre Volunteers&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing practical and emotional support for visitors to Wellingborough Prison.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;East of England&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;13&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;1220 (March) Squadron&amp;#x2014; Air Training Corps&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;promoting interest in aviation, training and development and community service for young people.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;14&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Aylsham and District Care Trust&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;strengthening the community through the development and co- ordination of voluntary care services and social activity.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Connect Club Welwyn and Hatfield (WOT-NOTS Project)&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;preserving, protecting and promoting the mental health of local residents.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;16&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Dunstable and District Disabled Sports&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing sports and other activities for disabled people.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;17&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Garboldisham Village Hall Management Committee&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing and maintaining the village hall for recreational, cultural, educational and sporting activities.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;18&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Gunton Woodland Community Project&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing, maintaining and regenerating a safe, accessible and pleasant woodland environment for the public.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;19&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Harlow Well Women Centre&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing an accessible centre for women with professional counselling, advice, support and information.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Hospice at Home Volunteers&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;befriending and supporting those suffering from life-threatening illness, their families and carers.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;21&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Jimmy&apos;s Night Shelter&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing accommodation for rough sleepers in Cambridge, helping them move into suitable accommodation and raising awareness.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;22&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Senior Stop&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing a meeting place and advice for older people in Peterborough.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;23&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;SNAP Special Needs and Parents&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;supporting parents and carers of children with any special need or disability in Essex.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;24&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Magdalene Group&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;running a drop-in centre, giving support and providing activities for people working in prostitution in Norwich.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;25&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Mount Bovingdon Visitors Centre Association&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing a safe, comfortable environment and support for visitors to the prison.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;26&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Redbourn Care Group&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;recruiting and organising volunteers to provide caring services to those who need assistance.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/table&gt;&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;12WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;&lt;table&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td colspan="3" align="center"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Winners of the Queen&apos;s Golden Jubilee Award for voluntary service by groups in the community 2003&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Voluntary Group&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Activity Description&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;27&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Woolverstone Project&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing sailing opportunities for those with physical or mental disabilities in East Anglia.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;28&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Watford Mosque and Welfare Association&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;catering for the religious, social welfare and cultural requirements of the Muslim Community.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Guernsey&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;29&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Guernsey Welfare Service Limited&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing food, clothing and fuel vouchers to people on low incomes in the community.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;30&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;WRVS Alderney&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;meeting the needs of the elderly and those less able to help themselves.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Isle of Man&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;31&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Volunteers of Hospice Care, Isle of Man&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;supporting and enabling hospice services for the people.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Jersey&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;32&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Honorary Police of Jersey&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing community policing and contributing to the administration of the justice system.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;London&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;33&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Aldgate Advice Centre Volunteers&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;assisting and befriending rough sleepers and homeless people.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;34&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Barnet Retired and Senior Volunteer Programme&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;harnessing the expertise and skills of volunteers over 50.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;35&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Body and Soul&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;supporting those living with and affected by HIV and AIDS, across London.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;36&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Harlesden Environmental Action Residents and Traders&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;creating a cleaner, safer and healthier environment for the community.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;37&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Homeless Action in Barnet&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;meeting the needs of homeless people and asylum seekers.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;38&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Kith and Kids&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;empowering and socially including families in North London where one or more members has a disability.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;39&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Lambeth Summer Projects Trust&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing educational and recreational holiday activities to reduce the potential for young people to commit crime.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;40&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;MERU&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing free specialist equipment for disabled children in South London and the surrounding area.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;41&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Nubian Life&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;reasserting the dignity of African and Caribbean Elders by providing for their health, psychological and cultural needs.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;42&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Redbridge Night Shelter&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;alleviating the effects of poverty by providing cold weather shelter to homeless adults.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;43&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Alzheimer&apos;s Society (Enfield Branch)&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;supporting carers of people with dementia.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;44&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Arab Group in Hounslow and Suburbs&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;supporting the Arab community with an advice service and social activities.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;45&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Centre for Filipinos&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;responding to the needs of Filipinos in the UK and enabling them to participate fully in society.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;46&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Greenwich Chinese Community School&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;advancing education within the Chinese community, understanding Chinese culture and encouraging mutual aid.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;47&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Muslim Women&apos;s Welfare Association&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing help and advice to Asian women in Waltham Forest.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;48&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Neutral Ground Child Contact Centre&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;running a support centre in Abbey Wood, where children of separated families can meet estranged parents.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;49&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Nightshelter Volunteers&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing shelter for homeless people in Newham throughout the winter.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;50&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Sikh Community Care Project&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;developing and facilitating community initiatives in Waltham Forest, particularly for the Sikh community.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/table&gt;&#x000A;&lt;image src="S6CV0406P0I0693"/&gt;&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;13WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;&lt;table&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td colspan="3" align="center"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Winners of the Queen&apos;s Golden Jubilee Award for voluntary service by groups in the community 2003&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Voluntary Group&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Activity Description&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;51&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The XL Project&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;working with and supporting schools, families and communities in South London.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;52&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Wandsworth Community Transport&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;enabling and helping individuals with mobility problems to access facilities in Wandsworth town centre through its shop mobility project&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;North East&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;53&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Ferryhill Town Youth&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;bringing together young people through sporting and other activities.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;54&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Grange Road Methodist Church Resource Centre&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing recreational, leisure and educational activities for people of Hartlepool.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;55&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Quaking Houses Village Hall Association&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing facilities and activities for the community of Stanley.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;56&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Stepney Bank Stables&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;educating and motivating young people from inner-city area and adults with learning difficulties.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;57&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Gateshead Visible Ethnic Minorities Support Group&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;supporting ethnic minority communities and promoting multi- cultural events.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;58&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Northumberland Family Camping Group&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing low-cost family holidays.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;59&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Scotswood Family Drug Support Group&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing support and advice to families of drug misusers in Scotswood.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;60&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;West Harton Churches Action Station Limited&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing advice and education facilities to South Tyneside residents.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;North West&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;61&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Acorn Venture Urban Farm&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;enabling disabled people in Kirkby to become involved in farming and giving young people opportunities to work with animals.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;62&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Advocacy in Wirral&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing support and advocacy to people experiencing mental health problems.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;63&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;CancerCare (North Lancashire and South Lakeland)&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing support, therapy, counselling and practical help for cancer patients and their families.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;64&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Chorlton Good Neighbours&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;offering support, practical help and friendship to those in need in Chorlton.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;65&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Delamere Toy and Tape Library&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing toys and equipment for children up to 8 years and for individuals with special needs.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;66&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;East Cheshire Hospice Volunteers&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;transporting patients, helping in Day Care and helping bereavement counsellors and receptionists.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;67&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Friends for Leisure&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;enabling young people with learning, sensory and physical disabilities in Macclesfield to participate in mainstream leisure activities.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;68&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Halton Child Contact Centre&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;helping children in Runcorn and Widnes in family breakdown to continue or re-establish contact with their non-resident parent or other family members.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;69&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Keswick (Calvert Trust) RDA Helpers Group&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing disabled people opportunities to ride and carriage drive to benefit their health and well being.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;70&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Knutsford and District Good Neighbours&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing transport for patients and providing practical assistance to elderly, disabled and housebound people.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;71&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;MOSAC&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing support, education and advice to parents of abused children in Blackpool, Wyre and Fylde.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;72&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;One Voice/Team 2000&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;improving lives of local residents through urban regeneration, crime prevention and educating young people in community citizenship.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/table&gt;&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;14WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;&lt;table&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td colspan="3" align="center"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Winners of the Queen&apos;s Golden Jubilee Award for voluntary service by groups in the community 2003&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Voluntary Group&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Activity Description&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;73&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Rochdale Childer&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing help and assistance for any Rochdale child in need.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;74&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;South Lakeland Voluntary Society for the Blind&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing practical support, information, advice and social activities to local people with sight problems.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;75&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;St Rocco&apos;s Hospice Volunteers&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing practical help and emotional support, transporting patients and helping with hospice events and fundraising.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;76&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Blackbrook Group and Residents&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;promoting community fire safety through young people in Warrington working with the Fire Service.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;77&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Blackburn Breast Care Support Group&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing support for women who have suffered from or have concerns about breast cancer.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;78&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Friday Club&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing holidays and social activities for adults with learning disabilities in Warrington and giving respite to their carers.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;79&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Littleborough Coach House Trust&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;maintaining a historic listed building for use by local groups and societies.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;80&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Open Door&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing facilities and resources to improve the quality of life for residents of Benchill and to regenerate the area.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;81&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Salford Link Project&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing links between ethnic communities and statutory and voluntary organizations, including promotion of advice and education programmes.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;82&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Standish Friendly Visiting Group&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;befriending elderly and housebound people and those living alone and arranging outings to places of interest.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;83&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Volunteers of Drugline&amp;#x2014;Lancashire&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;supporting people affected by drug use, directly or indirectly, by providing counselling and a telephone helpline.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;84&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Wirral and Chester Riding for the Disabled&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing practical facilities for people with physical or learning difficulties to enjoy horse riding.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Northern Ireland&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;85&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Broughshane and District Community Association&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;enhancing the sense of community ownership and responsibility.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;86&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Lynn Social Club&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing meals on wheels and organizing social and recreational activities for the community of Larne.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;87&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Newtownstewart Development Association&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;promoting economic development through tourism and employment regeneration and providing social and recreational facilities.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;88&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;St John Ambulance HQ Transport Division&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing a volunteer first aid and ambulance service for the community of Northern Ireland.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;89&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Lack Women&apos;s Group&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing recreational classes and training for local women in Lack.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;90&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Samiritans&amp;#x2014;Belfast Branch&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing a 24 hour confidential emotional support service for people experiencing distress or despair.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;91&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Walkway Women&apos;s Group &amp;amp; EBCEC&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing educational, arts and environment opportunities for local women in Belfast&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;92&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Voluntary Service Bureau&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing advice and practical fitting of security devices to older and vulnerable people.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Scotland&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;93&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Arran Lifeline&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing and servicing a telephone activated push button service in elderly and disabled peoples homes.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/table&gt;&#x000A;&lt;image src="S6CV0406P0I0694"/&gt;&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;15WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;&lt;table&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td colspan="3" align="center"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Winners of the Queen&apos;s Golden Jubilee Award for voluntary service by groups in the community 2003&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Voluntary Group&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Activity Description&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;94&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Canine Concern Scotland Trust&amp;#x2014;Therapet Scheme&amp;#x2014; Aberdeen&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing &apos;Therapy Dogs&apos; for people in hospitals, hospices and residential and nursing homes to help those devoid of animal contact.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;95&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Central Gurdware Singh Sabha, Glasgow&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;managing a Sikh community place of worship and providing activities to promote Sikh culture.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;96&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Churches Action for the Homeless&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;running a day centre, accommodation and training centre for the homeless or those at risk of homelessness in Perth and district.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;97&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Drug Initiative Group&amp;#x2014; Forfar&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;running a caf&amp;#x00E9; facility for young people and offering an alternative to drug use and misuse.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;98&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Eighteen and Under&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing information and support to young people in Dundee who have been abused and researching ways of preventing abuse.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;99&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Fife Christian Counselling Centre&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing support and counselling to members of the community.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;100&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Focus Youth Project Management Committee&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;overseeing the running of the Youth Project in Viewpark.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;101&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Glasgow Association of Family Support Groups&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;promoting the development of groups to support and advise parents of drug abusers.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;102&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Home Basics&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;collecting and refurbishing donated furniture and household goods for disadvantaged people in Tweeddale.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;103&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Inverclyde Peace Initiative&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;promoting conflict resolution within the community to make it cohesive and sustainable.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;104&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Islay Disabled Endeavours and Actions&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing care, advocacy, craft working, training and health supervision for individuals with special needs.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;105&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Lanarkshire Cancer Care Trust (The Volunteer Driver Service&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing, a personal hospital transport service for cancer suffers.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;106&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;McSence Limited&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;creating sustainable community owned and run business, employing and training unemployed people of Dalkeith.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;107&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Portlethen &amp;amp; District Community Ambulance Association&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing transport for those unable to attend church, social or health facilities.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;108&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Red Star Athletics Club&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing sporting, recreational and social opportunities for people with disabilities in Glasgow.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;109&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Roseberry Centre&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing support, advisory and counselling services to people with dementia and their families in and around Livingston.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;110&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Drop In&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing social activities, meals and advice for pensioners in Irvine.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;111&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Hit Squad&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;improving the environement in Dawson by enabling elderly and infirm residents to undertake low maintenance gardening and run a community allotment.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;112&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Moorpark Community Association&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing social and educational opportunities and raising funds to improve the local environment.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;South East&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;113&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;777 Conservation Group&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;conserving the environment of Buckinghamshire for the benefit of the public.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;114&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;A New Start For Netherfield Partnership Board&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;attracting and administering funds to transform Netherfield.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;115&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Berinsfield Information and Volunteer Centre&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing advisory services for local people.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/table&gt;&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;16WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;&lt;table&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td colspan="3" align="center"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Winners of the Queen&apos;s Golden Jubilee Award for voluntary service by groups in the community 2003&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Voluntary Group&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Activity Description&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;116&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;CHAIN&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing practical help and information for the people of Hungerford.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;117&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Epsom &amp;amp; Ewell Phab&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;integrating young people with and without physical disabilities.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;118&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Fleet Pond Society&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;promoting the preservation and maintenance of the Fleet Pond Nature Reserve.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;119&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Florence Nightingale House Volunteers&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;enhancing the quality of hospice patients care.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;120&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Folkestone Rainbow Centre&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;supporting the community&apos;s needs physically, spiritually and emotionally.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;121&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Gatehouse&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;a caf&amp;#x00E9; for homeless people in Oxford.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;122&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Hampshire Association for the Care of the Blind&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;supporting Hampshire people who have lost their sight.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;123&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Havant Area Bereavement Care Group&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing help and comfort to bereaved people.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;124&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Katharine House Hospice&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;enhancing the lives of hospice patients and their families.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;125&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Maidenhead Multiple Sclerosis Society&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing a social venue and outings for MS patients.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;126&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Mytchett Community Association&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing a community centre and playing fields to improve the quality of peoples lives.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;127&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Oxford Samaritans&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;offering year round confidential and emotional support for suicidal or desparate people&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;128&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Penrose Club for Adults with Special Needs&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing leisure activities in Surrey and encouraging the independence of it members.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;129&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Phyllis Tuckwell Hospice Volunteers&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing specialist activities and practical support for hospice patients.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;130&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;SEBEV Search and Rescue&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;assisting the authorities in the Thames Valley area, following reports of lost or missing persons.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;131&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Tandem&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing a transport service and a weekly club for elderly and disabled people in Midhurst and Petworth.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;132&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Leatherhead Swans Club&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;helping to provide recreation and leisure facilities for disabled people.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;133&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The V Team&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;enabling people in Maidstone who are ill or have support needs to be successful volunteers.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;134&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Wire&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing programmes to enhance the lives of the people of Wick&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;135&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Working Hospice Volunteer Team&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;helping to provide care for patients and their families&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;136&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Wokingham and West Berkshire Mind&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing support for mental health service users and carers.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;South West&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;137&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Blackdown Support Group&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;supplementing health and social services in the Blackdown Hills by providing care and support services.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;138&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Burnham &amp;amp; Highbridge Stroke Club&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;a social club providing companionship and activities for people who have suffered strokes.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;139&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Cheltenham and District Sports Association for the Disabled&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing swimming instruction and sailing opportunities for disabled people.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;140&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Downderry and District Community Bus Association&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing accessible and inexpensive transport for all local residents and holiday-makers.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;141&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Gloucestershire Chinese Women&apos;s Guild&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing services for socially excluded and isolated Chinese women and their families.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;142&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;North Devon Display Gymnastics Club&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing gymnastics and coaching opportunities for the people of North Devon.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/table&gt;&#x000A;&lt;image src="S6CV0406P0I0695"/&gt;&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;17WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;&lt;table&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td colspan="3" align="center"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Winners of the Queen&apos;s Golden Jubilee Award for voluntary service by groups in the community 2003&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Voluntary Group&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Activity Description&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;143&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Plymouth Musical Activities Club&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing opportunities for young people to learn and perform music to support charitable organizations.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;144&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;St Keverne Youth Band&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing young people with the opportunity to play musical instruments and perform.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;145&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Swindon Children&apos;s Scrapstore&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;promoting recycling by collecting useable waste and donating it to community orgainsations.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;146&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Talaton Village Community Shop &amp;amp; Post Office&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing service to the community and a focal point for village needs.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;147&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Beacon Community Regeneration Partnership&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;regenerating areas of Falmouth, alleviating disadvantages and social exclusion, and providing support services.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;148&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Sheltered Work Opportunities Project&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing horticultural work opportunities for people suffering from mental health problems in Bournemouth.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;149&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Southmead Project Limited&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing education, training, and counselling for individuals and families affected by drug misuse and historic abuse.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;150&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The St James Priory Project&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;supporting homeless people in Bristol with addition problems and facilitating their reintegration into society.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;151&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Trussell Trust&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing food for people in crisis in Wiltshire and augmenting the work of other statutory and voluntary organisations.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;152&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Thorncombe First Responders&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;pioneers of community life support between a &apos;999&apos; emergency call and the arrival of ambulance.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Wales&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;153&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Aberfan and Merthyr Vale Youth and Community Project&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing activities for young and unemployed people.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;154&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Bush and Park Tenants and Residents Association&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;improving the lives of estate residents.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;155&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Grangetown Community Concern&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;acting as an umbrella group for other voluntary organisations.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;156&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Gwynedd Hospice at Home&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;enabling patients to use day Hospice facilities, and supporting Hospice Nurses.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;157&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;North Wales Superkids&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing family holidays and gifts for needy children and young people.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;158&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Ogmore Centre Trust&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing residential courses for young people and a community life- long learning facility for rural residents.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;159&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Perthcelyn Tenants and Residents Association&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;organising social activities and learning opportunities for residents of the Perthcelyn estate.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;160&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Swansea Old People&apos;s Welfare&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;operating four day centres for elderly and housebound people&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;161&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Clwyd Special Riding Trust&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;enabling people with special needs to ride or carriage drive.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;162&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Muslim Welfare Association of Vale of Glamorgan&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;promoting education, art and culture among the ethnic minority community.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;163&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Treasure Trove&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing a residential project for young people aged 16 to 25 years both with and without physical disabilities.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;164&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Tyddyn Bach Trust&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;caring for and supporting those affected by HIV and Aids, and their families and carers in the UK.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;West Midlands&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;165&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Harborne Carnival Association&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;promoting and organising an annual carnival to improve community spirit and support local charities.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/table&gt;&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;18WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;&lt;table&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td colspan="3" align="center"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Winners of the Queen&apos;s Golden Jubilee Award for voluntary service by groups in the community 2003&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Voluntary Group&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Activity Description&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;166&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;OSCA&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing volunteers to support and represent people with learning difficulties throughout Shropshire.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;167&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Perry Hall Community Association&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing entertainment, holidays and exercise for residents of Perry Barr, Birmingham.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;168&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Pershore Pathfinders&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing social activities for blind and partially sighted people.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;169&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Rock Community Bus&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing educational, leisure and play activities to socially and economically disadvantaged communities in Birmingham.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;170&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;S.H.A.R.P. Peer Education&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;informing young people in Sandwell and Dudley of the dangers of leaving home unplanned and how to access support.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;171&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Shifnal Millennium Sensory Garden Committee&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;creating and maintaining a sensory garden for the community, especially elderly and disabled people.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;172&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;St Michael&apos;s Hospice&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing specialist palliative care for people form Herefordshire and surrounding counties and support for family and friends.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;173&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Stepping Stones Support Limited&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing support, advice and information to women experiencing domestic violence in Walsall.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;174&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Age Concern Stourbridge&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing services for the elderly including day care facilities and transport&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;175&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;T.S. Sutton Coldfield&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;guiding young people towards responsible and confident adulthood by encouraging personal attributes and conduct.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;176&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Asian Blind Association&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing advice and counselling for blind and partially sighted people, and their carers, in Coventry.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;177&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Rose Staner Friendship Club&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;offering friendship and support to elderly visually impaired people living alone in Coventry.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;178&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Royal Orthopaedic Hospital League of Friends Volunteers&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing support to patients, hospital management and staff.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;179&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Stonehouse Gang&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing activities for pre-school and school children, youths and senior citizens in Selly Oak.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;180&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Watch Limited&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;a community-led organisation, working to improve the quality of life for people in Hillfields.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;181&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Wetton and Alstonefield Community First Responders&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing emergency medical aid in response to &apos;999&apos; calls from remote areas.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;182&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Wolverhampton Asian Women and Diabetes Group&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing support and information about diabetes to Asian women.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;183&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Wolverhampton Support for Deafened People&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing a battery and repair service for hearing aid users.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;184&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Wolverhampton Urdu Centre&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing information, advice and linguistic services in Asian languages.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Yorkshire and the Humber&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;185&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Crosby Community Association&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;running a drop-in centre, neighbourhood watches, children&apos;s groups and an outreach service.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;186&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;FLAG&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing support and respite care to families of children with disabilities.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;187&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Friend to Friend&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing activities for the elderly people of Holme Valley.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;188&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Hornsea Inshore Rescue&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;rescuing those in difficulties at sea and promoting water safety.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;189&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Manor Young People&apos;s Health Project&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;educating and advising the young in Sheffield on health issues.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/table&gt;&#x000A;&lt;image src="S6CV0406P0I0696"/&gt;&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;19WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;&lt;table&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td colspan="3" align="center"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Winners of the Queen&apos;s Golden Jubilee Award for voluntary service by groups in the community 2003&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Voluntary Group&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Activity Description&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;190&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Sheffield Cathedral Breakfast &amp;amp; Archer Projects&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;supporting the homeless by providing education, breakfasts, shower and laundry facilities.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;191&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Community Care Association-Stockesley&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;promoting voluntary action and developing projects with service users and carers.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;192&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The British Fishermen&apos;s Association&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;achieved compensation for distant water trawler men in Hull.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;193&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Friends of Paces&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;supporting the local community of Sheffield and children with cerebral palsy by generating funds.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;194&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Goodwill Motorists&apos; Friendship Group&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;organising year-round, fun-filled gatherings for housebound (infirm, blind and/or bereaved) people, sponsored and entertained by groups in North East Lincolnshire.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;195&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Junction&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing support, education and advice to people in Harrogate with a wide range of special needs.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;196&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Longhill Link Up Trust&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing services and activities for those living on the Longhill Housing Estate.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;197&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Manor Farm, Monkswood, Thorogate Community Centre&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;maintaining the community centre and providing activities for the local people.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;198&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Safe Anchor Trust&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;giving special needs groups free access to waterways, and maintaining the canal environment in West Yorkshire.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;199&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Upper Wharfedale Fell Rescue Association&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;providing a rescue service for people and animals above and below ground in the Yorkshire Dales.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;200&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;York Students in Schools&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;introducing students from the University of York to Classrooms in York to help teachers and children.&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/p&gt;' title='Golden Jubilee Awards' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jun/04/golden-jubilee-awards'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3543375' text='DEPUTY PRIME MINISTER'>
      <outline id='3543376' text='The Minister for Local Government and the Regions (Mr. Nick Raynsford)&lt;p&gt;I can confirm that a note on the policy intent with regard to clause 71 of the Local Government Bill was available in the House Libraries on 29 May 2003 in advance of Committee consideration of the Bill in another place. Copies were also sent to Baroness Hanham and Baroness Hamwee. In addition, copies of the revised draft regulations for Part 1 of the Bill and the first draft of the regulations with regard to the 2004 local government elections provisions of the Bill, together with the draft guidance for the new charging provisions currently out to consultation.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Local Government Bill' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jun/04/local-government-bill'></outline>
      <outline id='3543377' text="The Deputy Prime Minister (Mr. John Prescott)&lt;p&gt;The Fire Brigades' Union Executive Council and the National Employers have reached an agreement which will be put to a recall conference on 12 June. As a result I am pleased to announce that the Armed Forces personnel deployed on firefighting duties have been stood down during the run up to the conference.&lt;/p&gt;" title="Firefighters' Dispute" type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jun/04/firefighters-dispute'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3543380' text='TREASURY'>
      <outline id='3543381' text="The Economic Secretary to the Treasury (John Healey)&lt;p&gt;On 9 December 2002, HM Customs and Excise and the US Customs Service signed a Declaration of Principles to implement the US Container Security Initiative (CSI) in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CSI is an important intelligence sharing partnership designed to make the movement of terrorist material, in sea containers to the US, more difficult.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Guidelines on the practical operation of CSI have been agreed between the two services and four US Customs and Border Protection Agency officers will, this week, commence work at the UK's largest sea container port of Felixstowe.&lt;/p&gt;" title='Container Security Initiative' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jun/04/container-security-initiative'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3543382' text='NORTHERN IRELAND'>
      <outline id='3543383' text="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Northern Ireland (Mr. Desmond Browne)&lt;p&gt;Stage One of the Quinqennial Review of the Northern Ireland Health and Social Services Estates Agency has been completed. The report has been made available to the House of Commons and the Northern Ireland Assembly's Libraries and on the Department of Health Social Services and Public Safety's website.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The purpose of Stage One was to establish whether there was a continuing need for the services provided by the Northern Ireland Health and Social Services Estates Agency and, if so, to consider a range of options for delivering those services.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The views of a wide range of stakeholders and interest groups including some from outside Northern Ireland were considered. These included Northern Ireland Public Service Alliance (NIPSA) and HPSS Boards Trusts and Agencies, political parties and Northern Ireland Local Government Association (NILGA). Various options for delivering the services&amp;#x2014;such as privatisation, contracting out/market testing, merger with another public body or reallocation of services to another public body&amp;#x2014;were considered. The review concluded that there was a continuing need for the services provided by the Northern Ireland Health and Social Services Estates Agency and that agency status remained the best value for money option for delivering them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Stage Two of the review, which will begin shortly, will examine how the agency operates and make recommendations for how delivery of its services might be improved. I will inform the House of the outcome in due course.&lt;/p&gt;" title='Quinqennial Review' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jun/04/quinqennial-review'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3543384' text='TRANSPORT'>
      <outline id='3543385' text='The Secretary of State for Transport (Mr. Alistair Darling)&lt;p&gt;I intend, subject to the passage of the Railways and Transport Safety Bill currently before Parliament, to transfer London Underground to Transport for London on or about 15 July 2003.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;image src="S6CV0406P0I0697"/&gt;&lt;col&gt;21WS&lt;/col&gt;&lt;p&gt;In my written statement of 4 February 2003 I said that the Government, Transport for London and the Mayor had agreed to work together to secure the transfer of the London Underground to TfL as soon as possible after the completion of the London Underground Public Private Partnerships (PPP). I also said that I would continue with the proposed amendments to the Greater London Authority Act 1999 as set out in the Railways and Transport Safety Bill. These amendments will ensure that the operation of London Underground&apos;s contracts is not affected when they are transferred from one body to another. In order to achieve this, the amendments in the Railways and Transport Safety Bill must be in force before the relevant provisions in the contracts transfer to TfL.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The remaining London Underground PPP contracts came into effect on 4 April 2003. The Railways and Transport Safety Bill has so far made good progress through Parliament. It is now in everyone&apos;s interest to set a target date to ensure an early and orderly transfer of London Underground. Subject to the continued good progress of the Railways and Transport Safety Bill through the House, I therefore intend to transfer London Underground to Transport for London on or about 15 July.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Transfer of London Underground to Transport for London will give effect to the policy originally set out in the Greater London Authority Act, and enable the investment that has already begun under the PPP to continue under the framework envisaged by the Act.&lt;/p&gt;' title='London Underground' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jun/04/london-underground'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3543386' text='TRADE AND INDUSTRY'>
      <outline id='3543387' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Trade and Industry (Miss Melanie Johnson)&lt;p&gt;I am pleased to announce that in the light of a strong performance outturn by the Insolvency Service in 2002&amp;#x2013;03 I have been able to reconsider the targets set for the current year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the basis of an expected outturn of 83 per cent. in the User Satisfaction Index I set the agency a target for 2003&amp;#x2013;04 of a satisfaction level of 84 per cent. I am pleased to report that the final outturn for 2002&amp;#x2013;03 was in fact 85 per cent. and I have therefore increased the target for 2003&amp;#x2013;04 to 86 per cent.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Similarly in the disqualification area, on the basis that the outturn for the average time taken to conclude disqualification proceedings would be 25.4 months I set the agency a target of 25 months for the current year. In fact the outturn was 24.3 months and I have therefore set the agency a target of 24 months for the current year. Also in the disqualification area the projected achievement against the percentage of cases concluded within 24 and 30 months was 43 per cent. and 82 per cent. respectively and I therefore set targets for this year of 45 per cent. and 84 per cent. In fact performance was 58 per cent. and 84 per cent. and I have therefore set increased targets of 60 per cent. and 85 per cent.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;col&gt;22WS&lt;/col&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finally 81 per cent. of redundancy claims were actioned within six weeks against a target of 80 per cent. and I have therefore set a new target of 82 per cent. for the current year.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Insolvency Service Performance Targets 200304' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jun/04/insolvency-service-performance-targets'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3543388' text='FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH AFFAIRS'>
      <outline id='3543389' text="The Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs (Mr. Jack Straw)&lt;p&gt;The search for a comprehensive settlement to the Cyprus Problem has been and remains a high priority for the Government. For seven years, our contribution has been led with great distinction by Lord Hannay as Special Representative for Cyprus. But in the light of recent developments, we have been reviewing the arrangements for ensuring an active British input into Cyprus diplomacy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;My right hon. Friend the Prime Minister and I have therefore accepted Lord Hannay's recommendation that his term should end with effect from the date of this announcement, and I have decided, for the time being at least, not to make any further appointment of this kind. Lord Hannay has worked with enormous professionalism and dedication, in support of the United Nations, to bring peace, security and prosperity to Cyprus in the form of a comprehensive settlement to enable a reunited Cyprus to join the European Union in 2004. Lord Hannay's support and advice during his time as Special Representative&amp;#x2014;invaluable here in London, but also singled out for praise by the UN Secretary-General and many of our international partners&amp;#x2014;have brought this country great credit.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The UN process culminated in the second revision of the Plan which the UN Secretary-General presented to the parties on 26 February, and in negotiations which reached a climax in The Hague on 11 March this year. For reasons set out in the subsequent report by the UN Secretary-General and endorsed in UN Security Council Resolution 1475, this final effort ended in failure, for which the Turkish Cypriot leader, Mr Denktash, bore the prime responsibility. It is the British Government's firm view that the Annan Plan remains the best way forward. We also concur with the Secretary-General's judgement that he should not take a new initiative unless and until he is given solid reason by all the parties to believe that the political will necessary for a successful outcome exists and that they are prepared to commit to finalising the Plan by a specific date and to putting it to separate simultaneous referenda on a date soon thereafter.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The House will understand that this announcement in no way indicates a weakening of the Government's determination to work with others under the aegis of the UN to find a solution to the Cyprus Problem. Should events again make it appropriate for a Special Representative to be appointed, the Government will not hesitate to do so.&lt;/p&gt;" title='Cyprus' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jun/04/cyprus'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3543391' text='HEALTH'>
      <outline id='3543392' text="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Health (Mr. David Lammy)&lt;p&gt;The system of patient and public involvement in the National Health Service that will be in place from 1 September provides far greater support for patients than ever before.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By 1 September the programme of work to set up patients' forums will be well under way and the support for them will be in place to provide. a one-stop shop for information and advice; the Commission for Patient and Public Involvement in Health (CPPIH) will be representing the patients voice nationally; local authority overview and scrutiny committees will be scrutinising the NHS; the NHS itself will be carrying out its new duty to involve and consult the public; there will be independent support for complainants; there will be support for patients from PALS (Patient Advice and Liaison Service) in almost all trusts; there will be a national help line set up by CPPIH that will provide advice, information and signposting for the public about where to get advice and support; and there will be monitoring of the NHS by the Commission for Health Improvement and by Patient Environment Action Teams.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Government have been consistent in their drive to ensure accessible and informed support for patients; provide for the independent scrutiny by democratically elected representatives; and, ensure that the views and experiences of patients are fed into decisions affecting their health and health services. Massive progress has already been made.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have listened to Parliamentarians and other stakeholders, including the CPPIH, and we are responding positively to comments around the specific issue of independent monitoring of the NHS during the transition period.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have therefore decided to make the position absolutely unassailable by retaining Community Health Councils to continue their monitoring function until 1 December, at which point all patient forums will be in place to take up this role. Sharon Grant, Chair of CPPIH, has stated that this decision allows an important breathing space to help ensure a smooth handover to the new system of Patient and Public Involvement Forums in December.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;All CHC staff and members have been sent a letter advising them of the change of arrangements.&lt;/p&gt;" title='NHS' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jun/04/nhs'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3543393' text='WORK AND PENSIONS'>
      <outline id='3543394' text="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Work and Pensions (Malcolm Wicks)&lt;p&gt;On behalf of my right hon. Friend the Secretary of State for Work and Pensions, the Benefit Fraud Inspectorate (BFI) inspection report on Basingstoke and Deane Borough Council was published on Wednesday 28 May 2003 and copies of the report have been placed in the Library.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In its response to the Housing Green Paper of November 2000, the Department for Work and Pensions developed a performance framework for housing benefits. The Performance Standards for housing benefit allow local authorities to make a comprehensive self-assessment of whether they deliver benefit effectively and securely. They are standards the Department for Work and Pensions aspires to and expects local authorities to achieve in time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The BFI inspected Basingstoke and Deane Borough Council against the Performance Standards. The report finds that the council is not at Standard for any of the seven functional areas of the Performance Standards&amp;#x2014;strategic management, customer services, processing of claims, working with landlords, internal security, counter-fraud, and overpayments.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The report finds a number of weaknesses in the council's procedures and performance. A focus on paying benefit quickly, due to the council's strategy to support vulnerable people, meant that benefit had been paid without the necessary controls in place. The emphasis on paying benefit quickly has caused poor adherence to the Verification Framework, adopted by the council in April 1999.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The quality of the council's counter-fraud activity was inconsistent and in some instances did not adhere to legal requirements. The council's Housing Benefit debt was not being managed, and the council did not use all of the recovery methods available to it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The report finds some clear strengths in the customer services offered by the council which had developed good working relationships with its major landlords and Housing Associations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 2001&amp;#x2013;02, Basingstoke and Deane Borough Council administered approximately &amp;#x00A3;22 million in housing benefits, approximately 22 per cent. of its total gross revenue expenditure.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The report makes recommendations to help the council address weaknesses and to further improve the administration of Housing Benefit and Council Tax Benefit, as well as counter-fraud activities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;My right hon. Friend the Secretary of State is now considering the report and will be asking the council for its proposals in response to the findings and recommendations of the BFI.&lt;/p&gt;" title='Basingstoke and Deane Borough Council' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jun/04/basingstoke-and-deane-borough-council'></outline>
    </outline>
  </body>
</opml>
