<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Lords Report of 21 March 1935</title>
    <dateCreated>Thu, 21 Mar 1935 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='2265940' text='Petition of the London County Council under their Common Seal, praying for leave to introduce a Bill to amend the London Building Act, 1930; together with a copy of the proposed Bill annexed thereto: Read and referred to the Examiners.' title='LONDON BUILDING ACT (AMENDMENT).' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1935/mar/21/london-building-act-amendment'></outline>
    <outline id='2265941' text="The King's consent signified; and Bill reported, with Amendments." title='SALTBURN AND MARSKE-BY-THE- SEA URBAN DISTRICT COUNCIL BILL.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1935/mar/21/saltburn-and-marske-by-the-sea-urban'></outline>
    <outline id='2265942' text='OXFORD CANAL BILL.&lt;br/&gt;ROCHDALE CANAL BILL.&lt;br/&gt;WEAVER NAVIGATION BILL.&lt;br/&gt;Reported without amendment.' title='COVENTRY CANAL NAVIGATION BILL.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1935/mar/21/coventry-canal-navigation-bill'></outline>
    <outline id='2265943' text="WEYMOUTH AND MELCOMBE REGIS CORPORATION BILL. [H.L.]&lt;br/&gt;Report from the Committee of Selection, That the following Lords be proposed to the House to form the Select Committee for the consideration of the said Bills; namely:&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;E. Poulett,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;E. Macclesfield,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;E. Mount Edgcumbe,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;V. Gough,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Cozens-Hardy (Chairman):&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/ul&gt;&#x000A;Agreed to; and the said Lords appointed accordingly. The Committee to meet on Tuesday, the 9th of April next, at eleven o'clock; and all Petitions referred to the Committee, with leave to the Petitioners praying to be heard by Counsel against the Bills to be heard as desired, as also Counsel for the Bills." title='SWANSEA AND DISTRICT TRANSPORT BILL. [H.L.]' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1935/mar/21/swansea-and-district-transport-bill-hl'></outline>
    <outline id='2265944' text='Report from the Special Orders Committee, That they have examined the&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;320&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;Order as required by the Standing Orders of the House:&lt;br/&gt;That in their opinion the Order raises questions of policy and principle which have been in part accepted already by the House when passing the Agricultural Marketing Act, 1933, under which the Order is submitted for approval:&lt;br/&gt;That the Order is founded on precedent, inasmuch as other Orders have been submitted for the approval of Parliament under the Act, although those Orders dealt with other agricultural products;&lt;br/&gt;That in the opinion of the Committee the Order can be passed by the House without special attention, subject to any arguments on the merits which may arise in debate, and that no further inquiry is necessary before the House proceeds to a decision on the Resolution to approve the said Order.&lt;br/&gt;Read, and ordered to lie on the Table.' title='PORK (IMPORT REGULATION) ORDER, 1935.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1935/mar/21/pork-import-regulation-order-1935'></outline>
    <outline id='2265946' text='ROMFORD GAS ORDER, 1935.&lt;br/&gt;Report from the Special Orders Committee, That no Petition has been presented praying to be heard against the Special Orders, and that there is nothing in these Orders to which they think it necessary to call the attention of the House:&lt;br/&gt;Read, and ordered to lie on the Table.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;MINISTRY OF HEALTH PROVISIONAL ORDER (COUNTY OF HOLLAND JOINT HOSPITAL DISTRICT) BILL.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;MINISTRY OF HEALTH PROVISIONAL ORDER (GUISBOROUGH JOINT SMALLPOX HOSPITAL DISTRICT) BILL.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;MINISTRY OF HEALTH PROVISIONAL ORDER (HUNTINGDONSHIRE JOINT HOSPITAL DISTRICT) BILL.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;MINISTRY OF HEALTH PROVISIONAL ORDER (SOUTH CHILTERNS JOINT SMALLPOX HOSPITAL DISTRICT) BILL.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Reported, without amendment, and re-committed to a Committee of the Whole House on Tuesday next.' title='LEEDS GAS ORDER, 1935.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1935/mar/21/leeds-gas-order-1935'></outline>
  </body>
</opml>
