<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Lords Report of 20 March 1928</title>
    <dateCreated>Tue, 20 Mar 1928 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='2249065' text="Petition of William Selby-Lowndes, of Whaddon Hall, in the County of Buckingham, Esquire, O.B.E., claiming to be one of the co-heirs of the ancient Baronies of Montacute and Monthermer, praying His Majesty to determine in his favour the abeyance now existing in the said Baronies, and in case it should be found that the said Baronies are affected by the attainder of Margaret Countess of Salisbury or any other of the attainders referred to in the said Petition, to be graciously pleased to give directions for the introduction of a Bill into Parliament to relieve the Petitioner from the effect or effects of the said attainder or attainders as aforesaid, in so far as it relates or they relate to the said honours and dignities of Montacute and Monthermer respectively, together with His Majesty's reference thereof to this House, and the report of the Attorney-General thereunto annexed: Presented (by command); read, and referred to the Committee for Privileges to consider and report.&lt;br/&gt;The Lord Rotherham&amp;#x2014;Sat first in Parliament after the death of his father.&lt;br/&gt;The LORD SPEAKER acquainted the House, that the Clerk of the Parliaments had laid upon the Table the Certificates from the Examiners that the further Standing Orders applicable to the following Bills have been complied with:&lt;br/&gt;Barnet District Gas and Water.&lt;br/&gt;Sunderland Corporation.&lt;br/&gt;The same were ordered to lie on the Table." title='BARONIES OF MONTACUTE AND MONTHERMER.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1928/mar/20/baronies-of-montacute-and-monthermer'></outline>
    <outline id='2249068' text='Report from the Select Committee, That the Committee had not proceeded with the consideration of the Bill, no parties having appeared in opposition thereto: Read, and ordered to lie on the&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;534&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;Table: The Orders made on the 21st of February last and the 1st instant discharged, and Bill committed.' title='SANDOWN URBAN DISTRICT COUNCIL BILL. [H.L.]' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1928/mar/20/sandown-urban-district-council-bill-hl'></outline>
    <outline id='2249070' text='A witness ordered to attend the Select Committee.' title='PLYMPTON ST. MARY RURAL DISTRICT COUNCIL BILL. [H.L.]' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1928/mar/20/plympton-st-mary-rural-district-council'></outline>
    <outline id='2249072' text='Reported, with Amendments.' title='GOVERNMENTS STOCK AND OTHER SECURITIES INVESTMENT COMPANY BILL. [H.L.]' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1928/mar/20/governments-stock-and-other-securities'></outline>
    <outline id='2249073' text='Reported, with an Amendment.' title='HARWICH HARBOUR BILL. [H.L.]' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1928/mar/20/harwich-harbour-bill-hl'></outline>
    <outline id='2249074' text='&lt;b&gt;POOLE CORPORATION BILL. [H.L.]&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;GLOUCESTER CORPORATION BILL. [H.L.]&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;WEALD ELECTRICITY SUPPLY BILL. [H.L.]&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;WHITBY WATER BILL. [H.L.]&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Report from the Committee of Selection, That the Earl of Cranbrook be proposed to the House as a member of the Select Committee on the said Bills in the place of the Lord Biddulph: Read, and agreed to.' title='BLACKPOOL IMPROVEMENT BILL. [H.L.]' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1928/mar/20/blackpool-improvement-bill-hl'></outline>
    <outline id='2249077' text="&lt;b&gt;GREENOCK AND PORT GLASGOW TRAMWAYS COMPANY BILL. [H.L.]&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;LEWES WATER BILL [H.L.]&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;CLEETHORPES URBAN DISTRICT COUNCIL BILL. [H.L.]&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;BOURNEMOUTIL GAS AND WATER BILL. [H.L.]&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;YORK TOWN AND BLACKWATER GAS AND ELECTRICITY BILL. [H.L.]&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;DOVER HARBOUR BILL. [H.L.]&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;WEY VALLEY WATER BILL. [H.L.]&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Report from the Committee of Selection, That the following Lords be proposed to the House to form the Select Committee for the consideration of the said Bills; namely:&amp;#x2014;&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;E. Spencer,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;E. Liverpool,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Wharton,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Kintore (&lt;i&gt;E. Kintore&lt;/i&gt;) (Chairman),&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Lawrence;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Agreed to; and the said Lords appointed accordingly: The Committee to meet on Wednesday, the 25th of April next, at eleven o'clock; and all Petitions referred to the Committee, with leave to the Petitioners praying to be heard by Counsel against the Bills to be heard as desired, as also Counsel for the Bills." title='NOTTINGHAMSHIRE AND DERBYSHIRE TRAMWAYS (TROLLEY VEHICLES, &amp;c.) BILL. [H.L.]' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1928/mar/20/nottinghamshire-and-derbyshire-tramways'></outline>
    <outline id='2249078' text="Report from the Committee of Selection, That the following Lords be proposed to the House to form the Select Committee to join with the Select Committee of the House of Commons for the consideration of the London, Midland and Scottish Railway (Road Transport) Bill, the Great Western Railway (Road Transport) Bill, the London and North Eastern Railway (Road Transport) Bill, the Metropolitan Railway (Road Transport) Bill, the Southern Railway (Road Transport.) Bill, the London, Midland and Scottish Railway (Road Transport, Scotland) Bill and the London and North Eastern Railway (Road Transport, Scotland) Bill, namely:&amp;#x2014;&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;E. Russell,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;V. Chelmsford,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Loch.&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;536&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Ruthven of Gowrie,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Darling;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Agreed to; and the said Lords appointed accordingly: Ordered, That such Committee have power to agree with the Committee of the House of Commons in the appointment of a Chairman.&lt;br/&gt;Then a Message was ordered to be sent to the House of Commons in answer to their Message of the 15th instant, to inform them of the appointment of the said Committee by this House, and to propose that the Joint Committee do meet in the Grand Committee Room, Westminster Hall, on Thursday the 26th of April next, at eleven o'clock." title='RAILWAY (ROAD TRANSPORT) BILLS.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1928/mar/20/railway-road-transport-bills'></outline>
    <outline id='2249079' text='Special Order proposed to be made on the application of the Otley Gas Company:&lt;br/&gt;Laid before the House (pursuant to Act) and referred to the Special Orders Committee.' title='OTLEY GAS ORDER, 1928.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1928/mar/20/otley-gas-order-1928'></outline>
    <outline id='2249080' text='&lt;b&gt;NEWCASTLE-UPON-TYNE AND GATESHEAD GAS ORDER, 1928.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;SOUTHEND-ON-SEA AND DISTRICT GAS ORDER, 1928.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;ANNFIELD PLAIN AND DISTRICT GAS ORDER, 1928.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Report from the Special Orders Committee, That no Petition has been presented praying to be heard against the Special Orders, and that there is nothing in these Orders to which they think it necessary to call the attention of the House: Read, and ordered to lie on the Table.' title='ILKLEY GAS ORDER, 1928.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1928/mar/20/ilkley-gas-order-1928'></outline>
  </body>
</opml>
