<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Written Statement of 23 October 2003</title>
    <dateCreated>Thu, 23 Oct 2003 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='3605791' text='SOLICITOR-GENERAL'>
      <outline id='3605792' text="The Solicitor-General (Ms Harriet Harman)&lt;p&gt;The Treasury Solicitor's Annual Report and Accounts 2002&amp;#x2013;2003 have today been published and laid before Parliament. Copies have been placed in the Libraries of both Houses.&lt;/p&gt;" title="Treasury Solicitor's Annual Report" type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/oct/23/treasury-solicitors-annual-report'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3605793' text='HOME DEPARTMENT'>
      <outline id='3605794' text='The Minister for Citizenship and Immigration (Beverley Hughes)&lt;p&gt;On 17 June I announced the introduction of UK residence permits and in parallel to this the introduction of an entry clearance requirement for all persons who want to stay in the UK for more than six months. The entry clearance requirement is being gradually phased in over a two year period. The first phase will require nationals of 10 specified countries to obtain entry clearance from 13 November.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have now decided to expand further the scope of the entry clearance requirement in order to streamline procedures for work permit holders. With effect from 13 November all work permit holders and training and work experience scheme (TWES) permit holders who wish to stay in the UK for more than six months should obtain entry clearance before travelling. This will enable these permit holders to be granted their full period of stay in the UK, as stated on their work permit, before they arrive here, saving them from needing to make a further application for stay shortly after arrival.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There will be a grace period for work permit and TWES permit holders until 23.59 on 13 January 2004 to ensure that those who are not aware of these new arrangements are not unduly inconvenienced on arrival in the UK. During this grace period if a work permit holder arrives in the UK without entry clearance, and would qualify for entry except for the absence of the necessary entry clearance, they will be admitted for a period of six months. During that time they will be able to apply for an extension of stay for a period up to the length of their work permit. This application will not require an accompanying second work permit application to be made by a UK employer.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Immigration Procedures (Work Permit Holders)' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/oct/23/immigration-procedures-work-permit'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3605795' text='DEFENCE'>
      <outline id='3605796' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Defence (Mr. Ivor Caplin)&lt;p&gt;Further to the written answer to the House by my right hon. Friend the Prime Minister on 11 June 2003,&lt;i&gt;Official Report,&lt;/i&gt; column 869W, I am&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;46WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;pleased to announce that Her Majesty The Queen has graciously agreed to the institution of the naval general service medal 1915 to 1962 and the general service medal 1918 to 1962 with the new clasp "Canal Zone" for service in the Suez Canal Zone. Command Paper No. 5999 is laid before Parliament today detailing the criteria for this award. My Department&apos;s medal offices will now commence the award to eligible Suez veterans.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Individuals who served in the Canal Zone during the early 1950s, or their next of kin, are invited to write to the appropriate medal office providing their name, date of birth and service number. The addresses of the medal offices are as follows:&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Royal Naval Medal Office, Room 1068, Centurion Building, Grange Road, Gosport, Hampshire P013 9XA.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote &gt;Royal Marines Medal Office, Room 038, Centurion Building, Grange Road, Gosport, Hampshire P013 9XA.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Army Medal Office, Government Buildings, Worcester Road, Droitwich Spa, Worcestershire WR9 8AU.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Royal Air Force Medal Office, Room 6, Building 248A, RAF PMA, RAF Innsworth, Gloucester, Gloucestershire GL3 1EZ.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Civilian Honours Unit, Room 462, St Giles Court, 1&amp;#x2013;13 St Giles High Street, London WC2H 8LD.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Royal Fleet Auxiliary Medal Office, SOS R FA CS1A, Room F11, Lancelot Building, PP29, HM Naval Base, Portsmouth, Hampshire P01 3NH.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;' title='Suez Medal' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/oct/23/suez-medal'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3605797' text='FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH AFFAIRS'>
      <outline id='3605798' text='The Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs (Mr. Jack Straw)&lt;p&gt;Together with my French and German colleagues I visited Tehran on 21 October for discussions on Iran&apos;s nuclear programme. We met President Khatami, Foreign Minister Kharrazi and the Secretary of the Supreme National Security Committee Hassan Rouhani. Our discussions were aimed at underlining to the Iranian authorities the concerns of the international community regarding Iran&apos;s nuclear ambitions, and the necessity for Iran to comply fully with the requirements of the international atomic energy agency (IAEA) board of governors&apos; resolution adopted on 12 September.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By the end of our visit, we were able to agree a joint statement, which committed Iran to comply with the three key elements of the IAEA board resolution:&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;to engage in full co-operation with the IAEA to address and resolve, through full transparency, all requirements and outstanding issues of the agency, and clarify and correct any possible failures and deficiencies within the IAEA;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;to sign the IAEA additional protocol, and commence ratification procedures. As a confirmation of its good intentions, the Iranian Government states that it would continue to co-operate with the Agency in accordance with the Protocol in advance of its ratification:&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;to suspend all uranium enrichment and reprocessing activities, as defined by the IAEA.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I will place the full text of the joint statement in the Library of the House today.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;image src="S6CV0411P0I0651"/&gt;&lt;col&gt;47WS&lt;/col&gt;&lt;p&gt;This joint statement represents a good start to the process of resolving international concerns over Iran&apos;s nuclear programme and we welcomed it as such. But we also made clear to our Iranian interlocutors that the real test will be full and early implementation of the commitments they have offered. They know that the international community will be looking closely at the evidence in the next report of the IAEA director-general, which is due to be presented to the board of governors in early November.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The joint statement makes clear that, while implementation of the steps outlined should enable the IAEA board to resolve the immediate problem with&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;48WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;Iran, there is also a longer-term issue. Britain, France and Germany remain ready to address that issue through dialogue with Iran on a basis for longer term co-operation, which would provide all parties with satisfactory assurances about Iran&apos;s nuclear power generation programme. We made clear that it is only once international concerns are fully resolved that Iran could expect easier access to modern technology and supplies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The visit has demonstrated the value of a united approach between Britain, France and Germany, working to uphold the decisions of the IAEA and its board of governors, and consistent with the common approach to Iran agreed by several European Councils.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Iran' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/oct/23/iran'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3605810' text='NORTHERN IRELAND'>
      <outline id='3605811' text='The Minister of State, Northern Ireland Office (Mr. John Spellar)&lt;p&gt;A review of sex offences in Northern Ireland is being undertaken by officials in the Northern Ireland Office. The review follows on from proposed changes to the law on sex offences in England and Wales, and is looking at ways to achieve a strengthened and modernised body of law on sexual offences in Northern Ireland.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The terms of reference for the review are:&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;"To review the sex offences in the common and statute law in Northern Ireland, and make recommendations that will:&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;provide coherent and clear sex offences which protect individuals, especially children and the more vulnerable, from abuse and exploitation; enable offenders, particularly abusive offenders, to be appropriately punished; and&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;be fair and non-disrciminatory in accordance with the ECHR, Human Rights Act and the Northern Ireland Act 1998."&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The review will seek to adopt, and adapt to the Northern Ireland context, much of the work undertaken in the Home Office review of sex offences. It will also take into account proposed reform of the law in England and Wales resulting from the Sexual Offences Bill currently before this House. It is our intention to draw upon the knowledge and experience of interested groups and to issue a consultation document in early 2004. Our aim is to introduce legislation in the 2004&amp;#x2013;05 parliamentary session.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Sex Offences Review' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/oct/23/sex-offences-review'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3605812' text='DEFENCE'>
      <outline id='3605813' text="The Minister of State, Ministry of Defence (Mr. Adam Ingram)&lt;p&gt;The first stage of the Quinquennial Review (QQR) of the Oil and Pipelines Agency (OPA), an Executive Non-Departmental Public Body (NDPB), has been completed. The review focused on the OPA and its role as managing agent of the Government Pipeline and Storage System (GPSS).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Stage 1 report found general satisfaction in the performance of the OPA since its inception and that customers both military and commercial were generally content with its stewardship of the GPSS. The report also established that there is a continuing need for the GPSS and hence for it to be managed. Having established this need, the review concluded that the OPA was best placed to discharge this role and, after examining a range of alternative status options for the OPA, considered that it should continue to operate as an NDPB for the present time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;col&gt;16WS&lt;/col&gt;&lt;p&gt;The review also concluded that there were a number of improvements that should be taken forward into Stage 2 of the review, the most significant of which are:&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Developing the 0PA's Management and Business Plans.&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Revising the Managing Agency Agreement between my right hon. Friend the Secretary of State for Defence and the OPA.&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Revising arrangements for corporate governance.&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Reviewing the OPA support structure and communications.&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have given my endorsement to the report's recommendations and Stage 2 is now underway with the aim of completing this work by the end of 2003. A copy of the Executive Summary of the QQR Stage 1 report has been placed in the Library of the House.&lt;/p&gt;" title='Oil and Pipelines Agency' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/oct/23/oil-and-pipelines-agency'></outline>
      <outline id='3605814' text='The Minister of State, Ministry of Defence (Mr. Adam Ingram)&lt;p&gt;Key Targets have been set for the Chief Executive of the Warship Support Agency for financial year 2003&amp;#x2013;04. The targets build on progress already made and are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Key Target 1: Quantity&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To meet the 100 per cent. available vessel days target.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Key Target 2: Timeliness&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To meet the &amp;#x003C;6.5 per cent. upkeep period timeliness target.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Key Target 3: Timeliness&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To achieve the 95 per cent. target for timely completion of the high priority upgrade programme.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Key Target 4: Quality&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To achieve the Operational Support Services target of providing the appropriate standard of single living accommodation to 35 per cent. of naval personnel.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Key Target 5: Quality&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To achieve the Operational Support Services target of meeting the Customers Needs ISO Quality Control Comment Form targets, as follows:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Group 1&amp;#x2013;0 failures Group 2&amp;#x2013;0 failures&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Group 3 &amp;#x003C;5 per cent. failure&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Key Target 6: Quantity&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To generate the capacity to support the Naval Force Generation Plan target with Green assessments against all elements.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Key Target 7: Cost&amp;#x002F;Efficiency&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To make the necessary Agency contribution to the Defence Logistics Organisation Strategic Goal of reducing Output Costs by 20 per cent. by 2005 whilst ensuring that we continue to deliver and, where appropriate, improve the quality of our outputs.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Warship Support Agency' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/oct/23/warship-support-agency'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3605815' text='CONSTITUTIONAL AFFAIRS'>
      <outline id='3605816' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Constitutional Affairs (Mr. Christopher Leslie)&lt;p&gt;The Code of Practice on Access to Government Information Monitoring Report for 2002 is being published today. Copies are available in the Libraries of both Houses.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Access to Government Information' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/oct/23/access-to-government-information'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3605817' text='HOME DEPARTMENT'>
      <outline id='3605818' text="The Minister for Citizenship and Immigration (Beverley Hughes)&lt;p&gt;The Government are firmly committed to maintaining effective immigration controls while at the same time ensuring that genuine passengers are able to pass through our ports with the least possible inconvenience.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The number of people arriving at UK airports who are found to be inadmissible is unacceptably high. Certain nationals, who are required to hold a valid visa to enter the UK, may transit this country for up to 24 hours without a visa.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This provides a relatively easy and inexpensive way for those who are intent on circumventing our immigration controls to do so. We have already introduced measures to tackle this problem with the introduction of a direct airside transit visa requirement for 16 nationalities on 24 June. We now need to take further action and have identified six nationalities (Angola, Bangladesh, Cameroon, India, Lebanon and Pakistan) as posing a particular problem. Therefore from 00.01 hours on Thursday 16 October nationals of those six countries wishing to transit the UK will require a visa to do so. To avoid undue hardship for those who had already made their travel plans, we have agreed to operate a grace period. Until 23.59 hours on Monday 20 October any transit passenger who bought their ticket on or before 15 October will not be refused entry solely on the basis of not holding a valid transit visa. Also, any person on the return leg of a journey they commenced before 16 October and who passed through the UK on the outward leg of their journey will be allowed to transit the UK without a visa until 23.59 on 12 November.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In parallel with those measures we are introducing changes that will allow certain groups of low risk passenger who would normally require a transit visa to be exempt from such a requirement if they are in possession of specific documents. This will include those who are in possession of a valid US or Canadian visa or certain types of residence permits, long-stay visas for entry to an EEA state, or the EU common format residence permit.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have also decided to remove the requirement for nationals of Croatia, Libya and Slovakia to hold a visa when transiting the UK for up to 24 hours. Finally, holders of diplomatic or service passports issued by the People's Republic of China, and holders of diplomatic or official passports issued by India will also be exempt from the requirement to hold a visa when transiting the UK for up to 24 hours.&lt;/p&gt;" title='Immigration Control' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/oct/23/immigration-control'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3605819' text='WORK AND PENSIONS'>
      <outline id='3605820' text="The Secretary of State for Work and Pensions (Mr. Andrew Smith)&lt;p&gt;In my written answer on 24 July 2002,&lt;i&gt;Official Report,&lt;/i&gt; column 1583W, I announced that my Department had decided to negotiate with its existing supplier LandSecurities Trillium (LST) to provide estate&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;18WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;and property services to its former Employment Service buildings by expanding the existing PFI (PRIME) contract.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;These negotiations have now reached the point where I can announce that agreement in principle has been reached. Subject to contract, the expansion will occur later this year. As part of this deal, my Department will receive &amp;#x00A3;100 million as a transfer payment as part of the agreed valuation of the former Employment Service estate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The expansion of the PRIME contract represents the best value solution. It will provide a uniform and consistent service with sufficient flexibility to meet the Department's future business needs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note: PRIME (Private Sector Resource Initiative for the Management of the Estate) is a PFI contract let to Trillium (now LandSecurities Trillium) in April 1998.&lt;/p&gt;" title='Departmental Estates' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/oct/23/departmental-estates'></outline>
      <outline id='3605821' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Work and Pensions (Mr. Chris Pond)&lt;p&gt;Copies of the UK&apos;s second National Action Plan (NAP) on Social Inclusion, covering the period 2003&amp;#x2013;05 have today been placed in the Library.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Government&apos;s commitment to eradicating child poverty and ensuring that everyone in the UK has the opportunity to escape social exclusion is central to its programme.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To achieve this, we need to work effectively with a wide range of organisations across the UK&amp;#x2014;and with people who are experiencing poverty and social exclusion. The UK Government has made clear its commitment to working with the European Union (EU) to make a decisive impact on poverty across Europe by 2010.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The two-yearly NAPs enable the Government to:&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;join up action across the UK, encouraging the participation of the voluntary and community sector, &apos;grassroots&apos; people and all levels of government;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;identify best practice and assess the effectiveness of our strategy against other EU Member States using commonly agreed indicators; and so&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;learn from what works well both within the UK and across the EU.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In preparing the UK&apos;s second NAP, published in July 2003, the Government has achieved unprecedented levels of participation in the anti-poverty strategy and a shared understanding of the challenges which will need to be addressed in the coming two years. The NAP also reflects the success of the Government&apos;s broader strategies. In particular, macroeconomic stability has generated resources to target investment in the priority areas of health, education, criminal justice, housing and transport;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Overall, there are now over 1.5 million more people in employment than in 1997 and around 350,000 fewer children in workless households. There has been good progress in reducing the numbers below absolute low-income thresholds&amp;#x2014;around 1.8 million fewer children&#x000A;&lt;image src="S6CV0411P0I0637"/&gt;&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;19WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;and 1.6 million fewer pensioners below the 1996&amp;#x2013;97, 60 per cent. median income after housing costs threshold held constant in real terms.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Social Inclusion' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/oct/23/social-inclusion'></outline>
      <outline id='3605822' text="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Work and Pensions (Mr. Chris Pond)&lt;p&gt;Copies of the UK's 2003 National Action Plan for Employment have been placed in the Library today.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The EU Treaty requires Member States to submit an annual report setting out the principal measures being taken at a national level to implement national employment policies in the context of the agreed EU Employment Guidelines.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The National Action Plan responds to this requirement. Reporting across the ten Guidelines, it includes detail about: how the UK's institutional and regulatory environment helps encourage job creation and removes barriers to entering and progressing in the labour market; how measures like the New Deal and Jobcentre Plus encourage people back into work; how steps are being taken to ensure that work pays by eliminating unemployment and poverty traps; and how measures are being developed that help create a skilled and adaptable workforce.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In preparing this plan, the Government have worked closely with representatives from local government and the voluntary sector, as well as the CBI and TUC, so that we have been able to include a broad range of examples of how the objectives of creating more and better jobs and greater social cohesion are being pursued in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;" title='Employment' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/oct/23/employment'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3605823' text='ENVIRONMENT, FOOD AND RURAL AFFAIRS'>
      <outline id='3605824' text='The Minister for Rural Affairs and Local Environmental Quality (Alun Michael)&lt;p&gt;This Department is publishing a Report of a Financial Management and Policy Review (FMPR) of the Commons Commissioners.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Commissioners act as an independent tribunal, now sponsored jointly by the Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs and the National Assembly for Wales. It was established under the provisions of the Commons Registration Act 1965 to deal with disputed registrations of common land.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;col&gt;20WS&lt;/col&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FMPR Report is available on the DEFRA website at &lt;u&gt;http://www.defra.gov.uk/wildlife-countryside/issues/common/index.htm,&lt;/u&gt; and copies have been placed in the Libraries of both Houses. In summary, the consultant has concluded that:&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;the functions undertaken by the Commissioners still need to be carried out;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;the Commissioners provide a cost effective service;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;the functions or the Commissioners should not be transferred to another body at this stage. Once the future role of the Commissioners is clearer, a transfer of responsibilities might be a possibility.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the third point, it should be noted that DEFRA is considering this complex area of policy and law in the light of the conclusions of the Common Land Policy Statement published in July 2002.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Review also recommended a number of primarily administrative improvements relating to internal audit, the keeping of better management information and the introduction of performance monitoring. The Chief Commissioner and his Clerk will be considering how to take these issues forward, in close conjunction with DEFRA and Welsh Assembly Government officials.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Commons Commissioners' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/oct/23/commons-commissioners'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3605825' text='TRANSPORT'>
      <outline id='3605826' text="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Transport (Mr. David Jamieson)&lt;p&gt;Last July, the Department for Transport, the Department of Trade and Industry, the Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs and the Treasury jointly published the Government's Powering Future Vehicles strategy for promoting the development, introduction and take-up of clean, low-carbon vehicles and fuels in the UK, and ensuring the full involvement of the UK's automotive industries in the new technologies. The strategy set out the Government's objective that the UK should lead the global shift to the low-carbon economy, building competitive advantage for our automotive industries. Today the Low Carbon Ministerial Group, charged with oversight of the implementation of the Powering Future Vehicles strategy, published its first annual report, setting out the significant progress made towards the strategy's targets for low-carbon cars and buses and the other objectives A set. The strategy emphasised that a speedy and productive shift to low-carbon vehicles and fuels needed to involve not only Government, but the other stakeholders&amp;#x2014;the auto and fuel industries, environmental groups, and transport users.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Government therefore welcomes the setting up of a Low Carbon Vehicles Partnership, bringing together all those with a stake in and commitment to the shift in the UK's transport economy&amp;#x2014;with the involvement of industry leaders and others at the most senior level. The report has been published on the DfT website, and copies have been placed in the Libraries of both Houses.&lt;/p&gt;" title='Powering Future Vehicles Strategy' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/oct/23/powering-future-vehicles-strategy'></outline>
    </outline>
  </body>
</opml>
