<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Written Statement of 28 October 2003</title>
    <dateCreated>Tue, 28 Oct 2003 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='3558804' text='DEPUTY PRIME MINISTER'>
      <outline id='3558805' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State, Office of the Deputy Prime Minister (Phil Hope)&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04128"&gt;I have today laid the Standards Board for England&apos;s Annual Report and Accounts for 2002&amp;#x2013;03.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04129"&gt;The Report and Accounts cover the first year of significant operations by the Standards Board for England. At the end of March 2003, 2,948 allegations of misconduct had been referred to the Standards Board since the introduction of the Code of Conduct in May 2002.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04130"&gt;As the Annual Report shows, the Board is continuing to work in partnership with local government to promote and sustain the high standards of conduct which are essential to public confidence in our local democracy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04131"&gt;Copies of the Report are available in the Libraries of the House.&lt;/p&gt;' title='The Standards Board for England' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/oct/28/the-standards-board-for-england'></outline>
      <outline id='3558816' text='The Minister for Local Government, Regional Governance and Fire (Mr. Nick Raynsford)&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04132"&gt;The Government are looking at many ways, including all-postal ballots and e-voting, to modernise our electoral system and to increase the opportunities that people have to vote. To test the robustness of the new options and to build public confidence in them, we have undertaken an extensive programme of pilot innovations at local elections. This is why we are promoting legislation to permit further pilots to be held in a number of regions at the European Parliament and combined local elections in June 2004.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04133"&gt;Our focus over the forthcoming months will be on working to ensure that pilots held at the combined elections are successful in delivering elections that are more straightforward and accessible for all electors. As a result, we are currently not minded to approve applications for by-election pilots for the period from 1 April 2004 until 1 August 2004.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04134"&gt;Outside that period, our general approach on local authority by-election pilots is that while we will consider, as legislation requires us to do, all applications for pilots at by-elections, we are minded normally to approve such applications only if the proposals are consistent with the recommendations of the Electoral Commission as set out in "The Shape of Elections to Come".&lt;/p&gt;' title='Electoral Pilot Schemes' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/oct/28/electoral-pilot-schemes'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3558817' text='TREASURY'>
      <outline id='3558818' text='The Financial Secretary to the Treasury (Ruth Kelly)&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04135"&gt;The Financial Services Authority, acting in its role as the competent authority for listing, is referred to as the United Kingdom Listing Authority. Every year, the operational objectives of the UKLA are discussed with the Treasury. The annual objectives for 2003&amp;#x2013;04, which the Treasury has endorsed, will be placed in the Library, and also put on the Treasury website.&lt;/p&gt;' title='United Kingdom Listing Authority' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/oct/28/united-kingdom-listing-authority'></outline>
      <outline id='3558828' text='The Financial Secretary to the Treasury (Ruth Kelly)&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04136"&gt;The Government are today publishing their detailed proposals for the Child Trust Fund. Copies are available in the Vote Office and the Libraries of the House.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Child Trust Fund' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/oct/28/child-trust-fund'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3558831' text='NORTHERN IRELAND'>
      <outline id='3558833' text='The Secretary of State for Northern Ireland (Mr. Paul Murphy)&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04137"&gt;The Compensation Agency will publish today its Corporate Plan for 2003 to 2006 and Business Plan for 2003 to 2004. I have set the Agency the following Key Performance Targets for 2003 to 2004:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04138"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Claims under the Criminal Damage (Compensation) (Northern Ireland) Order 1977&lt;/i&gt;&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Maintain average time taken to reach decisions at 19 weeks for claims received from 1 April 2003;&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Reduce by 85 per cent. the number of claims in hand at 31 March 2003 on which no decision has been reached; and&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Process claims under the Criminal Damage and Terrorism Act schemes at a combined average unit cost of &amp;#x00A3;140.&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04139"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Claims under the Terrorism Act 2000&lt;/i&gt;&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Reach decisions on claims in 53 days for claims received from 1 April 2003;&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Reduce by 85 per cent. the number of claims in hand at 31 March 2003 on which no decision has been reached; and&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;Process claims under the Criminal Damage and Terrorism Act schemes at the combined average unit cost of &amp;#x00A3;140.&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;This unit cost target relates to claims under the Criminal Damage and Terrorism Act schemes. The work involved in processing these claims is carried out in a single organisational unit within the agency so the efficiency of this element of the agency&apos;s operations is measured by reference to a combined unit cost target.&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04140"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Claims under Criminal Injuries (Compensation) (Northern Ireland) Order 1988&lt;/i&gt;&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Reduce by 45 per cent. the number of claims in hand at 31 March 2003; and&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Reach a decision on 50 per cent. of undecided criminal injuries claims in hand at 31 March 2003.&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04141"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Claims under the Criminal Injuries Compensation (Northern Ireland) Order 2002 (Tariff)&lt;/i&gt;&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;To decide 45 per cent. of all applications within 12 months of receiving the application.&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;To reach decisions on applications at an average unit cost of &amp;#x00A3;290.&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;image src="S6CV0412P0I0705"/&gt;&lt;col&gt;7WS&lt;/col&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04142"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Compliance with Legislation/Standards of Adjudication&amp;#x2014;All Schemes&lt;/i&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;That the agency&apos;s standards of adjudication are appropriate which will be confirmed by the Department&apos;s internal audit branch through random sampling of claims.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04143"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Value for Money&amp;#x2014;All Schemes&lt;/i&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Manage the workload in 2003&amp;#x2013;04 within a running costs budget (to cover salaries and administrative expenditure) to financial limits agreed with the Department (including in-year adjustments).&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;' title='Compensation Agency' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/oct/28/compensation-agency'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3558834' text='DEFENCE'>
      <outline id='3558836' text='The Secretary of State for Defence (Mr. Geoffrey Hoon)&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04144"&gt;HQ 3 (UK) Division continues to command the multinational division (South-East) (MND(SE)) in Iraq, with contributions from the Czech Republic, Denmark, Italy, Lithuania, the Netherlands, New Zealand, Norway, Portugal and Romania.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04145"&gt;We have begun a process of roulement of United Kingdom Forces, which involves the incremental replacement of HQ 3 (UK) Division with a composite HQ MND(SE), the replacement of 19 Mechanised Brigade with 20 Armoured Brigade the replacement of HQ 101 Logistic Brigade with a composite HQ UK National Support Element (NSE), the roulement of the combat service support units that will make up the UK NSE, and the mobilisation of around 1,000 reservists. We expect the maritime and air elements of our presence in theatre to remain broadly stable.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04146"&gt;A number of adjustments to our force levels in Iraq were made over the summer. Some of these were relatively minor, such as the withdrawal of around 30 armoured engineers and the short-term deployment of around 30 personnel from 23 Pioneer Regiment Royal Logistic Corps to undertake building and construction tasks around Shabah Logistics Base.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04147"&gt;On a larger scale, we also deployed the 2nd Battalion The Light Infantry (2LI) and the 1st Battalion The Royal Green Jackets (1RGJ), to conduct a number of additional security and training tasks and provide MND(SE) with the flexibility and capacity to carry out surge operations designed to counter crime and enhance security. A recent major operation in MND(SE), OPERATION SWEENEY, has resulted in 291 arrests, the seizure of six weapons caches, and the interception of 57 vessels and 58 vehicles involved in criminal activity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04148"&gt;Some of the additional requirements for which 2LI and 1RGJ deployed are now being reduced or progressively transferred to Iraqi security forces. But some other requirements will continue over the next few months, including the provision of training for the new Iraqi Civil Defence Corps. In overall terms, we assess that these continuing requirements can be met by approximately one battalion rather than two. When 2LI and 1 RGJ are withdrawn from theatre in November and December they will therefore be replaced by the 2nd Battalion The Parachute Regiment (2 PARA). We envisage that 2 PARA will deploy from early November.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;col&gt;8WS&lt;/col&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04149"&gt;In addition to adjustments to force levels, we have also deployed further equipment to theatre, including over 200 armoured Land Rovers, three Puma helicopters and three Gazelle helicopters. Taken together, these enhancements provide MND(SE) with greater mobility, force protection and surveillance capabilities, increasing the flexibility and effectiveness of the force.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04150"&gt;We will continue to keep the size and mix of forces in theatre under close review, and we expect to make further adjustments as a matter of routine to ensure that MND(SE) have appropriate capabilities for the tasks in hand. This is likely to include temporary increases in force levels when appropriate, to provide the General Officer Commanding MND(SE) with additional tactical flexibility and help ensure that progress and momentum are maintained and where possible accelerated. To facilitate this process we intend as a matter of course to nominate two battalions as over-the-horizon operational reserves for Iraq.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Iraq' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/oct/28/iraq'></outline>
      <outline id='3558838' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Defence (Mr. Ivor Caplin)&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04151"&gt;Skill Force is a nationwide Ministry of Defence originated and Department for Education and Skills supported youth initiative to reengage disaffected 14 to 16 year-olds with mainstream education. There are currently 23 teams operating in around 100 schools with 3,000 participants. Pupils drop two GCSE options in favour of a more vocationally based education. Skill Force mainly uses former military Instructors, who have recently left the armed services to deliver a wide range of Key Skill-based subjects to young people who are in danger of becoming disaffected with the formal academic education system.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04152"&gt;Evaluation of the first 12 schemes showed that Skill Force had been very successful in reducing truancy and exclusions by around 80 per cent. and had had a positive impact upon behaviour. As a consequence, DfES has helped to fund a further 11 schemes, which have been operating for a year as part of the behaviour improvement programme.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04153"&gt;The Institute of Education, London University, has recently conducted an independent and comprehensive evaluation of Skill Force. The report concluded that:&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;"Overall, Skill Force is an extremely well managed programme which provides a unique service to schools. It has been successful in meeting the needs of many disaffected students, improving their motivation, confidence, communication and social skills. It has reduced exclusions, improved behaviour, attendance, attitudes towards education and attainment and also provided students with a range of practical, vocational qualifications. It offers excellent value for money. The comments from students and parents provided in this report are a testament to the opportunities it offers. Perhaps more importantly it has the support of school management. The ethos of Skill Force is positive, &apos;can do&apos; and focused on problem solving. The challenges outlined above will be tackled with enthusiasm and solutions found."&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04154"&gt;I am today placing a copy of this report in the Library of the House. We are currently assessing, with the Connexions Service, the impact that Skill Force has had upon participants entering employment, training and&#x000A;&lt;image src="S6CV0412P0I0706"/&gt;&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;9WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;education on leaving secondary school in July 2003 at the end of the initial two year course. The Ministry of Defence and the Department for Education and Skills will continue to work together on the longer term future of Skill Force.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Skill Force' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/oct/28/skill-force'></outline>
      <outline id='3558840' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Defence (Mr. Ivor Caplin)&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04155"&gt;I have set the following Key Targets for the Chief Executive of the Veterans Agency for 2003&amp;#x2013;04. They are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04156"&gt;SERVICE&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Key Target 1: To reduce the average time it takes to issue decisions on claims to war pensions to no more than 63 working days. This is an improvement of 19 working days on the 2002&amp;#x2013;03 target; and it represents a cumulative improvement of 37 per cent. against the 2000&amp;#x2013;01 baseline level of 100 working days.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Key Target 2: To reduce the average time it takes to issue decisions on war widows claims to no more than 23 working days. This is an improvement of 11 working days on the 2002&amp;#x2013;03 target; and it represents a cumulative improvement of 36 per cent. against the 2000&amp;#x2013;01 baseline level of 36 working days.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Key Target 3: To achieve an externally validated claims accuracy rate of at least 97 per cent.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04157"&gt;PERSONNEL&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Key Target 4: To carry out an externally validated programme of internal Investors in People assessments during 2003&amp;#x2013;04 to determine whether the Agency continues to meet the requirements of the IiP standards.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04158"&gt;WORKING IN PARTNERSHIP&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Key Target 5: To work with the Department for Constitutional Affairs Court Service to reduce the average time it takes an appeal to pass through the war pensions appeals process. By 31 March 2004 the average time should reduce to no more than 250 working days. This is an improvement of 60 working days on the 2002&amp;#x2013;03 target; and it represents a cumulative improvement of 56 per cent. against the 2000&amp;#x2013;01 baseline level of 565 working days.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04159"&gt;EFFICIENCY&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Key Target 6: To use the Agency output costing methodology developed in 2002&amp;#x2013;03 to help identify and generate such administrative efficiencies and other savings as will enable the agency to operate within a 2003&amp;#x2013;04 running cost baseline figure that is 3 per cent. less than its resource departmental expenditure limit for that year.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;' title='Veterans Agency' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/oct/28/veterans-agency'></outline>
      <outline id='3558842' text='The Minister of State, Ministry of Defence (Mr. Adam Ingram)&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04160"&gt;We announced in February 2002 that the British-based consortium Paradigm Secure Communications had been selected as preferred bidder to supply the SKYNET 5 satellite communications service to the MOD under the Private Finance Initiative.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04161"&gt;I am pleased to announce that last Friday contract negotiations were successfully concluded and that the SKYNET 5 PFI contract, the biggest yet placed by the MOD, has been enacted.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04162"&gt;The full value of the contract, which is planned to run until 2018, is expected to be around &amp;#x00A3;2.5 billion and Paradigm expect it to create or sustain up to 1,900 jobs across the UK at its peak.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;col&gt;10WS&lt;/col&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04163"&gt;The MOD is getting this service at a significant value for money advantage compared to the costs that would have been associated with a more traditional procurement route.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04164"&gt;The move to a PFI approach and accompanying fresh and innovative thinking has resulted in substantial savings. SKYNET 5 is within budget and remains on target to achieve initial provision of new services from 2005. It is a clear example of how we are getting better military capability and better value for money by using Smart Acquisition principles.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04165"&gt;This deal will provide the MOD with a number of benefits, including transfer to risk to the contractor. SKYNET 5 will also provide a greatly improved service with regular technology upgrades, and the flexibility to cope with the growth in military satellite communications requirements we expect over the next few years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04166"&gt;The events of 11 September 2001 provided us all with a timely reminder to make sure that our key military communication and information systems have the necessary resilience to ensure business continuity. SKYNET 5 services will provide this assurance under almost any conceivable scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;' title='SKYNET 5' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/oct/28/skynet-5'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3558844' text='TRANSPORT'>
      <outline id='3558845' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Transport (Mr. Tony McNulty)&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04167"&gt;The Government will today announce their proposals for implementing the taxi provisions of the Disability Discrimination Act 1995. This will allow us to set standards for wheelchair access and a rang. of other features to help disabled people use taxis. We intend to vary the application of the regulations to target first those areas where we believe accessible taxis will make the biggest impact in meeting the needs of disabled people and where additional cost will not have a major effect. We are calling these first phase authorities and propose to introduce the Regulations in these areas over a 10-year period from 2010&amp;#x2013;20.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04168"&gt;Authorities within the first phase have been identified and each meet one or more of the following criteria:&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;A licensing authority population of at least 120,000 people;&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;A major transport interchange;&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;A major tourist attraction; or&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;An existing mandatory policy resulting in 100 per cent. accessible vehicles.&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04169"&gt;A list of those authorities that are currently included will be placed in the Libraries of both Houses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04170"&gt;Licensing authorities outside of this first phase would not be subject to the regulations in the first instance. We would instead issue voluntary guidance to these authorities on establishing an appropriate mix of vehicles and on design parameters that they should be considering. We would also monitor the introduction of accessible vehicles in these areas to determine whether the guidance is effective. A view would then be taken on the necessity of extending the regulations to these areas.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;image src="S6CV0412P0I0707"/&gt;&lt;col&gt;11WS&lt;/col&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04171"&gt;The proposals, which apply to England and Wales only, will be the subject of a full public consultation process in due course. Scotland and Northern Ireland will be holding their own separate consultation processes.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Disability Discrimination Act (Taxis)' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/oct/28/disability-discrimination-act-taxis'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3558847' text='CONSTITUTIONAL AFFAIRS'>
      <outline id='3558848' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Constitutional Affairs (Mr. Christopher Leslie)&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04172"&gt;The judicial appointments annual report, covering the period 1 April 2002 to 31 March 2003, is published today. This year&apos;s report shows that:&lt;quote&gt;Six hundred and ninety seven appointments were made in 2002&amp;#x2013;03 from 3,449 applications.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Appointments of minority ethnic candidates rose from 7.8 per cent. in 2001&amp;#x2013;02 to 8.9 per cent. (this includes lay appointments) and is more than double the 1999&amp;#x2013;2000 figure which was 4.2 per cent.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Women accounted for 31 per cent. of appointments and although this was a decrease of 3 per cent. compared with 2001&amp;#x2013;02, the figure remains significantly higher than it was five years ago when the first report was published.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;The pilot Assessment Centre in October/November for the Deputy District Judge (Civil and Magistrates) competitions and the Deputy Queen&apos;s Bench Master competition was a success. The Commissioner for Judicial Appointments&apos; audit of the pilot was very positive.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04173"&gt;The report also explains other recent action on equal opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04174"&gt;Copies of the report have been placed in the Libraries of both Houses. The report is also available on the Department&apos;s website at http://www.dca.gov.uk./&lt;/p&gt;' title='Judicial Appointments Annual Report for 2002–2003—10–28' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/oct/28/judicial-appointments-annual-report-for'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3558849' text='WORK AND PENSIONS'>
      <outline id='3558851' text='The Minister for Pensions (Malcolm Wicks)&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04175"&gt;Copies of the Government&apos;s consultation document on the implementation of the European Directive (2003/41/ EC) on Institutions for Occupational Retirement Pensions have today been placed in the Library. Copies of the consultation and the Directive are also available on the Department for Work and Pensions&apos; website at&lt;u&gt;http://www.dwp.gov.uk/resourcecentre/consultation_papers.asp&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04176"&gt;The Directive supports the Government&apos;s plans for reform of the UK pensions system, as outlined in the recent Green Paper Simplicity, Security and Choice: Working and Saving for Retirement (Cm 5677) and the Government&apos;s response, Action on Occupational Pensions (Cm 5835).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04177"&gt;It sets up a common framework across Europe for the operation and supervision of institutions providing occupational retirement pensions. It allows pension schemes established in one EU Member State to be sponsored by employers in another Member State, enabling the establishment of cross-border pension schemes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04178"&gt;The consultation being undertaken builds upon the extensive pensions consultation carried out by the Department for Work and Pensions over the last year. It focuses upon implementation of those areas of the Directive which have not been covered in the earlier consultations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0412P0-04179"&gt;The consultation period will close on 23 December.&lt;/p&gt;' title='EU Pensions Directive' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/oct/28/eu-pensions-directive'></outline>
    </outline>
  </body>
</opml>
