<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Lords Report of 16 November 1925</title>
    <dateCreated>Mon, 16 Nov 1925 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='2243417' text="Petition of Thomas Wentworth Russell, Commandant Cairo City Police, claiming to be a co-heir to the Baronies of Beauchamp, to His Majesty, praying His Majesty to determine in his favor the abeyance now existing in some one or both of the said Baronies, together with His Majesty's reference thereof to this House, and the report of the Attorney-General thereon thereunto annexed Presented (by command); read, and referred to the Committee for Privileges to consider and report." title='BARONIES OF BEAUCHAMP AND MORDAUNT.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1925/nov/16/baronies-of-beauchamp-and-mordaunt'></outline>
    <outline id='2243418' text="Petition of Constantine Joseph Lubienski-Bodenham, claiming to be a co-heir to the Barony of Pole of Montagu, to His Majesty, praying His Majesty to determine in his favour the abeyance now existing in the said Barony of Pole of Montagu, and in case it should be held that the said Barony is affected by the attainder of Margaret Countess of Salisbury, or by any other attainders referred to in the said Petition, to be graciously pleased to give directions for the introduction of a Bill into Parliament to relieve the Petitioner from the effect or effects of the attainder or attainders as aforesaid, in so far as it relates or they relate to the said Barony of Pole of Montagu, together with His Majesty's reference thereof to this House, and the report of the Attorney-General thereunto annexed: Presented (by command); read, and referred to the Committee for Privileges to consider and report." title='BARONY OF POLE OF MONTAGU.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1925/nov/16/barony-of-pole-of-montagu'></outline>
    <outline id='2243419' text='Petition of Percy Ronald Gardner, Earl of Bandon in the Peerage of Ireland, claiming a right to vote at the elections of Representative Peers for Ireland; read and referred to the Lord Chancellor to consider and report upon to the House.' title='EARL OF BANDON.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1925/nov/16/earl-of-bandon'></outline>
    <outline id='2243420' text='Commited: The Committee to be proposed by the Committee of Selection.' title='SANDWICH PORT AND HAVEN BILL.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1925/nov/16/sandwich-port-and-haven-bill'></outline>
    <outline id='2243422' text='MONEYLENDERS BILL. [H.L.]'>
      <outline id='2243425' text='Minutes of Evidence laid upon the table, and to be delivered out.' title='MONEYLENDERS (AMENDMENT) BILL.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1925/nov/16/moneylenders-amendment-bill'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='2243426' text="Report from the Committee of Selection, That the following Lords be proposed to the House to form the Select Committee for the consideration of the said Bill; namely:&amp;#x2014;&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;M. Bath (Chairman),&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;E. Spencer,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;E. Lucan,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Raglan,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Terrington;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&#x000A;agreed to; and the said Lords appointed accordingly: The Committee to meet on Thursday next, at half-past eleven o'clock; and all Petitions referred to the Committee, with leave to the Petitioners praying to be heard by Counsel against the Bill to be heard as desired, as also Counsel for the Bill." title='BEDFORDSHIRE, CAMBRIDGESHIRE, AND HUNTINGDONSHIRE ELECTRICITY BILL. [H.L.]' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1925/nov/16/bedfordshire-cambridgeshire-and'></outline>
    <outline id='2243427' text='Report from the Committee of Selection, That the five Lords appointed a Select Committee on the Bedfordshire, Cambridgeshire, and Huntingdonshire Electricity Bill [H.L.] do form the Select Committee for the consideration of the Northampton Gas Order, 1925; read, and agreed to: Petition referred to the Committee, with leave to the Petitioners praying to be heard by Counsel against the Order to be heard as desired, as also Counsel for the Order.' title='NORTHAMPTON GAS ORDER, 1925.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1925/nov/16/northampton-gas-order-1925'></outline>
    <outline id='2243428' text='Report from the Committee of Selection, That the following Lords be proposed to the House to form the Select&#x000A;&lt;image src="S5LV0062P0I0409"/&gt;&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;807&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;Committee for the consideration of the said Bill; namely:&amp;#x2014;&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;V. Falkland,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Fairfax,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Monkswell,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Glentanar,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Chalmers (Chairman);&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/ul&gt;&#x000A;agreed to; and the said Lords appointed accordingly: The Committee to meet on Thursday next, at eleven o&apos;clock; and all Petitions referred to the Committee, with leave to the Petitioners praying to be heard by Counsel against the Bill to be heard as desired, as also Counsel for the Bill.' title='GLASGOW BOUNDARIES BILL.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1925/nov/16/glasgow-boundaries-bill'></outline>
    <outline id='2243429' text='Special Order made by the Electricity Commissioners under the Electricity (Supply) Acts, 1882 to 1922, and con firmed by the Minister of Transport under the Electricity (Supply) Act, 1919, in respect of the urban district of Prestatyn in the County of Flint:&lt;br/&gt;Special Order made by the Electricity Commissioners under the Electricity (Supply) Acts, 1882 to 1922, and confirmed by the Minister of Transport under the Electricity (Supply) Act, 1919, in respect of the urban district of al district of Woodbridge in the Administrative County of East Suffolk:&lt;br/&gt;Special Order made by the Electricity Commissioners under the Electricity (Supply) Acts, 1882 to 1922, and confirmed by the Minister of Transport under the Electricity (Supply) Act, 1919, in respect of part of the County Borough of Barnsley in the West Riding of the County of York:&lt;br/&gt;Special Order made by the Electricity Commissioners under the Electricity (Supply) Acts, 1882 to 1922, and confirmed by the Minister of Transport under the Electricity (Supply) Act, 1919, in respect of part of the rural district of Preston in the County Palatine of Lancaster:&lt;br/&gt;Special Order made by the Electricity Commissioners under the Electricity (Supply) Acts, 1882 to 1922, and confirmed by the Minister of Transport under the Electricity (Supply) Act, 1919, in respect of the urban district of Crediton in the County of Devon:&lt;br/&gt;Special Order made by the Electricity Commissioners under the Electricity (Supply) Acts, 1882 to 1922, and confirmed by the Minister of Transport under the Electricity (Supply) Act, 1919, in respect of the Borough of Maldon and the parishes of Heybridge and Langford in the rural district of Maldon in the County of Essex:&lt;br/&gt;Special Order made by the Electricity Commissioners under the Electricity (Supply) Acts, 1882 to 1922, and confirmed by the Minister of Transport under the Electricity (Supply) Act, 1919, in respect of the parish of Whitchurch in the rural district of Whitchurch in the County of Southampton:&lt;br/&gt;Special Order made by the Electricity Commissioners under the Electricity (Supply) Acts, 1882 to 1922, and confirmed by the Minister of Transport under the Electricity (Supply) Act, 1919, in respect of the burgh of Bridge of Allan in the County of Stirling:&lt;br/&gt;Special Order made by the Electricity Commissioners under the Electricity (Supply) Acts, 1882 to 1922, and confirmed by the Minister of Transport under the Electricity (Supply) Act, 1919, in respect of the urban district of Ashton-in-Makerfield in the County Palatine of Lancaster:&lt;br/&gt;Special Order made by the Electricity Commissioners under the Electricity (Supply) Acts, 1882 to 1922, and confirmed by the Minister of Transport under the Electricity (Supply) Act, 1919, in respect of the Borough of Clitheroe and part of the rural district Clitheroe in the County Palatine of Lancaster:&lt;br/&gt;Special Order made by the Electricity Commissioners under the Electricity (Supply) Acts, 1882 to 1922, and confirmed by the Minister of Transport under the Electricity (Supply) Act, 1919, in respect of parts of the parishes of Llechwedd Llangelynin and Llangwstenin in the rural district of Conway in the County of Carnarvon:&lt;br/&gt;Special Order made by the Electricity Commissioners under the Electricity (Supply) Acts, 1882 to 1922, and con-&#x000A;&lt;image src="S5LV0062P0I0410"/&gt;&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;809&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;firmed by the Minister of Transport under the Electricity (Supply) Act, 1919, in respect of the parishes of Botley, Bursledon, Chilworth, Hamble, Hedge End, Hound and Millbrook and part of the parish of West End in the rural district of South Stoneham in the County of Southampton:&lt;br/&gt;Special Order made by the Electricity Commissioners under the- Electricity (Supply) Acts, 1882 to 1922, and confirmed by the Minister of Transport under the Electricity (Supply) Act, 1919, in respect of parts of the rural districts of Blackburn, Burnley and Clitheroe in the County Palatine of Lancaster:&lt;br/&gt;Special Order made by the Electricity Commissioners under the Electricity (Supply) Acts, 1882 to 1922, and confirmed by the Minister of Transport, under the Electricity (Supply) Act, 1919, in respect of the parishes of Erskine, Inchinnan, Houston, Kilbarchan, Lochwinnock and Eaglesham, and parts of the parishes of Kilmacolm, Renfrew, Paisley, Neilston, Eastwood, and Mearns all in the County of Renfrew:&lt;br/&gt;Laid before the House (pursuant to Act) and referred to the Special Orders Committee.' title='ELECTRICITY SPECIAL ORDERS.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1925/nov/16/electricity-special-orders'></outline>
    <outline id='2243430' text='Report from the Select Committee: That the Committee had not proceeded with the consideration of the Bournemouth Order, no parties having appeared in opposition to the said Order: The Orders made on the 2nd and 8th of July last respecting the commitment of the Bill to a Select Committee in regard to the said Order discharged, and Bill committed in regard of the said Order for Thursday next.' title='MINISTRY OF HEALTH PROVISIONAL ORDERS CONFIRMATION (BOURNEMOUTH AND LYME REGIS ORDERS) BILL [H.L.] [BOURNEMOUTH ORDER].' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1925/nov/16/ministry-of-health-provisional-orders'></outline>
    <outline id='2243431' text='House to be in Committee (on re-commitment) on Thursday next.' title='MONEYLENDERS BILL. [H.L.]' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1925/nov/16/moneylenders-bill-hl-1'></outline>
  </body>
</opml>
