<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Lords Report of 12 April 1938</title>
    <dateCreated>Tue, 12 Apr 1938 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='2305594' text="Report made from the Committee for Privileges, That the Barony of Vaux of Harrowden is a Barony by Writ and was first held by Sir Nicholas Vaux in the reign of King Henry VIII; that the said Barony descended to and was held by Henry, fifth Baron Vaux of Harrowden (heir of the body of the above-mentioned Sir Nicholas Vaux), and upon his death fell into abeyance between (&lt;i&gt;a&lt;/i&gt;) his niece Elizabeth Simeon, (&lt;i&gt;b&lt;/i&gt;) his sister Joyce Vaux, and (&lt;i&gt;c&lt;/i&gt;) his nephew George Neville, Baron Abergavenny, his co-heirs; that the abeyance in the said Barony was terminated by Her late Majesty Queen Victoria in favour of George Mostyn (heir of the body of Elizabeth Simeon above-mentioned) who was summoned to Parliament by Writ in the said Barony and took his seat in the House of Lords on 12th March, 1838; that the said George, sixth Baron Vaux of Harrowden, died in the year 1883, and that thereupon the Barony of Vaux of Harrowden descended on Hubert, his grandson and heir, who took his seat in the House of Lords as seventh Baron Vaux of Harrowden; that the said Hubert, seventh Baron Vaux of Harrowden, died 25th October, 1935, whereupon the Barony fell into abeyance between his three daughters and co-heirs, namely (&lt;i&gt;a&lt;/i&gt;) Grace Mary Eleanor, wife of William Gordon Gilbey, (&lt;i&gt;b&lt;/i&gt;) Gladys Flora, wife of George Victor Bellasis Charlton, and (&lt;i&gt;c&lt;/i&gt;) Dorothy Alice, and is now in abeyance between the above-mentioned coheirs; that the said Barony of Vaux of Harrowden is at His Majesty's disposal.&lt;br/&gt;Read, and agreed to; and resolved and adjudged accordingly; and Resolution and Judgment to be laid before His Majesty by the Lords with White Staves." title='BARONY OF VAUX OF HARROWDEN.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1938/apr/12/barony-of-vaux-of-harrowden'></outline>
    <outline id='2305595' text='Report from, That the Standing Orders not complied with in respect of the Petition for the following Bill:&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Penzance Corporation&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/ul&gt;&#x000A;ought to be dispensed with, and leave given to introduce the Bill:&lt;br/&gt;Read, and agreed to.' title='STANDING ORDERS COMMITTEE.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1938/apr/12/standing-orders-committee'></outline>
    <outline id='2305596' text='Presented (pursuant to leave given this day), and read 1&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;br/&gt;The LORD CHANCELLOR acquainted the House, That the Clerk of the Parliaments had laid upon the Table the Certificate from the Examiners that the further Standing Orders applicable to the following Bills have been complied with:&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Bangor Corporation,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Radcliffe Farnworth and District Gas.&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Also the Certificate that the Standing Orders have not been complied with in respect of the Petition for the following Bill:&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Harwich Harbour.&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The same were ordered to lie on the Table.' title='PENZANCE CORPORATION BILL. [H.L.]' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1938/apr/12/penzance-corporation-bill-hl'></outline>
    <outline id='2305597' text='SALFORD CORPORATION BILL. [H.L.]'>
      <outline id='2305598' text='CHICHESTER CORPORATION BILL [H.L.]'>
        <outline id='2305599' text="Report from the Committee of Selection, That the following Lords be proposed to the House to form the Select Committee for the consideration of the said Bills; namely:&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;E. Hardwicke,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;V. Plumer,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Loch (Chairman),&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Nunburnholme,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Woodbridge:&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/ul&gt;&#x000A;Agreed to; and the said Lords appointed accordingly. The Committee to meet on Tuesday, the 10th of May next, at eleven o'clock; and all Petitions referred to the Committee, with leave to the Petitioners praying to be heard by Counsel against the Bills to be heard as desired, as also Counsel for the Bills." title='ALDRIDGE URBAN DISTRICT COUNCIL BILL.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1938/apr/12/aldridge-urban-district-council-bill'></outline>
      </outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='2305600' text='Special Order proposed to be made on the application of the Portsmouth and Gosport Gas Company:&lt;br/&gt;Laid before the House (pursuant to Act) for affirmative Resolution and referred to the Special Orders Committee.' title='PORTSMOUTH AND GOSPORT GAS ORDER, 1938.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1938/apr/12/portsmouth-and-gosport-gas-order-1938'></outline>
    <outline id='2305602' text='Reported, without amendment, and recommitted to a Committee of the Whole House.' title='NORTH WEST MIDLANDS JOINT ELECTRICITY AUTHORITY PROVISIONAL ORDER BILL.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1938/apr/12/north-west-midlands-joint-electricity'></outline>
  </body>
</opml>
