<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Lords Report of 3 November 1936</title>
    <dateCreated>Tue, 03 Nov 1936 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='2294501' text='Draft of Instrument of Instructions which it is proposed to recommend His Majesty to issue to the Governors of Indian Provinces:&lt;br/&gt;Laid before the House (pursuant to Section 53 of the Act) and ordered to lie on the Table.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;GOVERNMENT OF BURMA ACT,1935.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Draft of Instrument of Instructions which it is proposed to recommend His Majesty to issue to the Governor of Burma:&lt;br/&gt;Laid before the House (pursuant to Section 9 of the Act) and ordered to lie on the Table.' title='GOVERNMENT OF INDIA ACT, 1935.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1936/nov/03/government-of-india-act-1935'></outline>
    <outline id='2294502' text='Special Order in respect of part of the rural district of Burnley in the County Palatine of Lancaster:&lt;br/&gt;Laid before the House (pursuant to Act) for affirmative Resolution and referred to the Special Orders Committee.' title='NELSON ELECTRICITY (EXTENSION) ORDER, 1936.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1936/nov/03/nelson-electricity-extension-order-1936'></outline>
    <outline id='2294503' text="Special Order proposed to be made on the application of the Sheffield Gas Company:&lt;br/&gt;Laid before the House (pursuant to Act) for affirmative Resolution and referred to the Special Orders Committee.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;GOVERNMENT OF INDIA (AUDIT AND ACCOUNTS) ORDER,&lt;/b&gt; 1936.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;GOVERNMENT OF INDIA (FAMILY PENSION FUNDS) ORDER,&lt;/b&gt; 1936.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;GOVERNMENT OF INDIA (GOVERNORS' ALLOWANCES AND PRIVILEGES) ORDER, 1936.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;GOVERNMENT OF INDIA (FEDERAL LEGISLATURE AMENDMENT) ORDER, 1936.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;GOVERNMENT OF INDIA (PRO VINCIAL LEGISLATURES) (MIS CELLANEOUS PROVISIONS) ORDER, 1936.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;GOVERNMENT OF INDIA (DEFENCE APPOINTMENTS) ORDER, 1936.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;GOVERNMENT OF INDIA (COMMENCEMENT AND TRANSITORY PROVISIONS) (No. 2) ORDER, 1936.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;GOVERNMENT OF INDIA (FEDERAL COURT) ORDER, 1936.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;GOVERNMENT OF BURMA (AUDIT&lt;lb/&gt;AND ACCOUNTS) ORDER, 1936.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;GOVERNMENT OF BURMA (GOVERNOR'S SALARY, ALLOWANCES AND PRIVILEGES) ORDER, 1936.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;GOVERNMENT OF BURMA (LEGISLATURE) (MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS) ORDER, 1936.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;GOVERNMENT OF BURMA (DEFENCE APPOINTMENTS) ORDER,1936.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Laid before the House (pursuant to Act) for affirmative Resolution and referred to the India and Burma Orders Committee." title='SHEFFIELD GAS (No. 2) ORDER, 1936.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1936/nov/03/sheffield-gas-no-2-order-1936'></outline>
  </body>
</opml>
