<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Lords Report of 10 December 1928</title>
    <dateCreated>Mon, 10 Dec 1928 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='2285937' text="Report made from the Committee for Privileges:&amp;#x2014;&lt;br/&gt;BARONY OF MONTACUTE (1299).&lt;br/&gt;1, That the Barony of Montacute is an ancient Barony in fee;&lt;br/&gt;2, That Simon de Montacute, who was summoned to Parliament by a writ, dated 29th December, 28 Edward I. (1299), was entitled to a Barony by Writ descendible to the heirs general of his body;&lt;br/&gt;3, That the said Barony descended to Margaret, Countess of Salisbury, who died in 1541;&lt;br/&gt;4, That the said Margaret, Countess of Salisbury, and Henry Pole, her eldest son, were attainted of high treason by Act of Parliament in 1539;&lt;br/&gt;5, That, but for the said attainders, the said Barony of Montacute would, on the death of the said Henry Pole Lord Montacute, have fallen into abeyance between his two daughters and co-heirs Katherine and Winifred;&lt;br/&gt;6, That the said Katherine married Francis Earl of Huntingdon and left issue, and that her representatives and co-heirs are the following persons&amp;#x2014;&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Edith Maud, Countess of Loudoun,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Elizabeth Frances, wife of John Wynford, Viscount St. Davids,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Lady Flora Anne Rawdon-Hastings,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Cecil Talbot Lord Grey de Ruthyn,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Constantine Mary Joseph Lubienski-Bodenham,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;May Flora Amy Kirwan,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Charles Earl of Romney;&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br/&gt;7, That the said Winifred married, first, Sir Thomas Hastings, Kt., and, secondly, Sir Thomas Barrington, Kt.; that she left issue by her second husband only and that her representatives and co-heirs are the following persons&amp;#x2014;&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;The Petitioner William Selby-Lowndes,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Helen Clara, wife of Henry Mangles Denham;&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br/&gt;8, That the said Barony of Montacute would, if the effect of the said attainders be removed, be in abeyance and at His Majesty's disposal." title='BARONIES OF MONTACUTE AND MONTHERMER.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1928/dec/10/baronies-of-montacute-and-monthermer'></outline>
    <outline id='2285938' text="1, That the Barony of Monthermer is an ancient Barony in fee;&lt;br/&gt;2, That Ralph de Monthermer, who was summoned to Parliament by a writ, dated 26th October, 3 Edward II. (1309), was entitled to a Barony by Writ descendible to the heirs general of his body;&lt;br/&gt;3, That the said Barony descended to Margaret, Countess of Salisbury, who died in 1541;&lt;br/&gt;4, That the said Margaret, Countess of Salisbury, and Henry Pole, her eldest son, were attainted of high treason by Act of Parliament in 1539;&lt;br/&gt;5, That, but for the said attainders, the said Barony of Monthermer would, on the death of the said Margaret, Countess of Salisbury, have fallen into abeyance between the two daughters and co-heirs of the said Henry Pole, namely, Katherine and Winifred;&lt;br/&gt;6, That the said Katherine married Francis Earl of Huntingdon, and that her representatives and co-heirs are the following persons&amp;#x2014;&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Edith Maud, Countess of Loudoun,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Elizabeth Frances, wife of John Wynford, Viscount St. Davids,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Lady Flora Anne Rawdon-Hastings,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Cecil Talbot Lord Grey de Ruthyn,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Constantine Mary Joseph Lubienski-Bodenham,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;May Flora Amy Kirwan,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Charles Earl of Romney;&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br/&gt;7, That the said Winifred married, first, Sir Thomas Hastings, Kt., and, secondly, Sir Thomas Barrington, Kt.; that she left issue by her second husband only, and that her representatives and coheirs are the following persons&amp;#x2014;&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;The Petitioner William Selby-Lowndes;&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Helen Clara, wife of Henry Mangles Denham;&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br/&gt;8, That the said Barony of Monthermer would, if the effect of the said attainders be removed, be in abeyance and at His Majesty's disposal.&lt;br/&gt;Read, and agreed to; and resolved and adjudged accordingly; and the Resolution and Judgment to be laid before His Majesty by the Lords with White Staves." title='BARONY OF MONTHERMER (1309).' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1928/dec/10/barony-of-monthermer-1309'></outline>
    <outline id='2285939' text='Report made from the Committee for Privileges that the Petitioner Constantine Mary Joseph Lubienski-Bodenham, has failed to show that there was treated any such Barony of Montacute (1357) or Pole of Montagu (1529) as he alleges:&lt;br/&gt;Read, and agreed to; and resolved and adjudged accordingly; and the Resolution and Judgment to be laid before His Majesty by the Lords with White Staves.' title='BARONY OF POLE OF MONTAGU OR MONTACUTE.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1928/dec/10/barony-of-pole-of-montagu-or-montacute'></outline>
    <outline id='2285940' text="1, That the Barony of Beauchamp is an ancient Barony in fee;&lt;br/&gt;2, That it is proved by the Writ of Summons, 1st June in the 37th year of King Edward III. and by other evidence adduced by the Petitioner that Roger Beauchamp, Lord Beauchamp, was summoned to Parliament and sat in Parliament as a Peer of the Realm, and that he was entitled to a Barony by Writ descendible to the heirs general of his body;&lt;br/&gt;3, That the Barony of Mordaunt is an ancient Barony in fee;&lt;br/&gt;4, That it is proved by the Writ of Summons, 27th April in the 28th year of King Henry VIII. and by other evidence adduced by the Petitioner that John Mordaunt, Lord Mordaunt, was summoned to Parliament and sat in Parliament as a Peer of the Realm, and that he was entitled to a Barony by Writ descendible to the heirs general of his body;&lt;br/&gt;5, That the said Barony of Beauchamp and the said Barony of Mordaunt descended to George, 5th Duke of Gordon and 13th Lord Mordaunt, and de jure 20th Lord Beauchamp, who died in the year 1836, when the said Baronies fell into abeyance between his five sisters and co-heirs, namely, Charlotte, Duchess of Richmond; Lady Madelina, wife first of Sir Robert Sinclair, Baronet, and secondly of Charles Fyshe Palmer; Susan, Duchess of Manchester; Louisa, Marchioness Cornwallis; and Georgians, Duchess of Bedford, or their respective heirs;&lt;br/&gt;6, That the co-heirs to the said five sisters of the said Duke of Gordon, as set forth hereafter, are the co-heirs to the Barony of Beauchamp and the Barony of Mordaunt, that is to say:&amp;#x2014;&#x000A;&lt;ol&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;(1) of Charlotte, Duchess of Richmond, Charles Henry, 8th Duke of Richmond;&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;(2) of Madelina, wife first of Sir Robert Sinclair, Baronet, Edith Charlotte Spencer-Smith, Claud Henry Maitland Lennox-Sinclair:&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;(3) of Susan, Duchess of Manchester, William Angus Drogo, 9th Duke of Manchester;&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;(4) of Louisa, Marchioness Cornwallis, James Richard Neville Stop-ford (commonly called Viscount Stopford), the Lady Rosemary Alexandra Eliot, the Lady Kathleen Blanche Lily Eliot, Alexander George Gordon Ross;&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;(5) of Georgiana, Duchess of Bedford, the Petitioner, Thomas Went-worth Russell;&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;br/&gt;7, That the said Barony of Beauchamp and the said Barony of Mordaunt are now in abeyance and at His Majesty's disposal:&lt;br/&gt;Read and agreed to; and resolved and adjudged accordingly; and the Resolution and Judgment to be laid before His Majesty by the Lords with White Staves." title='BARONIES OF BEAUCHAMP AND MORDAUNT.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1928/dec/10/baronies-of-beauchamp-and-mordaunt'></outline>
  </body>
</opml>
