<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Lords Report of 25 May 1932</title>
    <dateCreated>Wed, 25 May 1932 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='2290684' text='The LORD CHANCELLOR acquainted the House, that the Clerk of the Parliaments had laid upon the Table the Certificates from the Examiners that the Standing Orders applicable to the following Bills have been complied with:&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Ministry of Health Provisional Order Confirmation (Hertford) [H.L.],&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Ministry of Health Provisional Orders Confirmation (Elham Valley Water and Huts and Essex Water) [H. L.],&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Ministry of Health Provisional Order Confirmation (Hailsham Water) [H.L.],&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Ministry of Health Provisional Order Confirmation (Henley-on- Thames Water) [H.L.],&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Ministry of Health Provisional Orders (Derby and Stalybridge, Hyde, Mossley and Dukinfield Tramways and Electricity Board).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Also the Certificate that no Standing Orders are applicable to the following Bill:&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Ministry of Health Provisional Orders (Lindsey and Lincoln Joint Smallpox Hospital District and Wandle Valley Joint Sewerage District).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br/&gt;And also the Certificates that the further Standing Orders applicable to the following Bills have been complied with:&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Oakham Gas and Electricity,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Birkenhead Corporation,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Southern Railway,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Chesterfield and Bolsover Water.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The same were ordered to lie on the Table.' title='Preamble' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1932/may/25/preamble'></outline>
  </body>
</opml>
