<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Lords Report of 27 May 1941</title>
    <dateCreated>Tue, 27 May 1941 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='2298677' text='Returned from the Commons agreed to, with Amendments: The said Amendments considered and agreed to.&lt;br/&gt;The LORD CHANCELLOR acquainted the House, That the Clerk of the Parliaments had laid upon the Table the Certificate that no Standing Orders are applicable to the following Bill:&lt;br/&gt;Land Drainage Provisional Order.&lt;br/&gt;And also the Certificate that the further Standing Orders applicable to the following Bills have been complied with:&lt;br/&gt;Cannock Urban District Council.&lt;br/&gt;Railway Clearing System Superannuation Fund Corporation.&lt;br/&gt;The same were ordered to lie on the Table.' title='CAMBORNE WATER BILL. [H.L.]' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1941/may/27/camborne-water-bill-hl'></outline>
    <outline id='2298679' text="Report from the Committee of Selection, That the following Lords be proposed to the House to form the Select Committee for the Consideration of the' said Bill; namely:&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;E. Lucan,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Monkswell,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Kenilworth,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Belstead (&lt;i&gt;Chairman&lt;/i&gt;),&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Teviot:&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Agreed to; and the said Lords appointed accordingly. The Committee to meet on Tuesday the 10th of June next, at eleven o'clock; and all Petitions referred to the Committee, with leave to the Petitioners&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;296&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;praying to be heard by Counsel against the Bill to be heard as desired, as also Counsel for the Bill." title='EBBW VALE URBAN DISTRICT COUNCIL BILL. [H.L.]' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1941/may/27/ebbw-vale-urban-district-council-bill-hl'></outline>
    <outline id='2298680' text='Orders made by the Secretary of State for the Home Department, extending Section 1 of the Act to the&lt;br/&gt;Rural District of Barnet;&lt;br/&gt;Rural District of Erpingham (Parish of Holt):&lt;br/&gt;Laid before the House (pursuant to Act) for affirmative Resolution and ordered to lie on the Table.' title='SUNDAY ENTERTAINMENTS ACT, 1932.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1941/may/27/sunday-entertainments-act-1932'></outline>
    <outline id='2298681' text='Report from the Special Orders Committee, That they have examined the Special Order as required by the Standing Orders of the House; that in their opinion the Order raises important questions of policy and principle; that the Order is founded on precedent; that in the opinion of the Committee the Order cannot be passed by the House without special attention, but that no further inquiry is necessary before the House proceeds to a decision on the Resolution to approve the said Order:&lt;br/&gt;Read, and ordered to lie on the Table.' title='CENTRAL (COAL MINES) SCHEME (AMENDMENT) ORDER, 1941.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1941/may/27/central-coal-mines-scheme-amendment'></outline>
    <outline id='2298682' text='Message from the Commons for leave for the Viscount Bridgeman to attend to be examined as a witness before the Sub-Committee on Army Services of the Select Committee appointed by that House on National Expenditure. Leave given to his Lordship to attend, if he think fit; and a Message ordered to be sent to the Commons to acquaint them therewith.' title='NATIONAL EXPENDITURE.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1941/may/27/national-expenditure'></outline>
  </body>
</opml>
