<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Written Statement of 12 December 2002</title>
    <dateCreated>Thu, 12 Dec 2002 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='3478672' text='LORD CHANCELLOR'>
      <outline id='3478674' text='The Parliamentary Secretary, Lord Chancellor&apos;s Department (Ms Rosie Winterton)&lt;p&gt;I will tomorrow announce the Government&apos;s plans for implementing the judgments of the European Court of Human Rights in Goodwin v The United Kingdom and&lt;i&gt;"I"&lt;/i&gt; v The United Kingdom, following collective Ministerial consideration of the recommendations received from the Interdepartmental Working Group on Transsexual People. Copies of the announcement will be placed in the Libraries of both Houses, the Vote Office and the Printed Paper Office. The announcement will also be made available on the LCD website at www.lcd.gov.uk.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Transsexual People' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2002/dec/12/transsexual-people'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3478681' text='WORK AND PENSIONS'>
      <outline id='3478682' text='The Minister for Work (Mr. Nicholas Brown)&lt;p&gt;In the Pre-Budget Report of 27 November my right hon. Friend the Chancellor of the Exchequer said that:&lt;quote&gt;"Premiums for Employers&apos; Liability Compulsory Insurance (ELCI) have increased substantially in recent months, affecting many businesses, and especially Small and Medium Sized Enterprises in high-risk sectors. Following a request from the Government, Fhe Association of British Insurers (ABI) and trade associations are working to ensure that affordable cover is available. The Government has engaged with a wide range of stakeholders including the CBI, TUG and ABI to discuss the long-term issues affecting ELCI. The Department for Work and Pensions will now undertake a formal review of the operation of ELCI. Full details of this review will be announced shortly."&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;I am pleased now to announce the start of that review and its terms of reference.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The terms of reference of the review are to:&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Survey the operation of ELCI, taking into account any relevant aspects of the state benefits systems;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Assess the scale and nature of the current difficulties being experienced in relation to ELCI, in particular the extent to which these difficulties are likely to be short-term only, repeated in the future or permanent;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Make recommendations to Ministers as to the case or otherwise for reforming ELCI; and&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;If a case for reform is found, make recommendations as to the objectives, principles and high-level options for such reform.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;The review will be led by the Department for Work and Pensions, but will have the close involvement of a number of other Government Departments including HM Treasury, the Department of Trade and Industry and the Lord Chancellor&apos;s Department. It will report to Ministers in Spring 2003.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;col&gt;24WS&lt;/col&gt;&lt;p&gt;Written contributions to the work of the review are welcomed. Any such contributions should be sent to the ELCI REVIEW TEAM at the Department for Work and Pensions, The Adelphi, Level 2, 1&amp;#x2013;11 John Adam Street, London WC2N 6HT by Monday 17 February 2003. I have arranged for further details to be made available on the Department of Work and Pensions web site at: www.dwp.gov.uk/publications/2002/index.htm.&lt;/p&gt;' title="Employer's Liability" type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2002/dec/12/employers-liability'></outline>
      <outline id='3478683' text="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Work and Pensions (Malcolm Wicks)&lt;p&gt;The 89th Session of the International Labour Conference adopted a new Convention 184 on Safety and Health in Agriculture and a Recommendation 192 supplementing the Convention. My right hon. Friend the Secretary of State has today laid before Parliament a White Paper entitled 'International Labour Conference' (Cm 5703), copies of which have been placed in the Library.&lt;/p&gt;" title='International Labour Conference' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2002/dec/12/international-labour-conference'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3478684' text='PRIME MINISTER'>
      <outline id='3478685' text='The Prime Minister (Mr. Tony Blair)&lt;p&gt;The United Kingdom Delegation to the Parliamentary Assembly of the Council of Europe and the Assembly of Western European Union is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tony Lloyd Esq MP (Leader)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Full Representatives&lt;/i&gt;&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;David Atkinson Esq MP&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Malcolm Bruce Esq MP&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Sir Sydney Chapman MP&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Tom Cox Esq MP&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Terry Davis Esq MP&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Bill Etherington Esq MP&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Paul Flynn Esq MP&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Lord Judd&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Jim Marshall Esq MP&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Chris McCafferty MP&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Kevin McNamara Esq MP&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Eddie O&apos;Hara Esq MP&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Lord Russell-Johnston&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Sir Teddy Taylor MP&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Robert Walter Esq MP&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;John Wilkinson Esq MP&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Jimmy Wray Esq MP&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Substitute Members&lt;/i&gt;&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Tony Banks Esq MP&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Baroness Billingham&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Peter Bottomley Esq MP&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Lord Burlison&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Ann Cryer MP&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Jane Griffiths MP&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Michael Hancock Esq CBE MP&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Baroness Hooper&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Rt Hon Lord Kilclooney&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Baroness Knight of Collingtree DBE&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Khalid Mahmood Esq MP&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Humfrey Matins Esq MP&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;David Marshall Esq MP&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;image src="S6CV0396P0I0731"/&gt;&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;25WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Alan Meale Esq MP&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Gordon Prentice Esq MP&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Geraldine Smith MP&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Lord Tomlinson&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Dr Rudi Vis MP&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/p&gt;' title='Council of Europe and WEU Assembly' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2002/dec/12/council-of-europe-and-weu-assembly'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3478687' text='TRANSPORT'>
      <outline id='3478688' text='The Minister for Transport (Mr. John Spellar)&lt;p&gt;Statisticians in my Department have discovered errors in the urban/rural coding of the National Travel Survey data. A statistical release issued today presents revised data for key analyses for 1996&amp;#x2013;2001. Copies of the document have been placed in the Library of the House. The effects of the revisions are in general small, but they do affect the 10 Year Transport Plan indicator of rural bus service availability.&lt;/p&gt;' title='National Travel Survey Data' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2002/dec/12/national-travel-survey-data'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3478690' text='ENVIRONMENT, FOOD AND RURAL AFFAIRS'>
      <outline id='3478691' text='The Secretary of State for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs (Margaret Beckett):&lt;p&gt; I am pleased to report to the House that Government are today launching a Strategy for Sustainable Farming and Food. Later today, my right hon. Friend the Prime Minister and I will meet farmers and leaders of the food industry, rural, environmental and consumer bodies to discuss the new strategy and hear examples of good practice from across the food chain.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The strategy is further evidence of this Government&apos;s commitment to help deliver innovative and practical solutions to the challenges faced by those involved in the food chain. We do not underestimate the scale of these challenges: farm incomes remain under pressure and the foot and mouth disease outbreak also added to the momentum for change.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This strategy builds on the invaluable work conducted by the Policy Commission on the Future of Farming and Food to chart a way through these challenges. It sets out how industry, Government and consumers can work together to secure a profitable and internationally competitive future for our industries, whilst contributing to a better environment, improving nutrition and public health and prosperous communities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The strategy is backed by &amp;#x00A3;500 million from Government over the next three years. Subject to clearance under the usual EU procedures, this will provide:&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;a new entry-level agri-environment scheme: developing a simple scheme, suitable for all farmers which will pay them to farm in a more sustainable way, a core Curry Commission recommendation. Subject to successful piloting, this would be rolled out nationally in 2005.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Continued expansion of premium rural and environmental schemes like Countryside Stewardship: further work to improve the targeting of these schemes and make them simpler to applicants.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;26WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;A new &apos;whole farm&apos; approach to management and regulation: helping farmers plan their business as a whole to meet commercial and regulatory needs. The Government also plan to develop an audit-based approach to identify a farm&apos;s strengths and weaknesses as a basis for cutting red tape and the number of inspections required.&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;The new Agricultural Development Scheme: to improve competitiveness and marketing, including the priority areas of co-operation, farm assurance and spreading best practice.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;New funding to assist small regional food producers: extra money channelled through Food from Britain will enable it to work with Regional Development Agencies and the Regional Food Groups to expand this sector.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;More money for skills and training: knowing how to make a profit is fundamental, but respecting the environment and marketing require different skills and knowledge. We are reviewing training and advice services to help farmers develop and to exploit new opportunities.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;A Food and Health Action Plan: led by the Department of Health, to build on existing work to improve diet and nutrition, working with industry and consumers. The Plan will address food production and access as well as consumer information.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;A network of demonstration farms: in early 2003 a pilot network of farms will open their doors to share best practice and experiences.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Improving animal health and combating diseases: government is drawing up a new animal health and welfare strategy, has strengthened our emergency preparations and efforts to combat illegal meat imports.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition, the Government will ask the Institute of Grocery Distribution, in conjunction with the Food Chain Centre to undertake analysis of the impact of nutrition initiatives such as the National School Fruit Scheme and the five-a-day programme, on the food chain. This will highlight the commercial opportunities for English farmers and growers and other sectors of the food industry.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The strategy&amp;#x2014;which builds on the work of the Curry Commission&amp;#x2014;also underlines the need for farming to reconnect with its markets, better cooperation with the food chain, investment in people and technology and the adoption of environmental best practice. There are many examples of good practice to build upon:&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;More than 25,000 farm holdings in existing government environmental schemes.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;More than 400 farmers&apos; markets offering producers the opportunity to sell direct to their markets.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Over 78,000 farmers and growers are already members of farm assurance schemes with their produce branded under logos such as the Red Tractor and a number of industry initiatives being taken forward as part of the strategy:&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;The Food Chain Centre is working to improve the efficiency of the food chain through the provision of information, analysis and training and promotion of benchmarking and best practice.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;The Red Meat Industry Forum is working to improve efficiency and information flow in the red meat supply chain.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;English Farming and Food Partnerships, established by the industry with Defra support, will promote cooperation between farmers and between farmers and the rest of the food chain.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Assured Food Standards is working to broaden support for farm assurance within the food chain and to consolidate and develop assurance standards.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;image src="S6CV0396P0I0732"/&gt;&lt;col&gt;27WS&lt;/col&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Government have already announced that an independent Implementation Group, led by Sir Don Curry, will oversee the delivery of the strategy by both Government and industry.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Across England, regional delivery plans will be drawn up between government offices, Regional Development Agencies, local farmers, Rural Affairs Forums, Regional Chambers and a range of stakeholders, assisted by Sir Don Curry&apos;s Implementation Group.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The strategy is being laid before Parliament at 11.00am today and copies of this and the strategy related documents will be available in the Vote Office and the Libraries of the House at that time.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Sustainable Farming and Food Strategy' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2002/dec/12/sustainable-farming-and-food-strategy'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3478693' text='HOME DEPARTMENT'>
      <outline id='3478694' text="The Minister for Citizenship and Immigration (Beverley Hughes):&lt;p&gt; I have now received a copy of the first interim report prepared by the Race Monitor, Mary Coussey who was appointed this year to the post created under Section 19E of the Race Relations Act 1976, as amended by the Race Relations (Amendment) Act 2000.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The report is based on Ms Coussey's short time as Race Monitor and describes the visits to ports she has made so far and also gives an indication of her work programme for the rest of this financial year. She has not on this occasion made any recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under the terms of her appointment, the Race Monitor will be submitting a full annual report to Parliament in March next year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A copy of the interim report has been placed in the Library.&lt;/p&gt;" title='Race Monitor' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2002/dec/12/race-monitor'></outline>
      <outline id='3478695' text="The Secretary of State for the Home Department (Mr. David Blunkett):&lt;p&gt; I have considered the current arrangements on the use of intrusive surveillance of prison cells during hostage incidents and have concluded that the current arrangements do not assist the Prison Service in bringing a hostage incident to a safe conclusion. As things stand, the Prison Service Incident Commander is required to obtain my authorisation of any hostage incident where he considers it necessary to use surveillance in the management of the incident. This can take an hour or more, which could be a dangerous delay.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It makes no sense that the Prison Service is hampered in its safe management of the incident through concerns about the hostage-taker's privacy. The Prison Service has taken advice of the Chief Surveillance Commissioner, who concluded that a hostage-taker forfeits his right to privacy by engaging in this activity. I agree with this approach and I have instructed the Prison Service to alter procedures accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This will mean that in future the Director General or Deputy Director General will authorise applications for covert surveillance in hostage incidents. The Prison Service will however be required to maintain an audit trail of each authorisation demonstrating that the use of&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;28WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;surveillance was necessary, proportionate and consistent set out in the Regulation of Investigatory Powers Act 2000 (RIPA).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Should the Prison Service require the use of intrusive surveillance of a prisoner's cell for any other purpose, those applications will still come to me, as they are likely to raise issues of privacy.&lt;/p&gt;" title='Prisons (Hostage Incidents)' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2002/dec/12/prisons-hostage-incidents'></outline>
      <outline id='3478697' text='The Minister for Policing, Crime Reduction and Community Safety (Mr. John Denham):&lt;p&gt; Nicholas Hardwick has been appointed by Her Majesty as Chairman of the Independent Police Complaints Commission, which will replace the Police Complaints Authority on 1 April 2004 under the provisions of the Police Reform Act 2002. The Commission will exist in shadow form from 1 April 2003.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The appointment will be for five years in the first instance, and Mr Hardwick is expected to take up post on 1 February 2003.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nicholas Hardwick has been Chief Executive of the Refugee Council for the past eight years. Prior to this, he was Chief Executive of Centrepoint, the charity and Housing Association, from 1986 to 1995.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Independent Police Complaints Commission' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2002/dec/12/independent-police-complaints-commission'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3478698' text='EDUCATION AND SKILLS'>
      <outline id='3478699' text='The Minister for School Standards (Mr. David Miliband):&lt;p&gt; The Department for Education and Skills, in conjunction with the National College for School Leadership, carried out a wide-ranging consultation exercise earlier this year on our proposals to make the NPQH mandatory for first time headteachers. Over 650 responses were received from individuals, LEAs and the main teachers&apos; professional associations. Respondents were in favour of the NPQH being made mandatory for first time headteachers. Following this consultation, I have taken the decision that from 1 April 2004, all those appointed to their first headship post in the maintained sector, including nursery schools, and in non-maintained special schools, will be required to hold, or be working towards, the NPQH.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Working towards NPQH means that appointees must have at least successfully applied for a place on the course prior to their first headship appointment. The working towards arrangement is a transitional measure that will be in place for five years until 31 March 2009. After this date, the requirement to hold the NPQH will be a pre-appointment requirement for those appointed to their first headship post.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Those currently serving as headteachers will not be required to gain the qualification.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The NPQH provides aspiring headteachers with practical, professional training and the introduction of the mandatory requirement will give governing bodies a choice of qualified, well prepared new candidates for headship, in addition to any applications from experienced headteachers. We have carried out&#x000A;&lt;image src="S6CV0396P0I0733"/&gt;&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;29WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;extensive modelling work and we are confident that there will be enough holders of the NPQH by April 2004 to meet demand.&lt;/p&gt;' title='National Professional Qualification for Headship' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2002/dec/12/national-professional-qualification-for'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3478701' text='DEFENCE'>
      <outline id='3478702' text="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Defence (Dr. Lewis Moonie):&lt;p&gt; The Ministry of Defence has appointed Brey Utilities as the Preferred Bidder for Package A of Project Aquatrine, the MOD contract to provide water and wastewater services for the first pack age of work in the Midlands, Wales, and South West England. Project Aquatrine, one of the leading Public Private Partnership projects in the MOD, will transfer the responsibility for the maintenance and operation of all the Department's water and wastewater assets and infrastructure in Great Britain to private sector providers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This project will enable the transfer of environmental risk to those in the private sector who are best placed to manage it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is anticipated that Contract signature for the first package of work will be achieved in March 2003, following a three-month Preferred Bidder negotiation period. On this basis, it is expected the Contract will go live in December 2003. The Reserve Bidder for Package A is C2C.&lt;/p&gt;" title='Project Aquatrine Package A' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2002/dec/12/project-aquatrine-package-a'></outline>
      <outline id='3478704' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Defence (Dr. Lewis Moonie):&lt;p&gt; The competition announced in May 2000 has resulted in the selection of a preferred partner, Landmarc Support Services. Detailed negotiations will now take place to secure a contract to provide support services to the Army Training Estate with effect from 1 April 2003.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This will result in the transfer of approximately 1,400 Ministry of Defence civilian personnel to the private sector. The full protection of the Transfer of Undertaking (Protection of Employment) will apply. The departmental trades unions will be fully consulted in the normal way.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This contract will maintain existing command and control arrangements together with safety and public relations under MOD whilst introducing best commercial practice in all areas of non-core business. It will also lead to a more cost-effective professional and relevant means of service delivery.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Training Estate' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2002/dec/12/training-estate'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3478705' text='DEPUTY PRIME MINISTER'>
      <outline id='3478706' text="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State, Office of the Deputy Prime Minister (Mr. Christopher Leslie):&lt;p&gt; I have today placed in the Library of the House the Standards Board for England's Annual Report and Accounts for 2001&amp;#x2013;02.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;col&gt;30WS&lt;/col&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Report and Accounts cover the period when the Standards Board for England was being established and was putting in place its basic procedures. Since May 2002&amp;#x2014;shortly after the period covered in this report&amp;#x2014;all local authorities in England have been required to adopt a new Code of Conduct and it has been open to anyone to make an allegation of misconduct to the Standards Board.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Annual Report sets out very clearly the role of the Standards Board and describes the approach which the Board is seeking to take to handling complaints and to working with other regulators. Importantly, the report emphasises very strongly that the Standards Board will seek to work in partnership with councils, offering support and advice in a joint effort to promote high standards and confidence in local democracy.&lt;/p&gt;" title='Standard Board for England' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2002/dec/12/standard-board-for-england'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3478708' text='TRADE AND INDUSTRY'>
      <outline id='3478709' text="The Minister for E-Commerce and Competitiveness (Stephen Timms):&lt;p&gt; The Agency currently charges &amp;#x00A3;50 per hour plus VAT to provide advice and undertake remedial work at the request of business users where problems are identified in the own radio systems. The charge, which has not been increased since 1997, will be increased to &amp;#x00A3;57 per hour plus VAT and the charge for the use of the Agency's specialist mobile laboratory which is accredited to the United Kingdom Accreditation Service (ACAS) will be increased from &amp;#x00A3;1140 to &amp;#x00A3;1293 plus VAT per day with effect from 1 January 2003. The Agency does not charge business users for enforcement work which is carried out as part of its regulatory duties. The charge only applies for remedying problems which can be dealt with by filters and improvements to site and equipment.&lt;/p&gt;" title='Radiocommunications Agency' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2002/dec/12/radiocommunications-agency'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3478711' text='ENVIRONMENT, FOOD AND RURAL AFFAIRS'>
      <outline id='3478712' text='The Minister for Rural Affairs (Alun Michael):&lt;p&gt; I am pleased to announce that today we have published a summary of the results of the consultation, Towards a National Ambient Noise Strategy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There was very clear support for the Government&apos;s proposals for the development of an ambient noise strategy and I am pleased to confirm that we are taking the next steps to develop the strategy. These include: continuing the mapping already underway across England, the establishment of an expert working group to address the effects of noise and to establish cost-effective techniques to take action to improve or preserve noise levels, as appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A significant number of respondents indicated a need for a more strategic approach to neighbour noise. I agree that there is a need for a separate Neighbour Noise Strategy and as a first steps towards developing this I am pleased to launch a study to examine neighbour noise, both from the point of view of the noise makers and their victims. The research will generate appropriate and realistic options for action both to raise awareness and&#x000A;&lt;image src="S6CV0396P0I0734"/&gt;&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;31WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;to influence behaviour and, with many of the proposals identified during the consultation, should provide us with a solid basis to also develop a more strategic approach to the control of neighbourhood noise.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Ambient Noise Strategy' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2002/dec/12/ambient-noise-strategy'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3478713' text='HEALTH'>
      <outline id='3478714' text="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Health (Ms Hazel Blears):&lt;p&gt; The Human Fertilisation and Embryology Authority's 11th Annual Report and Accounts 2002 were laid before Parliament today.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Copies have been placed in the Library.&lt;/p&gt;" title='Human Fertilisation and Embryology Authority' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2002/dec/12/human-fertilisation-and-embryology'></outline>
      <outline id='3478715' text='The Secretary of State for Health (Mr. Alan Milburn):&lt;p&gt; The Government have decided to roll forward, unchanged, the maximum price scheme for generic medicines used in National Health Service primary care. This follows consultation with stakeholders that concluded on 29 November 2002.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;col&gt;32WS&lt;/col&gt;&lt;p&gt;The scheme was introduced in August 2000 as a result of price increases in the generics market that started in 1999. It was rolled forward in October 2001. The scheme has restored stability in the generics market and the NHS has saved some &amp;#x00A3;330 million annually as a result. The continuation of it will ensure that this stability continues and that the expenditure savings are maintained.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Generic Medicines' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2002/dec/12/generic-medicines'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3478717' text='NORTHERN IRELAND'>
      <outline id='3478718' text='The Secretary of State for Northern Ireland (Mr. Paul Murphy):&lt;p&gt; In order to ensure that security vetting is up to date and appropriate to current circumstances, and in view of recent events, I have asked for a review to be conducted of security vetting arrangements operating in Northern Ireland. This review will be led by the Northern Ireland Office, and includes senior representatives of the Northern Ireland Civil Service and the Police Service of Northern Ireland. The review will report to me with recommendations, and a plan for their implementation. I will inform the House of the outcome.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Security Vetting (Northern Ireland)' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2002/dec/12/security-vetting-northern-ireland'></outline>
    </outline>
  </body>
</opml>
