<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Written Statement of 12 May 2004</title>
    <dateCreated>Wed, 12 May 2004 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='3551596' text='INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT'>
      <outline id='3551597' text="The Secretary of State for International Development (Hilary Benn)&lt;p&gt;Having reviewed the higher education links programme, I have decided to continue with a redesigned programme, maintaining current levels of annual investment (&amp;#x00A3;3 million) but with some modifications to the existing scheme (which will end in March 2006). I expect the new scheme to commence in April 2005, with commitments being made over the following seven years (until March 2012).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The review report identified a number of strengths of the current scheme, but there were also some areas for improvement. The redesigned programme will tackle these issues.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The overall goal of the redesigned programme will be the reduction of poverty, the promotion of sustainable development in poor countries; and the building of human capital and skills. Only countries where DFID has bilateral country programmes will be eligible for funding; there will therefore be more emphasis on sub-Saharan Africa and low-income countries.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The revised programme should also support south-south links and links between southern partners and non-UK partners in the North, and it will also give more attention to science and technology. An independent evaluation will take place after five years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DFID's Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State has written to Professor Robert Boucher, vice-chancellor of the University of Sheffield and Chair of the existing Higher Education Links Steering Committee, setting out the features of the new scheme. His letter is on DFID's website. Copies have been placed in the Library of the House.&lt;/p&gt;" title='Higher Education Links Programme' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/may/12/higher-education-links-programme'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3551611' text='HOME DEPARTMENT'>
      <outline id='3551613' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for the Home Department (Caroline Flint)&lt;p&gt;The Home Office consultation paper on firearms controls is published today. Copies have been placed in the House Library. The paper invites a wide-ranging debate on the principles that should underpin firearms licensing and how the existing system might be improved. People will have until 31 August to respond.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Controls on Firearms' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/may/12/controls-on-firearms'></outline>
      <outline id='3551614' text='The Minister for Citizenship and Immigration (Mr. Desmond Browne)&lt;p&gt;The Government are firmly committed to maintaining effective immigration&lt;col&gt;12WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;controls while at the same time ensuring that genuine passengers are able to pass through our ports with the least possible inconvenience.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The number of people arriving at UK airports who are found to be inadmissible is unacceptably high. Certain nationals, who are required to hold a valid visa to enter the UK, may transit this country for up to 24 hours without a visa. This provides a relatively easy and inexpensive way for those who are intent on circumventing our immigration controls to do so. Last year we introduced measures to tackle this problem with the introduction of a direct airside transit visa (DATV) requirement for 23 nationalities. For the three months following the introduction on 16 October of DATV regimes for Angola, Bangladesh, Cameroon, India, Lebanon and Pakistan, the number of asylum applications made at ports by those nationalities fell by 58 per cent. DATV requirements have been shown to work and we now need to take further action to strengthen the regime. Intelligence would suggest that some individuals travelling on Kenyan and Tanzanian documents to the United Kingdom are destroying these documents either en route or after gaining entry to the UK, and are then applying for asylum as Somalian nationals. Therefore from 00.01 hours on Thursday 13 May all nationals of Kenya and Tanzania wishing to transit the UK will require a visa to do so.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To avoid undue hardship for those who had already made their travel plans, we have agreed to operate a grace period. Until 23.59 hours on Wednesday 19 May, any transit passenger who bought their ticket on or before 12 May will not be refused entry solely on the basis of not holding a valid transit visa. Also, any person on the return leg of a journey they commenced before 13 May and who passed through the UK on the outward leg of their journey will be allowed to transit the UK without a visa until 23.59 on 9 June.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In parallel with those measures, we are introducing changes to the arrangements that allow certain groups of low risk passenger to be exempt from a transit visa requirement if they are in possession of specific documents. The exemption applying to those holding a valid visa for the United States of America or Canada has been widened to enable visa-free transit of the United Kingdom irrespective of the routing chosen to reach the USA or Canada. Similarly, a passenger returning from a trip to the USA or Canada will be able to transit the United Kingdom irrespective of the routing they choose providing they are in possession of an onward air ticket and they are not seeking to transit the UK more than six months since they last entered the USA or Canada with a valid visa.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have also decided to introduce an exemption for holders of diplomatic or official passports issued by the Vietnamese Government, who will be exempt from the requirement to hold a visa when transiting the UK for up to 24 hours.&lt;/p&gt;' title='United Kingdom Immigration Control' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/may/12/united-kingdom-immigration-control'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3551615' text='HEALTH'>
      <outline id='3551616' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Health (Miss Melanie Johnson)&lt;p&gt;The national service framework for coronary heart disease, published in&lt;image src="S6CV0421P2I0014"/&gt;&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;13WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;March 2000, heralded a new era for the development of fast and modern services for the prevention and treatment of heart disease.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With significant progress now secured for patients with coronary artery disease, the national health service is now well placed to deliver similar improvements for patients with arrhythmia and with syndromes that can lead to sudden cardiac death.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dr. Roger Boyle, the national director for heart disease, is today launching a consultation paper on a new national service framework chapter for these conditions. The views received will be considered by a new expert group that is being established by the Department of Health to take forward the task of writing the new national service framework chapter.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Government have already shown their determination to tackle coronary heart disease through the publication of the national service framework. The prospect of a new the national service framework chapter setting out the standards and models of care for patients with arrhythmia marks a major step forwards for cardiac patients in England.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Copies of "New NSF Chapter on Arrhythmias and Sudden Cardiac Death: A Consultation Paper", have been placed in the Library.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Cardiac Arrhythmias and Sudden Cardiac Death' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/may/12/cardiac-arrhythmias-and-sudden-cardiac'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3551619' text='NEW NSF CHAPTER ON ARRHYTHMIAS AND SUDDEN CARDIAC DEATH'>
      <outline id='3551620' text='&lt;i&gt;Introduction&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The national service framework for coronary heart disease, published in March 2000, heralded a new era for the development of fast and modern services for the prevention and treatment of heart disease. Four years on from its publication, the combination of a clear set of national standards, sustained levels of investment and reform and redesign of services has delivered real improvements for patients. Primary care has made extraordinary progress in ensuring that patients with heart disease are on the right combination of drugs to lengthen their lives. Waiting times for bypass surgery and angioplasty have fallen dramatically. Patients with a heart attack are treated quickly with life-saving clot busting drugs.&lt;br/&gt;With significant progress now secured for patients with coronary artery disease, the NHS is now well placed to deliver similar improvements for patients with arrhythmia and with syndromes that can lead to sudden cardiac death. These patients have already benefited from the substantial growth in NHS staff, equipment and facilities. The Government have now agreed to drive further progress for these patients by working with patients, families and NHS professionals to develop new NSF standards or practice recommendations for these conditions.&lt;br/&gt;The strength of the existing NSF has been that it is based on the views of clinicians, patients and their families. Its aims and approaches have credibility with those who deliver it and those who benefit from it. The aim of this consultation paper is to invite initial comments from everyone with an interest in these issues to ensure that we can build a similar consensus for this new NSF chapter.&lt;br/&gt;The views received will be considered by a new expert group that is being established by the Department of Health to take forward the task of writing the new NSF chapter. Detailed membership of the group will be published shortly, but it will include patients, relatives of patients, patient organisations, professional bodies, experts in the field, health service managers and other Government Departments with an interest. The group will be chaired by Dr. Roger Boyle, national clinical director for heart disease, and is aiming to produce the new chapter within twelve months.&lt;br/&gt;The attached paper sets out the proposed scope of the work and how we propose to take the work forward. In addition to your comments on this way forward, we would welcome specific views on:&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Whether the scope covers all the aspects of these conditions which the new NSF chapter should cover;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Examples of existing good practice in the management of these conditions that might inform the work of the expert group;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Views on the obstacles to progress on developing state of the art services for these patients, and suggestions on how these might be overcome;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Areas where further research is needed to improve understanding of these conditions;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Views on what the immediate, medium term and long term priorities should be for these services; and&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;How best to ensure that the patient, family and carer perspective is at the forefront of policy and service development.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Details of how to respond to this consultation are included at the end of this document.' title='A CONSULTATION PAPER' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/may/12/a-consultation-paper'></outline>
      <outline id='3551622' text="&lt;i&gt;Membership&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The group will be composed of external stakeholders similar to the expert external reference groups who helped create the national service framework for coronary heart disease with voluntary and professional organisations being invited to take part. Patients, cardiologists, GPs, nurses and members of voluntary and professional organisations (including CRY, the Ashley Jolly SAD Trust, Hearty Voices, the British Cardiac Society and the British Pacing and Electrophysiology Group) will be asked to join. Representatives from Wales, Scotland and Northern Ireland will also be invited.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;i&gt;Other Stakeholders&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br/&gt;We will be holding a stakeholders' event during the consultation period to raise awareness of the new group and invite wider consultation and participation. This will help to ensure that the key issues are covered and that the outcomes address the needs of all the interested parties. If you would be interested in attending this event, please e-mail your name and contact details to &lt;u&gt;Jennifer.francis@doh.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/u&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;i&gt;Proposed Workstreams&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br/&gt;We propose four key workstreams for the expert group to manage its work, sudden cardiac death and screening; acute care; cardiac interventions; and patient involvement and support.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;i&gt;Sudden Cardiac Death and Screening&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br/&gt;It is estimated that 200&amp;#x2013;400 young people die from sudden cardiac death syndrome each year. Dari Taylor MP's recent Private Members Bill highlighted a number of important issues that the new NSF chapter will need to address. These include:&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Raising awareness of signs and symptoms of conditions that may lead to sudden cardiac death;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Support for those who have lost relatives or friends;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Considering the feasibility of guidelines on how these deaths are certified;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Setting standards or practice recommendations around how suspected cases are treated in primary care;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Promoting models of good practice for local use; and&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Design of an evidence-based protocol that clarifies when it is recommended that patients and/or their relatives should ideally be invited for screening.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;i&gt;Acute Care&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br/&gt;For many patients the first sign of their cardiac condition is an emergency admission to hospital. Those who know they have the condition but whose care is not well managed may also need urgent treatment. Arrhythmia is consistently in the top 10 reasons for hospital admission, using up significant A&amp;amp;E time and bed days. This workstream will cover:&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Design of a care pathway showing the ideal treatment of those who require emergency care for these conditions;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Outlining what information patients require when in hospital to help them successfully manage their condition after discharge;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Considering the feasibility of setting or practice recommendations around readmission rates for those with conditions which could be better managed; and&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Development of a set of audit indicators and suitable performance indicators that might be used locally around emergency care for those with arrhythmias and conditions which may lead to sudden cardiac death.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;i&gt;Cardiac Interventions&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Since publication of the NSF there have been significant improvements in both the technology and the clinical capacity to intervene to treat arrhythmias and related conditions, giving more options for this group of patients in terms of both diagnosis and treatment. New emerging technologies such as the implantable cardioverter defibrillator (ICD) or more sophisticated pacing devices, with good medical evidence for their use, has given the cardiologist many more treatment options in 2004 compared to the 1990s. This workstream will cover:&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Design of a care pathway for the diagnosis, management and treatment of arrhythmias and conditions which may lead to sudden cardiac death (considering cardiomyopathies, atrial fibrillation and electrical conduction disorders);&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Identification of models which deliver the appropriate interventions reliably; and&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Development of audit measures and suitable performance indicators around the care and treatment of people with these conditions, which might be used locally.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;i&gt;Patient Involvement and Support&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Patients with a lifelong or long to term cardiac problem need continuing support to help them manage their condition and live as full a life as possible. Assistance also needs to be available for carers and family members&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;16WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;where they wish it. Patients need to be involved in decisions about their own care and in helping to shape the planning of services. This workstream will include:&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Design of care pathway for management and control of specific conditions (for example, atrial fibrillation);&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Development of guidance on monitoring patients with chronic conditions;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Identifying effective ways of providing emotional support to patients and their relatives where appropriate; and&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Identifying effective means of involving patients in their own care and in influencing the way that services are provided.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;i&gt;Next Steps&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Ideas and proposals should reach the project team by 4 August 2004 at the latest.&lt;br/&gt;The Department of Health would welcome contributions throughout the consultation. Emerging issues and contributions will be fed into the discussions of the expert group and used to develop the proposed new NSF chapter on arrhythmias and sudden cardiac death.&lt;br/&gt;The information you send to us may need to he passed to colleagues within the Department of Health and/or published in a summary of responses to this consultation. We will assume that you are content for us to do this and, if you are replying by e-mail, that your consent overrides any confidentiality disclaimer that is generated by your organisation's IT system, unless you specifically include a request to the contrary in the main text of your submission to us.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;i&gt;Contact Details&lt;/i&gt;&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;New NSF Consultation&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Heart Team&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Department of Health&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;403 Wellington House&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;133&amp;#x2013;155 Waterloo Road&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;London SE1 8UG&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Email: chdnsf@doh.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Website: &lt;u&gt;www.dh.gov.uk/consultations&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Telephone: 0207 972 4513&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Annex: Consultation Criteria&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Code of Practice on Consultation&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br/&gt;We will ensure that this consultation meets the following criteria:&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Consult widely throughout the process, allowing a minimum of twelve weeks for written consultation at least once during the development of the policy.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Be clear about what your proposals are, who may be affected, what questions are being asked and the timescale for responses.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Ensure that your consultation is clear, concise and widely accessible.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Give feedback regarding the responses received and how the consultation process influenced the policy.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Monitor your department's effectiveness at consultation, including through the use of a designated consultation coordinator.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Ensure your consultation follows better regulation best practice, including carrying out a regulatory impact assessment if appropriate.&lt;/quote&gt;" title='EXPERT GROUP' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/may/12/expert-group'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3551624' text='WORK AND PENSIONS'>
      <outline id='3551625' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Work and Pensions (Mr. Chris Pond)&lt;p&gt;On behalf of my right hon. Friend the Secretary of State for Work and Pensions, the benefit fraud inspectorate (BFI) inspection report on Milton Keynes Council was published today and copies of the report have been placed in the Library.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following the housing Green Paper "Quality and Choice: A Decent Home for All", published in April 2000, the Department for Work and Pensions developed a performance framework for housing benefits. The performance standards for housing benefits allow local authorities to make a comprehensive self-assessment of whether they deliver benefit effectively and securely. They are the standards that the Department for Work and Pensions expects local authorities to aspire to and achieve in time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 2002&amp;#x2013;03, Milton Keynes council administered some &amp;#x00A3;48.3 million in housing benefits, about 18.5 per cent. of its gross revenue expenditure. BFI inspected Milton Keynes council against the performance standards for housing benefits, and concludes that the council&apos;s benefits service had not reached standard in any of the seven functional areas&amp;#x2014;strategic management, customer services, processing of claims, working with landlords, internal security, counter-fraud and overpayments.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The report finds that the benefits service had been given low priority within the council in the past and performance overall had been poor. However, several significant changes had taken place over the past two years, including a complete service restructure and the replacement of its benefits IT system.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The December 2002 comprehensive performance assessment classified the council as poor. Since then progress had been made across many areas of the performance standards. The claims backlog had reduced considerably since 2002 but it was still having an impact on claims processing times. Times taken to process new benefit claims and changes of circumstances were reducing but still did not meet the performance standards. Processing times for new claims had reduced to an average 49 days from 68 days compared with the performance standard of 36 days. The council processed changes of circumstances in 13 days, compared to the standard of nine days.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The council&apos;s counter-fraud performance was strong, with successful sanctions against benefit fraudsters and excellent relations with the Department&apos;s counter fraud investigation service. However, the council needs to develop procedural guidance for investigators and do more management checks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The council did not have an overpayment policy or debt recovery strategy. However, actions plans, developed with the support of BFI&apos;s performance improvement action team, had been in place since March 2003 and these were having a positive impact on the recovery of overpaid benefits.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;col&gt;18WS&lt;/col&gt;&lt;p&gt;The council further demonstrated its commitment to improvement by entering into a public private partnership agreement, in January 2004, to deliver a number of its services, including benefits.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The major challenge for the council now is to continue to improve its benefits processing performance. This will be helped by a more systematic approach to planning, backed up by improvements to its management information and reporting systems.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The report makes recommendations to help the council address weaknesses and to further improve the administration of housing benefit and council tax benefit, as well as counter-fraud activities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;My right hon. Friend the Secretary of State is now considering the report and will be asking the council for its proposals in response to the BFI&apos;s findings and recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Benefit Fraud Inspectorate Report (Milton Keynes Council)' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/may/12/benefit-fraud-inspectorate-report-milton'></outline>
      <outline id='3551626' text='The Secretary of State for Work and Pensions (Mr. Andrew Smith)&lt;p&gt;In December 2002, the Government published the Pensions Green Paper: "Simplicity, Security and Choice: Working and Saving for Retirement." Chapter 6: "Extending Opportunities for Older Workers" sets out a range of measures to increase employment among older workers, which is considered essential to address the pensions challenge.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Over 50s Outreach pilot is one of these measures and supports PSA target 4c: In the three years to 2006, to increase the employment rate of people aged 50 and over, taking account of the economic cycle, and significantly reduce the difference between their employment rate and the overall rate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Research has shown that contact from Jobcentre Plus can concern people aged over 50, particularly those on benefits such as incapacity benefit (IB), income support (IS), and severe disability allowance. Clients on these benefits may be concerned about Jobcentre Plus forcing them into work, or reducing their benefits, if queries about work are made, in spite of assurances from Jobcentre Plus to the contrary.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The pilot involves external organisations acting as an intermediary between the Jobcentre and the customer. These organisations will:&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;contact people aged 50 and over who are not in work, and encourage their use of Jobcentre Plus services or volunteering opportunities;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;market the back to work help, employment and volunteering opportunities available and overcoming the concerns of some IB and IS clients that their benefits may be affected if they approach a Jobcentre Plus office with a work related enquiry; and&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;promote the back to work help available through Jobcentre Plus to people aged 50 and over who may not be aware of this help or who do not normally have contact with Jobcentre Plus.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The evaluation of these pilots will demonstrate what methods of contact and awareness raising worked most successfully to encourage people who would not otherwise have asked about or taken up Jobcentre Plus services and work or volunteering opportunities to do so. The methods that are most successful can then be disseminated throughout Jobcentre Plus to be incorporated into the continuous improvement of their services.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;image src="S6CV0421P2I0017"/&gt;&lt;col&gt;19WS&lt;/col&gt;&lt;p&gt;The pilot will run in seven Jobcentre Plus regions for two years and commenced in April 2004. The organisations that successfully tendered for the pilot are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;table&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Region&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;District&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Partner Organisation&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Wales&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Cardiff &amp;amp; Vale&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Working Links&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;North East&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Newcastle &amp;amp; North&lt;lb/&gt; Tyneside&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Age Concern North&lt;lb/&gt; Tyneside&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;North West&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Wigan&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Adactus Housing&lt;lb/&gt; Group&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;North West&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Liverpool&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Forty Plus&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;West Midlands&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Dudley &amp;amp; Sandwell&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Pertemps&lt;lb/&gt; Employment&lt;lb/&gt; Alliance&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Scotland&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Lanarkshire&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;South Lanarkshire&lt;lb/&gt; Council&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Scotland&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Fife&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Instep&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/p&gt;' title='Over 50s Outreach Pilot' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/may/12/over-50s-outreach-pilot'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3551629' text='DEPUTY PRIME MINISTER'>
      <outline id='3551630' text='The Deputy Prime Minister (Mr. John Prescott)&lt;p&gt;The Office of the Deputy Prime Minister is today launching the design coding pilots programme. Kate Barker in her review of housing supply identified significant levels of undersupply, and a lack of certainty and speed in the planning process. This programme aims to test the use of design coding as a means to accelerate the delivery of housing while maintaining the high level of design content required to ensure that new development contributes fully towards improving the quality of our villages, towns and cities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A design code is a set of specific rules or requirements to guide the physical development of a site or a place. The aim of design coding is to provide clarity as to what constitutes acceptable design quality, and thereby a level of certainty for developers and the local community alike, that can help to accelerate the delivery of good quality new development.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Operating over a number of different development circumstances, the pilots will be carefully monitored over the coming year and will provide the means to evaluate various models and approaches for developing, adopting and implementing design codes. Depending on the outcome, the review may inform the development of future planning policy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Government wish to test the potential for design coding as a means of delivering higher quality development at greater speed through the planning process. The development projects which they have chosen to monitor and evaluate in order to assess the effectiveness of the coding approach are subject to approval through the planning system in the normal way. It is possible that some of these projects may, at a later stage, be referred to the Secretary of State for decision (for example on whether an application should be called in for his own determination or on an appeal against the decision of a local planning authority).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For the avoidance of doubt, partners involved in the design coding exercise should understand that the Office of the Deputy Prime Minister is encouraging the use of&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;20WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;coding on these sites without prejudice to any decisions the Secretary of State may be required to take through his formal role in the planning process. The fact that development is proposed in accordance with a design code does not imply that the Secretary of State is content for any particular development proposal to proceed. Any decisions which fall to be made will be taken having regard to the facts and merits of the case, taking into consideration all relevant matters.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Design Coding (Pilot Programme)' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/may/12/design-coding-pilot-programme'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3551631' text='ENVIRONMENT, FOOD AND RURAL AFFAIRS'>
      <outline id='3551632' text='The Minister for the Environment (Mr. Elliot Morley)&lt;p&gt;Following the incident in 2003 in which four redundant US naval vessels were transferred from the USA to Hartlepool without the necessary authorisations for them to be dismantled there, I announced in the House on 3 November that&lt;quote&gt;"We will require a full evaluation of the situation to set out why the problems have arisen and what lessons we can learn."&amp;#x2014;[&lt;i&gt;Official Report&lt;/i&gt;, 3 November 2003; Vol. 412, c. 535&amp;#x2013;42.]&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Subsequently, the Environment Agency has carried out its own internal Review of the events surrounding the incident. Similarly, DEFRA commissioned its own Review. Both Reviews&apos; terms of reference were to identify lessons that could be learned from the incident.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The reports of each Review are available on my Department&apos;s &lt;u&gt;website www.defra.gov.uk&lt;/u&gt;, and have today been placed in the Libraries of both Houses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Government will carefully consider the conclusions and recommendations of both Reviews, which were broadly compatible, before issuing a further statement.&lt;/p&gt;' title='US Naval Ships' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/may/12/us-naval-ships'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3551635' text='TRADE AND INDUSTRY'>
      <outline id='3551636' text='The Secretary of State for Trade and Industry (Ms Patricia Hewitt)&lt;p&gt;Creating a fair and more inclusive society is fundamental to building a prosperous country. Equality and human rights must be at the heart of modern Britain. Discrimination has no place in our society.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We need a step change in the fight against discrimination. We need to create a culture of respect based on equal value, the dignity and worth of every individual.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Extending opportunities to all means removing unfair barriers. Delivering prosperity for all means harnessing the skills and potential of every member of society, whatever their background. Equality and human rights matter to everyone&amp;#x2014;they are not minority concerns.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last October, we announced the Government&apos;s plan for a single equality body to realise this vision of a fairer, more inclusive and prosperous Britain. Today we are setting out how we propose to deliver that vision. Our White Paper on: "Fairness for All: A New Commission for Equality and Human Rights", detailing our proposals has been placed in the Libraries of both Houses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;image src="S6CV0421P2I0018"/&gt;&lt;col&gt;21WS&lt;/col&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is a bold and innovative plan. The new Commission will have a dual remit to challenge discrimination and promote equality of opportunity and human rights.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We believe there is an opportunity for it to create a strong, proactive relationship with private sector employers, both large and small, and service providers to maximise progress towards equality.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Commission for Equality and Human Rights will bring together the work of three existing equality commissions&amp;#x2014;the Commission for Racial Equality (CRE), the Equal Opportunities Commission (EOC) and the Disability Rights Commission (DRC). It will also support new laws outlawing workplace and vocational training discrimination on grounds of religion or belief, sexual orientation and, in time, age.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We owe the existing Commissions a debt of gratitude for their work in changing attitudes and practice on disability, gender and racial equality and their hard work in bringing us to this point. Now we are ready to adopt fresh approaches to meet new challenges.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In making today&apos;s announcement, we have taken account of the responses to the Government&apos;s consultation document Equality and Diversity: "Making It Happen" and the Sixth report of the Joint Committee on Human Rights.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The White Paper owes much to the discussions of the CEHR Taskforce whose membership reflected the broad range of interests involved in this issue, including the existing Commissions. The Taskforce advised Government on a number of key issues for the new body through an innovative and open process.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We are grateful to all its members for so willingly sharing their depth of expertise. Their participation and contributions are an important aspect of our wider policy development, and have informed the White Paper significantly.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The White Paper sets out the proposed vision, functions, powers and governance arrangements for the CEHR. It outlines the work the body will be expected to carry out to support key stakeholders; it sets out the Scottish and Welsh dimensions of the new body and also maps out the road to implementation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;The Core Duties of the New Body&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The proposed core duties of the CEHR set out in the document will be to:&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Encourage awareness and good practice on equality and diversity.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Promote equality of opportunity between people in the different groups protected by discrimination law.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Promote awareness and understanding of human rights.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Work towards the elimination of unlawful discrimination and harassment.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Promote good relations among different communities and between these communities and wider society.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;col&gt;22WS&lt;/col&gt;&lt;p&gt;Additional responsibilities will include:&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Keeping relevant legislation under review.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Acting as a centre of expertise on equality and human rights.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Key Issues in the White Paper&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The increasing complexities of our diverse society require appropriate tools to challenge discrimination and enforce the law. Our proposals build on the existing Commissions&apos; powers and create a selection of tools for the CEHR to enforce discrimination law effectively.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The White Paper sets out detailed proposals on the role of the CEHR in promoting a culture of respect for human rights and improving public service delivery. The human rights framework will also be used to help balance potentially conflicting rights.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Government propose that the CEHR will have an obligation to consult stakeholders on its strategic plan. The CEHR will clearly set out how, when and with whom, it intends to consult.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To ensure experience and expertise is not lost from the existing Commissions, the CEHR Board will also, for a transitional period, have three additional reserved seats for a commissioner from the CRE, the DRC, and the EOC.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The White Paper recognises the distinctive issues that arise for disabled people in the establishment of the CEHR and the need to ensure effective transition from the DRC. The Government propose that the nominated transitional DRC commissioner is appointed to sit on the CEHR board until vesting day. After that date, we will ensure, via a statutory requirement, that at least one person who has, or has had, a disability is appointed to the CEHR Board.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The White Paper also proposes a Disability Committee, with disabled people making up the majority of its members. This Committee will have authority to set strategy, develop policy and monitor delivery for specific areas of the CEHR&apos;s disability work, and will be subject to a mandatory review after 5 years of the continuing case for the committee. This will give disabled people a clear voice in the CEHR&apos;s work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We recognise the unique and important local racial equality work that has historically been supported by the CRE. The White Paper proposes a commitment to maintaining existing levels of support for local race work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The White Paper also confirms that the Government will start detailed. preparatory work on the nature and shape of a new statutory duty on public bodies to promote gender equality in fulfilment of its longstanding commitment to introduce such a duty. This duty will oblige public bodies to ensure that their actions (either as employers or service providers) will promote equality of opportunity between women and men and make public services more responsive to their different needs. Part of the preparatory work will involve learning from the experiences of the public sector duty introduced for race through the Race Relations (Amendment) Act 2000, and will be informed by the proposed public sector duty for disability. The Government will consult interested stakeholders and parties as this work develops.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;image src="S6CV0421P2I0019"/&gt;&lt;col&gt;23WS&lt;/col&gt;&lt;p&gt;Establishing the CEHR will require primary legislation. We intend to bring a Bill before Parliament as soon as Parliamentary time allows. The Commission will not be fully operational before the end of 2006 at the earliest. A planning phase, beginning shortly, will become progressively more detailed over the next 12&amp;#x2013;18 months. Plans for bringing in the "new strands" of equality, religion and belief, sexual orientation and age, are outlined in the White Paper.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Government look forward to consulting and debating on all these issues, and particularly welcomes views responding to the White Paper&apos;s questions on regional and local issues and how the body should work with stakeholders. We welcome the eleventh report of the Joint Committee on Human Rights on the structures, functions and powers of the new body, and will consider this further alongside responses to the consultation.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Commission for Equality and Human Rights' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/may/12/commission-for-equality-and-human-rights'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3551639' text='FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH AFFAIRS'>
      <outline id='3551640' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs (Mr. Chris Mullin)&lt;p&gt;The British Council, although not a Government Department, receives a substantial grant-in-aid from the Foreign and Commonwealth Office. The Council regularly organises or sponsors exhibitions overseas of works of art loaned from National Galleries and private collections in the United Kingdom. It provides certain assurances or guarantees in respect of loss or damage while these works are on loan.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the year ended 31 March 2004, the British Council provided such assurances to six national lenders and undertakings to 206 private lenders. The value of the contingent liabilities that remained outstanding as at 31 March 2004 was &amp;#x00A3;2,807,500 in respect of national lenders and &amp;#x00A3;7,247,453 in respect of private lenders.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Overseas Art Exhibitions' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/may/12/overseas-art-exhibitions'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='2580162'>
      <outline id='2580164' text='The Lord President of the Council (Baroness Amos)&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08262"&gt;My right honourable friend the Secretary of State for International Development has made the following Statement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08263"&gt;Having reviewed the Higher Education Links programme, I have decided to continue with a redesigned programme, maintaining current levels of annual investment (&amp;#x00A3;3 million) but with some modifications to the existing scheme (which will end in March 2006). I expect the new scheme to commence in April 2005, with commitments being made over the following seven years (until March 2012).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08264"&gt;The review report identified a number of strengths of the current scheme, but there were also some areas for improvement. The redesigned programme will tackle these issues.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08265"&gt;The overall goal of the redesigned programme will be the reduction of poverty, the promotion of sustainable development in poor countries and the building of human capital and skills. Only countries where DfID has bilateral country programmes will be eligible for funding. There will therefore be more emphasis on sub-Saharan Africa and low-income countries.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08266"&gt;The revised programme should also support south-south links and links between southern partners and non-UK partners in the north, and it will also give more attention to science and technology. An independent evaluation will take place after five years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08267"&gt;DfID&apos;s Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State has written to Professor Robert Boucher, Vice-Chancellor of the University of Sheffield and chair of the existing Higher Education Links steering committee, setting out the features of the new scheme. His letter is on DfID&apos;s website. Copies have been placed in the Library of the House.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Higher Education Links Programme' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/may/12/higher-education-links-programme'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='2580174'>
      <outline id='2580175' text='The Secretary of State for Constitutional Affairs and Lord Chancellor (Lord Falconer of Thoroton)&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08268"&gt;My right honourable friend the Secretary of State for Trade and Industry and Minister for Women and Equality (Ms Patricia Hewitt) made the following Statement in the other place today.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08269"&gt;Creating a fair and more inclusive society is fundamental to building a prosperous country. Equality and human rights must be at the heart of modern Britain. Discrimination has no place in our society.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;col&gt;WS 8&lt;/col&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08270"&gt;We need a step change in the fight against discrimination. We need to create a culture of respect based on equal value and the dignity and worth of every individual.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08271"&gt;Extending opportunities to all means removing unfair barriers. Delivering prosperity for all means harnessing the skills and potential of every member of society, whatever their background. Equality and human rights matter to everyone&amp;#x2014;they are not minority concerns.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08272"&gt;Last October, we announced the Government&apos;s plan for a single equality body to realise this vision of a fairer, more inclusive and prosperous Britain. Today we are setting out how we propose to deliver that vision. Our White Paper on &lt;i&gt;Fairness for All: A New Commission for Equality and Human Rights&lt;/i&gt; detailing our proposals has been placed in the Libraries of both Houses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08273"&gt;It is a bold and innovative plan. The new commission will have a dual remit to challenge discrimination and promote equality of opportunity and human rights.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08274"&gt;We believe there is an opportunity for it to create a strong, proactive relationship with private sector employers, both large and small, and service providers to maximise progress towards equality.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08275"&gt;The Commission for Equality and Human Rights will bring together the work of three existing equality commissions&amp;#x2014;the Commission for Racial Equality (CRE), the Equal Opportunities Commission (EOC) and the Disability Rights Commission (DRC). It will also support new laws outlawing workplace and vocational training discrimination on grounds of religion or belief, sexual orientation and, in time, age.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08276"&gt;We owe the existing commissions a debt of gratitude for their work in changing attitudes and practice on disability, gender and racial equality and their hard work in bringing us to this point. Now we are ready to adopt fresh approaches to meet new challenges.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08277"&gt;In making today&apos;s announcement, we have taken account of the responses to the Government&apos;s consultation document &lt;i&gt;Equality and Diversity: Making It Happen&lt;/i&gt; and the sixth report of the Joint Committee on Human Rights.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08278"&gt;The White Paper owes much to the discussions of the CEHR task force whose membership reflected the broad range of interests involved in this issue, including the existing commissions. The task force advised government on a number of key issues for the new body through an innovative and open process.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08279"&gt;We are grateful to all its members for so willingly sharing their depth of expertise. Their participation and contributions are an important aspect of our wider policy development, and have informed the White Paper significantly.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08280"&gt;The White Paper sets out the proposed vision, functions, powers and governance arrangements for the CEHR. It outlines the work the body will be expected to carry out to support key stakeholders; it sets out the Scottish and Welsh dimensions of the new body and maps out the road to implementation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;image src="S5LV0661P0I1038"/&gt;&lt;col&gt;WS 9&lt;/col&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08281"&gt;&lt;i&gt;The Core Duties of the New Body&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08282"&gt;The proposed core duties of the CEHR set out in the document will be to:&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Encourage awareness and good practice on equality and diversity.&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Promote equality of opportunity between people in the different groups protected by discrimination law.&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Promote awareness and understanding of human rights.&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Work towards the elimination of unlawful discrimination and harassment.&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Promote good relations among different communities and between these communities and wider society.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08283"&gt;Additional responsibilities will include:&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Keeping relevant legislation under review.&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Acting as a centre of expertise on equality and human rights.&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08284"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Key Issues in the White Paper&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08285"&gt;The increasing complexities of our diverse society require appropriate tools to challenge discrimination and enforce the law. Our proposals build on the existing commissions&apos; powers and create a selection of tools for the CEHR to enforce discrimination law effectively.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08286"&gt;The White Paper sets out detailed proposals on the role of the CEHR in promoting a culture of respect for human rights and improving public service delivery. The human rights framework will also be used to help balance potentially conflicting rights.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08287"&gt;The Government propose that the CEHR will have an obligation to consult stakeholders on its strategic plan. The CEHR will clearly set out how, when and with whom it intends to consult.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08288"&gt;To ensure experience and expertise is not lost from the existing commissions, the CEHR board will also, for a transitional period, have three additional reserved seats for a commissioner from the CRE, the DRC and the EOC.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08289"&gt;The White Paper recognises the distinctive issues that arise for disabled people in the establishment of the CEHR and the need to ensure effective transition from the DRC. The Government propose that the nominated transitional DRC commissioner is appointed to sit on the CEHR board until vesting day. After that date, we will ensure, via a statutory requirement, that at least one person who has, or has had, a disability is appointed to the CEHR board.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08290"&gt;The White Paper also proposes a disability committee, with disabled people making up the majority of its members. This committee will have authority to set strategy, develop policy and monitor delivery for specific areas of the CEHR&apos;s disability work, and will he subject to a mandatory review after&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;WS 10&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;five years of the continuing case for the committee. This will give disabled people a clear voice in the CEHR&apos;s work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08291"&gt;We recognise the unique and important local racial equality work that has historically been supported by the CRE. The White Paper proposes a commitment to maintaining existing levels of support for local race work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08292"&gt;The White Paper also confirms that the Government will start detailed, preparatory work on the nature and shape of a new statutory duty on public bodies to promote gender equality in fulfilment of its longstanding commitment to introduce such a duty. This duty will oblige public bodies to ensure that their actions (as either employers or service providers) will promote equality of opportunity between women and men and make public services more responsive to their different needs. Part of the preparatory work will involve learning from the experiences of the public sector duty introduced for race through the Race Relations (Amendment) Act 2000, and will be informed by the proposed public sector duty for disability. The Government will consult interested stakeholders and parties as this work develops.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08293"&gt;Establishing the CEHR will require primary legislation. We intend to bring a Bill before Parliament as soon as parliamentary time allows. The commission will not be fully operational before the end of 2006 at the earliest. A planning phase, beginning shortly, will become progressively more detailed over the next 12 to 18 months. Plans for bringing in the new strands of equality, religion and belief, sexual orientation and age are outlined in the White Paper.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08294"&gt;The Government look forward to consulting and debating on all these issues and particularly welcome views responding to the White Paper&apos;s questions on regional and local issues and how the body should work with stakeholders. We welcome the 11th report of the Joint Committee on Human Rights on the structures, functions and powers of the new body, and will consider this further alongside responses to the consultation.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Commission for Equality and Human Rights' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/may/12/commission-for-equality-and-human-rights'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='2580177'>
      <outline id='2580178' text='The Minister of State, Foreign and Commonwealth Office (Baroness Symons of Vernham Dean)&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08295"&gt;The British Council, although not a government department, receives a substantial grant-in-aid from the Foreign and Commonwealth Office. The council regularly organises or sponsors exhibitions overseas of works of art loaned from national galleries and private collections in the United Kingdom. It provides certain assurances or guarantees in respect of loss or damage while these works are on loan.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08296"&gt;In the year ended 31 March 2004, the British Council provided such assurances to six national lenders and undertakings to 206 private lenders. The value of the contingent liabilities that remained outstanding as at 31 March 2004 was &amp;#x00A3;2,807,500 in respect of national lenders and &amp;#x00A3;7,247,453 in respect. of private lenders.&lt;/p&gt;' title='British Council Art Exhibitions Overseas' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/may/12/british-council-art-exhibitions-overseas'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='2580179'>
      <outline id='2580180' text='The Minister of State, Home Office (Baroness Scotland of Asthal)&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08297"&gt;The Home Office consultation paper on firearms controls is published today. Copies have been placed in the House Library. The paper invites a wideranging debate on the principles that should underpin firearms licensing and how the existing system might be improved. People will have until 31 August to respond.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Firearms' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/may/12/firearms'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='2580181'>
      <outline id='2580182' text='The Minister of State, Office of the Deputy Prime Minister (Lord Rooker)&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08298"&gt;My right honourable friend the First Secretary of State and Deputy Prime Minister has made the following Written Ministerial Statement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08299"&gt;The Office of the Deputy Prime Minister is today launching the design coding pilots programme. Kate Barker in her review of housing supply identified significant levels of undersupply, and a lack of certainty and speed in the planning process. This programme aims to test the use of design coding as a means to accelerate the delivery of housing while maintaining the high level of design content required to ensure that new development contributes fully towards improving the quality of our villages, towns and cities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08300"&gt;A design code is a set of specific rules or requirements to guide the physical development of a site or a place. The aim of design coding is to provide clarity as to what constitutes acceptable design quality, and thereby a level of certainty for developers and the local community alike, that can help to accelerate the delivery of good quality new development.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08301"&gt;Operating over a number of different development circumstances, the pilots will be carefully monitored over the coming year and will provide the means to evaluate various models and approaches for developing, adopting and implementing design codes. Depending on the outcome, the review may inform the development of future planning policy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08302"&gt;The Government wish to test the potential for design coding as a means of delivering higher quality development at greater speed through the planning process. The development projects which we have chosen to monitor and evaluate in order to assess the effectiveness of the coding approach are subject to approval through the planning system in the normal way. It is possible that some of these projects may, at a later stage, be referred to the Secretary of State for decision (for example on whether an application&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;WS 12&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;should be called in for his own determination or on an appeal against the decision of a local planning authority).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08303"&gt;For the avoidance of doubt, partners involved in the design coding exercise should understand that the Office of the Deputy Prime Minister is encouraging the use of coding on these sites without prejudice to any decisions the Secretary of State may be required to take through his formal role in the planning process. The fact that development is proposed in accordance with a design code does not imply that the Secretary of State is content for any particular development proposal to proceed. Any decisions which fall to be made will be taken having regard to the facts and merits of the case, taking into consideration all relevant matters.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Design Coding' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/may/12/design-coding'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='2580183'>
      <outline id='2580184' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State, Department of Health (Lord Warner)&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08304"&gt;My honourable friend the Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Public Health (Miss Johnson) has made the following Written Ministerial Statement today.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08305"&gt;The National Service Framework for coronary heart disease, published in March 2000, heralded a new era for the development of fast and modern services for the prevention and treatment of heart disease.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08306"&gt;With significant progress now secured for patients with coronary artery disease, the National Health Service is now well placed to deliver similar improvements for patients with arrhythmia and with syndromes that can lead to sudden cardiac death.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08307"&gt;Dr Roger Boyle, the national director for heart disease, is today launching a consultation paper on a new national service framework chapter for these conditions. The views received will be considered by a new expert group which is being established by the Department of Health to take forward the task of writing the new national service framework chapter.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08308"&gt;The Government have already shown their determination to tackle coronary heart disease through the publication of the National Service Framework. The prospect of a new national service framework chapter setting out the standards and models of care for patients with arrhythmia marks a major step forward for cardiac patients in England.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08309"&gt;Copies of &lt;i&gt;New NSF Chapter on Arrhythmias and Sudden Cardiac Death: A Consultation Paper&lt;/i&gt; have been placed in the Library.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Cardiac Arrhythmias and Sudden Cardiac Death' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/may/12/cardiac-arrhythmias-and-sudden-cardiac'></outline>
    </outline>
  </body>
</opml>
