<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Written Statement of 25 May 2004</title>
    <dateCreated>Tue, 25 May 2004 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='3551881' text='ENVIRONMENT, FOOD AND RURAL AFFAIRS'>
      <outline id='3551883' text='The Minister for Rural Affairs and Local Environmental Quality (Alun Michael)&lt;p&gt;I have set the Pesticides Safety Directorate the following performance targets for 2004&amp;#x2013;05.&lt;quote&gt;To evaluate pesticide approval applications and contribute to the EU review programme.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;To develop policy initiatives to reduce the negative impact of pesticides and to encourage alternative control measures.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;To ensure UK objectives are reflected in EU legislation and regulation.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;&gt;To monitor actively pesticide use and limit illegal use by taking appropriate enforcement action.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;To increase public awareness and understanding of safe use and regulation of pesticides.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;To recover the full cost of our operations from the industry and DEFRA, and achieve efficiency savings.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Further details are given in the business plan, a copy of which has been provided to the Library of the House.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Pesticides Safety Directorate' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/may/25/pesticides-safety-directorate'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3551903' text='INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT'>
      <outline id='3551905' text="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for International Development (Mr. Gareth Thomas)&lt;p&gt;The Department for International Development (DFID) will be increasing its support to Vietnam to &amp;#x00A3;40 million in 2004&amp;#x2013;05 and to &amp;#x00A3;60 million in 2005&amp;#x2013;06 to help Vietnam meet its challenges. Our new Country Assistance Plan for Vietnam (copies of which I have placed in the Library) will support the Government of Vietnam's own strategies for growth and poverty reduction. It sets out three key objectives for our contribution to the collective development effort. First, we will promote fair, efficient and effective use of public financial resources. Second, we will seek to strengthen the Government of Vietnam's efforts to achieve social and economic development that includes all groups of society. Third, we will support Vietnam in its transition to market-based economy. A fourth pillar of our programme in Vietnam will be to help improve the effectiveness of the international development effort.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;col&gt;76WS&lt;/col&gt;&lt;p&gt;DFID intends to provide &amp;#x00A3;20 million a year over the next three years in the form of poverty reduction budget support. This commitment will constitute the single largest element of our programme in Vietnam and will provide a significant boost to Vietnam's overall reform programme. I can also announce today a &amp;#x00A3;500,000 project to help improve the quality of public investment in Vietnam by supporting the introduction of a modern and efficient inspection system in the Ministry of Planning and Investment.&lt;/p&gt;" title='Vietnam Programme' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/may/25/vietnam-programme'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3551908' text='DEPUTY PRIME MINISTER'>
      <outline id='3551910' text="The Minister for Local and Regional Government (Mr. Nick Raynsford)&lt;p&gt;I have today received the independent boundary committee's final reports and recommendations on options for unitary local government for each of the existing two-tier county areas in the three northern regions. We welcome the completion of this significant step towards the holding of referendums for elected regional assemblies in the autumn.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We will now carefully consider the recommended options and any representations about them that are made to us before taking decisions about the options that will be included in a draft order. We do not intend to take decisions about the options until 6 July.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, those who wish to make representations to us may do so. We will have regard to those before deciding what options we propose to put to electors. These options, together with the date of the referendums, will be contained in an order to be made following parliamentary approval.&lt;/p&gt;" title="Local Government Reviews (Boundary Committee's Final Recommendations" type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/may/25/local-government-reviews-boundary'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3551913' text='FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH AFFAIRS'>
      <outline id='3551914' text="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs (Mr. Bill Rammell)&lt;p&gt;The Government have recently issued a licence for the BBC to export to Iran up to three civilian armoured vehicles which are of military specification. Although military rated, these vehicles are manufactured for civilian use and would provide essential protection for journalists working for the BBC. Her Majesty's Government believed that an exception to the UK unilateral arms embargo should be made to allow the free and secure movement of journalists throughout the region and that approval of the application was otherwise consistent with the consolidated EU and national arms export licensing criteria. Specific provisos about usage and disposal are attached and Her Majesty's Government are satisfied that there is minimal risk of diversion to a military end-use or for use in internal repression.&lt;/p&gt;" title='Iran (Export Licence Application)' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/may/25/iran-export-licence-application'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='2580273'>
      <outline id='2580275' text='The Lord President of the Council (Baroness Amos)&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08505"&gt;My honourable friend the Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for International Development has made the following Statement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08506"&gt;The Department for International Development (DAD) will be increasing its support to Vietnam to &amp;#x00A3;40 million in 2004&amp;#x2013;05 and to &amp;#x00A3;60 million in 2005&amp;#x2013;06 to help Vietnam to meet its challenges. Our new country assistance plan for Vietnam (copies of which I have placed in the Library) will support the Government of Vietnam&apos;s own strategies for growth and poverty reduction. It sets out three key objectives for our contribution to the collective development effort. First, we will promote fair, efficient and effective use of public financial resources. Secondly, we will seek to strengthen the Government of Vietnam&apos;s efforts to achieve social and economic development which includes all groups of society. Thirdly, we will support Vietnam in its transition to a market-based economy. A fourth pillar of our programme in Vietnam will be to help to improve the effectiveness of the international development effort.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;col&gt;WS 52&lt;/col&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08507"&gt;DfID intends to provide &amp;#x00A3;20 million a year over the next three years in the form of poverty reduction budget support. This commitment will constitute the single largest element of our programme in Vietnam and will provide a significant boost to Vietnam&apos;s overall reform programme. I can also announce today a &amp;#x00A3;500,000 project to help to improve the quality of public investment in Vietnam by supporting the introduction of a modern and efficient inspection system in the Ministry of Planning and Investment.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Vietnam Programme' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/may/25/vietnam-programme'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='2580289'>
      <outline id='2580290' text='The Minister of State, Foreign and Commonwealth Office (Baroness Symons of Vernham Dean)&lt;p id="S5LV0661P0-08508"&gt;The Government have recently issued a licence for the BBC to export to Iran up to three civilian armoured vehicles which are of military specification. Although military rated, these vehicles are manufactured for civilian use and would provide essential protection for journalists working for the BBC. Her Majesty&apos;s Government believed that an exception to the UK unilateral arms embargo should be made to allow the free and secure movement of journalists throughout the region and that approval of the application was otherwise consistent with the consolidated EU and national arms export licensing criteria. Specific provisos about usage and disposal are attached and Her Majesty&apos;s Government are satisfied that there is minimal risk of diversion to a military end-use or for use in internal repression.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Iran: Export Licence Application' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/may/25/iran-export-licence-application'></outline>
    </outline>
  </body>
</opml>
