<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Lords Report of 23 June 1921</title>
    <dateCreated>Thu, 23 Jun 1921 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='2231309' text='A Bill to amend the law relating to the manufacture, sale and supply of intoxicating liquor, and to provide for the popular control thereof, and for other purposes incidental thereto&amp;#x2014;Was presented by the Lord Bishop of Oxford; read 1&amp;#x00AA;to be printed: and to be read 2&amp;#x00AA;on Thursday the 7th of July next.' title='LIQUOR (POPULAR CONTROL) BILL. [H.L.]' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1921/jun/23/liquor-popular-control-bill-hl'></outline>
    <outline id='2231310' text='The Committee to be proposed by the Committee of Selection.' title='BURNLEY CORPORATION BILL.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1921/jun/23/burnley-corporation-bill'></outline>
    <outline id='2231311' text='CARDIFF GAS BELL.'>
      <outline id='2231312' text='Committees to meet on Tuesday next.' title='WEST IIAM CORPORATION BILL. [H.L.]' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1921/jun/23/west-iiam-corporation-bill-hl'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='2231313' text='Committee to meet on Tuesday next.' title='PILOTAGE PROVISIONAL ORDERS (NO. 3) BILL.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1921/jun/23/pilotage-provisional-orders-no-3-bill'></outline>
    <outline id='2231314' text='Reported from the Joint Committee, with Amendments, and re-committed to a. Committee of the Whole House.' title='EDUCATION (CONSOLIDATION) BILL. [H.L.]' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1921/jun/23/education-consolidation-bill-hl'></outline>
    <outline id='2231315' text='Reported, with Amendments.&lt;br/&gt;[&lt;i&gt;At Judicial Sitting on June 27.&lt;/i&gt;]' title='HASTINGS TRAMWAYS (EXTENSION) BILL. [H.L.]' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1921/jun/23/hastings-tramways-extension-bill-hl'></outline>
    <outline id='2231316' text="Petition of Edith Maud, in her own right Countess of Loudoun, and of Elizabeth Frances, Viscountess St. Davids, claiming to be two of the co-heirs to the Earldoms of Warwick and Salisbury, to His Majesty, praying His Majesty to determine in favour of the said Edith Maud,&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;806&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;Countess of Loudoun, the abeyance now existing in the said Earldom of Warwick, and to determine in favour of the said Elizabeth Frances, Viscountess St. Davids, the abeyance now existing in the said Earldom of Salisbury; and in case it should be held that the said Earldoms are affected by the attainder of Margaret, Countess of Salisbury, or by any other attainders referred to in the said Petition, to be graciously pleased to give directions for the introduction of a Bill into Parliament to relieve the Petitioners from the effects of the attainder or attainders as aforesaid, in so far as it or they relates or relate to the said honours and dignities of the Earldom of Warwick and the Earldom of Salisbury, together with His Majesty's reference thereof to this House, and the report of the Attorney-General thereon thereunto annexed: Presented (by command); read, and referred to the Committee for Privileges to consider and report." title='EARLDOMS OF WARWIC.K AND SALISBURY.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1921/jun/23/earldoms-of-warwick-and-salisbury'></outline>
    <outline id='2231317' text="Petition of Edith Maud, in her own right Countess of Loudoun, and of Elizabeth Frances, Viscountess St. Davids, claiming to be two of the co-heirs to the Baronies of Montagu, Montacute, Monthermer and Pole of Montagu, to His Majesty, praying His Majesty to determine in favour of the said Edith Maud, Countess of Loudoun, the abeyance now existing in the said Baronies of Montacute and Pole of Montagu, and to determine in favour of the said Elizabeth Frances, Viscountess St. Davids, the abeyance now existing in the said Baronies of Montagu and Monthermer, and in case it should be held that the Baronies or any of them are affected by the attainder of Margaret, Countess of Salisbury, or any other attainders referred to in the said Petition, to be graciously pleased to give directions for the introduction of a Bill into Parliament to relieve the Petitioners from the effects of the attainder or attainders as aforesaid, in so far as it or they relates or relate to the said honours and dignities of Montagu, Montacute, Monthermer or Pole of Montagu respectively, together with His Majesty's reference thereof to this House, and the report of the Attorney-General thereunto annexed: Presented (by command); read, and referred to the Comirittee for Privileges to consider and report." title='BARONIES OF MONTAGU, MONTACUTE, MONTHERMER AND POLE OF MONTAGU.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1921/jun/23/baronies-of-montagu-montacute-monthermer'></outline>
  </body>
</opml>
