<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Lords Report of 7 May 1940</title>
    <dateCreated>Tue, 07 May 1940 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='2308389' text='Returned from tie Commons, agreed to, with Amendments; the said Amendments considered, and agreed to.&lt;br/&gt;The LORD CHANCELLOR&lt;member&gt;The LORD CHANCELLOR&lt;/member&gt; acquainted the House, That the Clerk of the Parliaments had laid upon the Table the Certificate from the Examiners that the further Standing Orders applicable to the following Bill have been complied with: Birmingham Corporation.&lt;br/&gt;Also the Certificate that no Standing Orders are applicable to the following Bill: Ministry of Health Provisional Order (Blackburn).&lt;br/&gt;And also the Certificate that the Standing Orders have not been complied with in respect of the Petition for the following Bill: Saint Mary Magdalene Hospital (Newcastle-upon-Tyne).&lt;br/&gt;The same were ordered to lie on the Table.' title='COMMERCIAL GAS BILL. [H.L.]' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1940/may/07/commercial-gas-bill-hl'></outline>
    <outline id='2308391' text='Report from, That the Standing Orders not complied with in respect of the Petitions for the following Bills ought to be dispensed with, and leave given to introduce the Bills: Saint Mary Magdalene Hospital (Newcastle-upon-Tyne); Mid-Wessex Water.&lt;br/&gt;And that the Standing Orders not complied with in respect of the Petition for additional provision the Taunton Corporation Bill ought to be dispensed with;&lt;br/&gt;Read, and agreed to.' title='STANDING ORDERS COMMITTEE.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1940/may/07/standing-orders-committee'></outline>
    <outline id='2308393' text="MONMOUTHSHIRE AND SOUTH WALES EMPLOYERS' MUTUAL INDEMNITY SOCIETY, LIMITED BILL. [H.L.]">
      <outline id='2308395' text="Report from the Committee of Selection, That the following Lords be proposed to the House to form the Select Committee&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;266&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;for the consideration of the said Bills, namely:&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;V. Buckmaster,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Hare (&lt;i&gt;E. Listowel&lt;/i&gt;),&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. O'Hagan,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Macmillan (&lt;i&gt;Chairman&lt;/i&gt;),&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Belstead:&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/ul&gt;&#x000A;Agreed to; and the said Lords appointed accordingly. The Committee to meet on Wednesday, the 29th instant, at eleven o'clock; and all Petitions referred to the Committee, with leave to the Petitioners praying to be heard by Counsel against the Bills to be heard as desired, as also Counsel for the Bills." title='SOUTH-EASTERN GAS CORPORATION, LIMITED (ASSOCIATED COMPANIES) BILL. [H.L.]' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1940/may/07/south-eastern-gas-corporation-limited'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='2308397' text='Report from the Special Orders Committee, That they have examined the Order as required by the Standing Orders of the House; that in their opinion the provisions of the Order raise important questions of policy and principle; that the Order complies with the terms of Section 15 of the Agriculture Act, 1937, under which it is submitted for approval, but is not founded on that in the opinion of the Committee the Order cannot be passed by the House without special attention, but that no further inquiry is necessary before the House proceeds to a decision on the Resolution to approve the said Order:&lt;br/&gt;Read, and ordered to lie on the Table.' title='LAND DRAINAGE GRANTS (POSTPONEMENT OF PRESCRIBED DATE) ORDER, 1940.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1940/may/07/land-drainage-grants-postponement-of'></outline>
    <outline id='2308398' text='Report from the Special Orders Committee, That they have examined the Order as required by the Standing Orders of the House, that in their opinion the provisions of the Order raise important question of policy and principle&amp;#x2014;the Order complies with the terms of Section 15 of the Agriculture Act, 1937, under which it is submitted for approval, but is not founded on precedent&amp;#x2014;that in the opinion of the Committee the Order cannot be pressed by the House without special attention, but that no further inquiry is necessary before the House proceeds to a decision on the Resolution to approve the said Order:&lt;br/&gt;Read, and ordered to lie on the Table.' title='LAND FERTILITY SCHEME (POSTPONEMENT OF PRESCRIBED DATE) ORDER, 1940.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1940/may/07/land-fertility-scheme-postponement-of'></outline>
  </body>
</opml>
