<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Lords Report of 26 June 1934</title>
    <dateCreated>Tue, 26 Jun 1934 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='2245810' text="Report made from the Lord Chancellor that Eric FitzGerald, Viscount Dillon in the Peerage of Ireland, has established his succession to the Viscounty of Dillon, and his right to vote at any elections of Representative Peers for Ireland which may be held in future under the Statutes in force relating thereto, to the satisfaction of the Lord Chancellor: Read, and ordered to lie on the Table.&lt;br/&gt;Ordered, That the Report of the Lord Chancellor of the United Kingdom, made to the House of Lords this day, that Eric FitzGerald, Viscount Dillon in the Peerage of Ireland, has established his succession to the Viscounty of Dillon, and his right to vote at any elections of Representative Peers for Ireland, which may be held in future under the Statutes relating thereto, be sent to the Clerk of the Crown in Ireland, together with a certificate stating that such Report has been made, and that the House has ordered it to be sent to the said Clerk of the Crown in Ireland.&lt;br/&gt;The LORD CHANCELLOR&lt;member&gt;The LORD CHANCELLOR&lt;/member&gt; acquainted the House, That the Clerk of the parliaments had laid upon the Table the Certificate from the Examiners that the further Standing Orders applicable to&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;170&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;the following Bill have been complied with:&lt;br/&gt;London Passenger Transport Board.&lt;br/&gt;And also the Certificate that the Standing Orders applicable to the following Bills have been complied with:&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Mexborough and Swinton Traction (Trolley Vehicles) Provisional Order,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;St. Helen's Corporation (Trolley Vehicles) Provisional Order,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Southend-on-Sea Corporation (Trolley Vehicles) Provisional Order,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Nottingham Corporation (Trolley Vehicles) Provisional Order.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The same were ordered to lie on the Table." title='VISCOUNT DILLON.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1934/jun/26/viscount-dillon'></outline>
    <outline id='2245822' text='Reported with Amendments.' title='STOCKPORT CORPORATION BILL.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1934/jun/26/stockport-corporation-bill'></outline>
    <outline id='2245824' text='Brought from the Commons; read 1&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;; and referred to the Examiners.' title='LONDON PASSENGER TRANSPORT BOARD (INTERIM FINANCIAL ARRANGEMENTS) BILL.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1934/jun/26/london-passenger-transport-board-interim'></outline>
    <outline id='2245825' text='Message to the Commons for leave for the Right Honourable Wilfred Guild Normand, K.C., Lord Advocate, to attend the Select Committee.' title='SHERIFFDOM OF PERTH AND ANGUS ORDER, 1934.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1934/jun/26/sheriffdom-of-perth-and-angus-order-1934'></outline>
  </body>
</opml>
