<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Written Statement of 11 March 2003</title>
    <dateCreated>Tue, 11 Mar 2003 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='3598564' text='HOME DEPARTMENT'>
      <outline id='3598565' text='The Minister for Citizenship and Immigration (Beverley Hughes)&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-04874"&gt;In the light of concern that some asylum applicants from other countries are posing falsely as nationals from Iraq, we have decided to pilot language analysis testing for use in cases where appropriate when a person claiming Iraqi nationality applies for asylum. Language testing arrangements in such cases will start on 12 March 2003 and continue for an initial period of one month.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-04875"&gt;The purpose of language analysis is to provide expert evidence which helps to identify the place of origin of asylum seekers. Language analysis is used in a number of European countries, and the results have been generally successful. In the UK language analysis has been used already in the case of asylum claims made by nationals claiming to be from Afghanistan, Somalia or Sri Lanka. It was found to be a valuable aid in the asylum consideration process, clearly identifying in many instances that the applicant was not of the nationality he or she claimed to be, or not from the area of the country from which they claimed to originate. Language analysis also benefited genuine applicants by confirming the information they gave about their nationality.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-04876"&gt;The extension of language testing to nationals from Iraq is being given legal effect today by an authorisation made by myself under section 19D of the Race Relations Act 1976. Where there are objective reasons for doubting the nationality of a person claiming to be from Iraq, the authorisation will enable staff in the Immigration and Nationality Directorate to request the applicant to undertake a further interview which will be taped and sent to a language expert for analysis. Individuals may refuse to consent to this further interview (which will be conducted at the initial screening stage), but this refusal can be taken into account when determining whether the applicant has established the facts of their case. This may lead to their claim being refused.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-04877"&gt;We will review the need for this further authorisation later in the year. Independent scrutiny of the likely effect of authorisations made by Ministers and how they are operated in practice by officials is exercised by the race monitor, Mary Coussey, who reports to Parliament via the Secretary of State.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-04878"&gt;A copy of the addition authorisation has been place in the Library of the House. Any additional or amended authorisations will also be placed in the Library.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Asylum Seekers (Language Analysis)' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/mar/11/asylum-seekers-language-analysis'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3598566' text='DEPUTY PRIME MINISTER'>
      <outline id='3598567' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State, Office of the Deputy Prime Minister (Mr. Christopher Leslie)&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-04879"&gt;The Office of the Deputy Prime Minister consulted last year on proposals to amend and consolidate the Accounts and Audit Regulations, which set out the duties of local authorities on the keeping of accounts. The three-month consultation period provided for in our consultation came to an end in December. Having carefully considered representations made, I have today laid the Accounts and Audit Regulations 2003 (SI 2003 No. 533), to implement the changes. The aims of the amendments are to update the rules governing the way local authorities keep accounts, to reduce unnecessary bureaucracy so the accounting burden is proportionate to the size of the authority, and to make improvements to provisions relating to local authority corporate governance and accountability. Various changes have been made to the original proposals to reflect the concerns of consultees. The regulations will come into effect on 1 April 2003. Guidance will be issued to assist authorities in implementing the regulations.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Local Authorities (Accounting Arrangements)' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/mar/11/local-authorities-accounting-arrangements'></outline>
      <outline id='3598568' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State, Office of the Deputy Prime Minister (Mr. Tony McNulty)&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-04880"&gt;I am pleased to announce the Government&apos;s acceptance of all the recommendations of the Advisory Panel on Standards (APOS) for the Planning Inspectorate Agency, as set out in their Ninth Annual Report published in November 2002. APOS jointly advises the First Secretary of State and the First Minister of the Welsh Assembly Government on the maintenance and improvement of quality standards for the planning inspectorate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-04881"&gt;The panel&apos;s main finding was that the demanding quality standard target, that 99 per cent. of the Inspectorate&apos;s casework should be free from justified complaints, was being maintained. However, the panel also made a number of recommendations on steps that could be taken to further enhance quality standards. These included improvements to training and procedures, that have already been implemented, and the introduction of arrangements to correct simple errors within decision letters which is included in the Planning and Compulsory Purchase Bill currently before Parliament. The remaining recommendations are all part of a continuous process of training, development and monitoring, such as the introduction of a rolling customer satisfaction survey, to build on the experiences of users of the system.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-04882"&gt;I am particularly pleased to note the Panel&apos;s comments on the good work of the Inspectorate in encouraging diversity within the organisation, in promoting training interchange schemes to develop staff and in encouraging electronic access to information for the public and other interested parties through its planning portal project. These initiatives are playing an important part in the Government&apos;s wider initiative to promote planning as a positive instrument and to involve the community more effectively.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;image src="S6CV0401P0I0821"/&gt;&lt;col&gt;9WS&lt;/col&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-04883"&gt;I commend the work of the panel and thank them for their helpful recommendations, and look forward to seeing further results of their hard work over the next year.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Planning Inspectorate' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/mar/11/planning-inspectorate'></outline>
      <outline id='3598569' text='The Deputy Prime Minister (Mr. John Prescott)&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-04884"&gt;I am today publishing the Government&apos;s response to the House of Lord&apos;s constitution Committee&apos;s report: "Devolution: Inter-Institutional Relations in the United Kingdom". The Government&apos;s response is published as CM5780 and copies have been placed in the Libraries of both Houses. The response will also be made available on the Office of the Deputy Prime Minister&apos;s website.&lt;/p&gt;' title='House of Lords Report on Devolution' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/mar/11/house-of-lords-report-on-devolution'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3598570' text='HEALTH DEPARTMENT'>
      <outline id='3598571' text='The Secretary of State for Health (Mr. Alan Milburn)&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-04885"&gt;Pursuant to the dissolution of 59 National health Service trusts on 1 April 2002 and their reconfiguration through the establishment of nineteen new NHS trusts, I propose to create originating capital for the new NHS trusts equal to the net assets transferred to them and therefore to remit the outstanding debt of the dissolved trusts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-04886"&gt;A number of primary care trusts were also established during the year. Public dividend capital is not required for the establishment of new primary care trusts as they are subject to a different financial regime. Net assets transferred from dissolving NHS trusts to primary care trusts are reflected in the general fund of the primary care trust.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-04887"&gt;These operations involved no overall loss to the Exchequer. Her Majesty&apos;s Treasury has today presented a minute to the House giving particulars and circumstances of the proposed remission which it has approved in principle.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Dissolved NHS Trusts (Outstanding Public Dividend Capital)' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/mar/11/dissolved-nhs-trusts-outstanding-public'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3598572' text='ENVIRONMENT, FOOD AND RURAL AFFAIRS'>
      <outline id='3598573' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs (Mr. Elliot Morley)&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-04888"&gt;The ruling of the European Court of Justice in the Thomsen case has important implications for UK dairy farmers. It means that quota holders who do not produce against their quota for one year will have it confiscated to the national reserve. In effect, non-producing milk quota holders (NPQHs) will no longer be able to hold quota. Leasing out of quota will not be enough to avoid confiscation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-04889"&gt;There has understandably been considerable interest in the timetable for implementation of the ruling in the UK. I can confirm that the new rules will apply from 1 April 2004. Accordingly, NPQHs who have not produced against their quota in 2003&amp;#x2013;04 will be allowed until 31 March 2004 to sell it. If they do not do so by that&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;10WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;date, it will be confiscated to the national reserve. During the 2003&amp;#x2013;04 quota year NPQHs may lease out quota if they so wish.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-04890"&gt;Currently, NPQHs who lose their quota may apply for its restoration within 6 years of confiscation if they resume active production. However, under current EC proposals this period may be reduced to two years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-04891"&gt;In association with this, we shall be going out to consultation later in the year on the possible introduction of a 70 per cent usage rule. Under such a rule producers who do not use at least 70 per cent of their quota over a period to be fixed would have all or part of the unused portion confiscated to the national reserve. The introduction of such a rule would depend on the outcome of the consultation exercise. Subject to final confirmation of the legal base, we also propose to consult on breaking the link between quota and land, which will make it easier for tenants to buy in their own right any quota released by NPQHs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-04892"&gt;We recognise that the change concerning NPQHs is an important one and have publicised the new rules widely, including sending individual letters to all NPQHs. We believe that we have put in place a fair transitional arrangement that both allows NPQHs a reasonable period of time to adjust to the new circumstances and also recognises the UK&apos;s obligations under Community law.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Non-Producing Milk Quota Holders' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/mar/11/non-producing-milk-quota-holders'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3598574' text='CULTURE, MEDIA AND SPORT'>
      <outline id='3598575' text='The Secretary of State for Culture, Media and Sport (Tessa Jowell)&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-04893"&gt;On 10 February 2003,&lt;i&gt;Official Report&lt;/i&gt;, column 35WS, the Government announed that from 1 April 2003, the fee for a colour television licence would rise to &amp;#x00A3;116 and the black and white licence fee to &amp;#x00A3;38.50. Later on today I will be laying before the House the regulations necessary to bring these new fees into force.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-04894"&gt;The new regulations also introduce preserved rights for beneficiaries of the Accommodation for Residential Care concessionary TV licence scheme whose accommodation ceases to meet the existing qualifying criteria, so long as it continues to be provided or managed by a local authority, a housing association or a development corporation.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Television Licence Fee' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/mar/11/television-licence-fee'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3598576' text='EDUCATION AND SKILLS'>
      <outline id='3598577' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Education and Skills (Mr. Ivan Lewis)&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-04895"&gt;In accordance with the Government&apos;s policy of conducting quinquennial reviews of all non-departmental public bodies, my Department is today beginning reviews of the Industrial Training Boards, CITB and ECITB.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-04896"&gt;Following Cabinet Office guidelines, the terms of reference for the first stage of the review will be:&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;To review the functions of the Boards, and the likely need in the future for these functions&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;image src="S6CV0401P0I0822"/&gt;&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;11WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;To consider whether some or all of the functions can be better performed through other means&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;To review the efficiency and effectiveness of the Boards in carrying out their functions&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;To consider the powers, terms of reference, constitutional status, membership and activities of the Boards&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;To ensure initial findings are available for consideration in and, if appropriate, incorporation into, the Government&apos;s Skills Strategy&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;To report the outcome of Stage 1 of the review by June 2003.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-04897"&gt;We should welcome comments on those matters to be covered by the reviews from all those with an interest in the work of the CITB and ECITB. Comments, which may be made public unless respondents specifically request otherwise, should be sent by 30 April to:&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Anne Donkin&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Department for Education and Skills&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;E4c&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Moorfoot&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Sheffield S1 4PQ&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-04898"&gt;Or by e-mail to: &lt;u&gt;anne.donkin&amp;#x0040;dfes.gsi.gov.uk&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-04899"&gt;We have asked that this first stage of the review should be completed by 27 June 2003.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Industrial Training Boards' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/mar/11/industrial-training-boards'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3598578' text='NORTHERN IRELAND'>
      <outline id='3598579' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Northern Ireland (Angela Smith)&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-04900"&gt;Later today, I intend to launch a public consultation process on proposals for reform of water and sewerage services in Northern Ireland.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-04901"&gt;Since assuming responsibility for the Regional Development Ministerial portfolio, I have been acutely aware of the need for massive investment in Northern Ireland&apos;s water and sewerage infrastructure. Such a step-change in long-term investment can only be achieved through the development of secure, self-financing arrangements which also address the needs of the public as fairly and efficiently as possible.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-04902"&gt;In principle, this will require the introduction of domestic water charges in tandem with structural reform of the delivery of water and sewerage services in Northern Ireland to ensure that people will not be asked&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;12WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;to pay more than is absolutely necessary. I am committed to full and inclusive consultation through which I believe arrangements for the delivery of water and sewerage services, tailored to the specific needs and circumstances of the people of Northern Ireland, can be developed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-04903"&gt;The Consultation. Paper which I have published today sets out a range of possible options for domestic water charging. Possible structural arrangements for water and sewerage delivery and business models for a reformed Water Service are also outlined, along with the associated issues of economic and consumer regulation and mechanisms for consumer representation on water issues.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-04904"&gt;The period of public consultation on these issues will run until June 2003. Following a period of assessment of the responses to the consultation document, detailed proposals will be brought forward for further public consultation in the autumn, ultimately leading into the production of appropriate legislation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-04905"&gt;Copies of the Consultation Document; "The Reform of Water and Sewerage Services in Northern Ireland" have been placed in the Libraries of the House.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Water and Sewerage' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/mar/11/water-and-sewerage'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3598580' text='WALES'>
      <outline id='3598581' text='The Secretary of State for Wales (Peter Hain)&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-04906"&gt;A consultation on the future of public sector Ombudsman services in Wales began in November last year when the First Minister of the National Assembly for Wales and I published "Ombudsmen&apos;s Services in Wales: Time for change?". That document invited views on a proposal to bring together the offices of Welsh Administration Ombudsman, Health Service Commission Wales and the Commissioner for Local Administration in Wales to create a unified Ombudsman&apos;s jurisdiction for Wales, led by a single individual. We undertook to consult further on the precise remit of the new office if the principle of a single jurisdiction was endorsed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-04907"&gt;I can announce that responses to the consultation have given the proposal for a single Ombudsman&apos;s jurisdiction in Wales almost unanimous support. We will therefore move later this year to a further round of consultation on the jurisdiction and powers of this new Office. Individual copies and a summary of the responses will be placed in the Libraries of both Houses.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Public Sector Ombudsman Services' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/mar/11/public-sector-ombudsman-services'></outline>
    </outline>
  </body>
</opml>
