<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Written Statement of 17 March 2003</title>
    <dateCreated>Mon, 17 Mar 2003 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='3598610' text='INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT'>
      <outline id='3598611' text='The Secretary of State for International Development (Clare Short)&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-05004"&gt;On 4 March 2003 the Board of Directors of the European Bank for Reconstruction and Development (EBRD) agreed a new two-year strategy for Uzbekistan, which was supported by the UK. As the strategy clearly states, Uzbekistan has taken some positive measures on economic and political reforms but overall the situation remains serious and progress with reforms has been slow and characterised by setbacks. The country&apos;s ability to grow its economy, attract investment and reduce poverty is dependent on the Uzbek authorities making progress with both economic and political (including human rights) reforms.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-05005"&gt;The UK welcomes the EBRD strategy, which provides a detailed analysis of the current political and economic situation in Uzbekistan. We agree with EBRD that the Government of Uzbekistan needs to take a number of critical steps to put the country on a path of sustained progress towards multi-party democracy and a market economy and we support the decision by the Bank to hold a review after one year, looking for progress against seven key benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-05006"&gt;The EBRD has identified three operational priorities: support for private investment, strengthening financial institutions, and critical infrastructure; but the strategy notes that only through economic and political reforms can Uzbekistan hope to unlock its economic potential, which will in turn allow the Bank to mobilise additional financial support for the country.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-05007"&gt;Uzbekistan&apos;s economy remains generally closed to competition with a high degree of state control. EBRD notes that it is crucial, if the Uzbek authorities are to unlock their country&apos;s economic potential, that they embrace more fully the principles of open and free markets and encourage the private sector to drive economic growth. Uzbekistan&apos;s human rights record remains very poor. During 2002, Uzbekistan made some limited attempts to address human rights. But the UK shares the widespread and serious concern about the continuing abuse of human rights in the country, including the recent assessment of the UN Special Rapporteur on Torture that torture is systematic in Uzbekistan. The strategy identifies critical areas for progress by the Uzbek authorities. These include implementation of recommendations to be made on the basis of the UN Special Rapporteur&apos;s report.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;col&gt;32WS&lt;/col&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-05008"&gt;In May, EBRD will hold its annual meeting in Uzbekistan. This will be the first time that the EBRD annual meeting has been held in Central Asia. Since the collapse of the Soviet Union, Central Asia has largely been neglected. The newly independent countries faced the double challenge of building new institutions and making the transition to a market economy and political pluralism. Their progress has been patchy. Uzbekistan, Tajikistan and the Kyrgyz Republic are all now low-income countries. Desperate poverty, high levels of debt and corruption, and deteriorating infrastructure and public services exist in much of the region. The region&apos;s geography means that the countries are co-dependent for trade and natural resources. But relations have been characterised by the isolationism of some states; all the countries stand to benefit from increased regional cooperation and trade.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-05009"&gt;We hope the annual meeting will focus international attention on the country, and that it will provide a forum for international engagement and an open debate on the opportunities and challenges facing Uzbekistan and the countries of central Asia. The meeting is an opportunity to try to secure social and economic progress, progress with human rights, and improved regional cooperation. It is an incentive for the Uzbek authorities to reform and not an endorsement of current policies. The UK hopes that the Uzbek authorities will consider the strategy carefully and, by the time of the annual meeting, take the opportunity to demonstrate to the international community, progress towards political and economic change.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-05010"&gt;The strategy was published on EBRD&apos;s website www.ebrd.com/ yesterday. I have placed a copy in the Library of the House.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Uzbekistan' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/mar/17/uzbekistan'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3598612' text="LORD CHANCELLOR'S DEPARTMENT">
      <outline id='3598613' text='The Parliamentary Secretary, Lord Chancellor&apos;s Department (Ms Rosie Winterton)&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-05011"&gt;A report on the responses to the e-conveyancing consultation exercise will be published later today. Copies have been placed in the Libraries of both Houses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-05012"&gt;Most respondents viewed the concept of an e-conveyancing system positively. Useful suggestions were made to enhance the initial proposals, and a number of concerns were highlighted. All of these issues will be addressed during the next phase of the e-conveyancing programme. My Department believes it to be important that the system finally delivered carries the greatest measure of support from stakeholders and makes full use of the talents of the private sector. My noble and learned Friend Baroness Scotland has asked the Land Registry to continue to take forward this work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-05013"&gt;It will now be engaging stakeholders, including potential service providers in developing the e-conveyancing concept and proposing the shape of the final system.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-05014"&gt;My noble and learned Friend Baroness Scotland has asked for a report on progress to be made to her later in the year.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Electronic Conveyancing' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/mar/17/electronic-conveyancing'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3598614' text='DEPUTY PRIME MINISTER'>
      <outline id='3598615' text='The Minister for Social Exclusion and Deputy Minister for Women (Mrs. Barbara Roche)&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-05015"&gt;Neighbourhood renewal is about reversing the spiral of decline in our most disadvantaged neighbourhoods and raising the standard of public services in the places which need them most. It involves working with local communities to deliver economic prosperity and jobs, safer streets, good education, decent homes and better health, as well as fostering a new sense of community among residents. This can be achieved by encouraging better partnerships at the local level and through a major investment of resources to drive change.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-05016"&gt;Our aim is thriving and sustainable communities, where people are being empowered to improve their quality of life. Local people are therefore working with the public, private and voluntary sectors to tackle the problems of deprived neighbourhoods, and bring about a step change in the way local services are planned and delivered. Over the last 2 years, &amp;#x00A3;500 million of Neighbourhood Renewal Fund resources have supported this work. As a result of progress so far, entitlement to a further &amp;#x00A3;400 million is today being confirmed for 88 deprived communities across the country. The final neighbourhood renewal fund allocations and spending conditions will be subject to Parliamentary approval later this month.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-05017"&gt;Making sure public services work better over the long term in deprived neighbourhoods, is vital to building sustainable communities. Lasting change can be delivered by shaping and resourcing public services for the task, and making them focus on the places and people most in need of support. The neighbourhood renewal fund is being used to initiate this process and local communities have already benefited from a range of actions to improve living conditions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-05018"&gt;In Wythenshawe in Greater Manchester, for example, NRF has funded the youth contact team to worked with local partners to run environmental clean ups, and a football tournament as well as taking part in outreach work on the streets, leading to an overall reduction of almost 40 per cent. in youth nuisance and an 18 per cent. reduction in recorded crime. In Portsmouth, over 50 dedicated coaching staff have been funded in 18 schools to improve the quality of teaching and learning. In Halton in Cheshire, a new approach and improved technology for dealing with benefits claims has reduced processing times from eight weeks to less than a fortnight.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-05019"&gt;Equally important to the lasting renewal of neighbourhoods, is the engagement of local communities in identifying local priorities and needs, and developing solutions for their area. Through the establishment of local strategic partnerships, local people have been brought together with local authorities and other public service providers, to plan for a step change in the way local services are delivered. &amp;#x00A3;53 million was made available over the last two years to support community and voluntary sector involvement in renewal. Networks have been set up to&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;34WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;strengthen the sector&apos;s voice in the planning and delivery of services, building communities where people want to live, not leave.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-05020"&gt;Progress over the last year means that that today I can announce the re-accreditation of the local strategic partnerships in all 88 areas. This allows the delivery phase of their plans, and will bring real change on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-05021"&gt;Over the next year, service providers must continue to work with local communities to strengthen plans for improving services and meet challenging targets for improving living conditions in the worst neighbourhoods. In order to ensure results on the ground, we will support partnerships over the next year through their full access to &amp;#x00A3;400 million of NRF, and by improving skills, driving performance by service providers and empowering local people to participate in this process. Ensuring real change in the way public services are delivered will be the priority for partnerships over the year ahead.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-05022"&gt;I will make a more detailed announcement in due course on how the Office of the Deputy Prime Minister, will monitor and drive delivery by local partnerships. This will include ensuring that accreditation of partnerships is streamlined. I will also make an announcement shortly on the future distribution of and priorities for the additional &amp;#x00A3;975 million of neighbourhood renewal fund resources, and related Community Programme funding, for 2004&amp;#x0213;05 and 2005&amp;#x2013;06.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Neighbourhood Renewal Funds' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/mar/17/neighbourhood-renewal-funds'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3598616' text='HOME DEPARTMENT'>
      <outline id='3598617' text='The Minister for Policing, Crime Reduction and Community Safety (Mr. John Denham)&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-05023"&gt;I commissioned an independent review into the provision of forensic pathology services and have accepted the key recommendations of that independent review. There is clearly a need to establish a unified forensic pathology service to deliver the needs of the police service, coroners and the wider criminal justice system.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-05024"&gt;The Government intend to:&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;enable a standard high quality service to be offered across England and Wales;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;ensure availability of service by providing the framework of a career structure to retain existing practitioners and to attract new entrants to the field;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;facilitate the provision of specialist regional service delivery centres;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;introduce improved management and budgetary controls for the provision of forensic pathology services.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-05025"&gt;I have instructed my officials to implement the key recommendations of the review as quickly as possible, with the intention that:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-05026"&gt;by autumn 2003, we will:&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;move to new accreditation and disciplinary procedures based on model competencies; and&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;have two centres prepared to deliver a training programme against the improved standards.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;image src="S6CV0401P0I0834"/&gt;&lt;col&gt;35WS&lt;/col&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-05027"&gt;by summer 2004, we will aim to have:&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;more newly trained, and operational forensic pathologists;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;an agreed career structure for the future national forensic pathology service; and&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;developed contracts of employment.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-05028"&gt;I will continue to take a close interest in progress and will receive regular reports on progress from the Programme Delivery Board established to take this work forward. The delivery board will include representatives of both users and providers of forensic pathology services.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-05029"&gt;A copy of the review has been placed in the Library.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Forensic Pathology Services' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/mar/17/forensic-pathology-services'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3598618' text='FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH AFFAIRS'>
      <outline id='3598619' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs (Mr. Mike O&apos;Brien)&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-05030"&gt;The Attorney General of the Cayman Islands, Mr. David Ballantyne, has decided to leave office on 15 March, by mutual agreement with the Cayman&lt;col&gt;36WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;Islands Government. Mr. Ballantyne had come under criticism in the Cayman Islands following the collapse of the Eurobank money-laundering trial. He took the view that this made it impossible for him to carry out his role there effectively. I am informed that press allegations that Mr. Ballantyne had prior knowledge of or had approved the destruction of evidence which led to the collapse of the Eurobank trial are inaccurate. The evidence is that he acted to ensure the disclosure of all relevant information to the defence in order to secure a fair trial, and acted properly in bringing the trial to an end when he concluded that a fair trial could not be ensured. In doing so he carried out the independent role the Cayman Islands Constitution assigns to the Attorney General. Her Majesty&apos;s Government are satisfied that Mr. Ballantyne has throughout acted with professional integrity and in the best interests of the administration of justice in the Cayman Islands.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0401P0-05031"&gt;Press reports suggesting that Baroness Amos agreed, on behalf of Her Majesty&apos;s Government, to the dismissal from office of Mr. Ballantyne are also incorrect. The independence and security of tenure of the Attorney General is constitutionally protected in the Cayman Islands.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Cayman Islands' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/mar/17/cayman-islands'></outline>
    </outline>
  </body>
</opml>
