<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Written Statement of 19 January 2005</title>
    <dateCreated>Wed, 19 Jan 2005 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='2557056'>
      <outline id='2557058' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State, Department for Culture, Media and Sport (Lord McIntosh of Haringey)&lt;p id="S5LV0668P0-05314"&gt;My right honourable friend the Minister of State for Sport and Tourism (Richard Caborn) has made the following Written Ministerial Statement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0668P0-05315"&gt;Improving safeguards for children and vulnerable adults in relation to gambling is a government priority. As outlined in the Gambling Bill, we intend to introduce greater safeguards than are available under the present law. We need to address the challenges that are caused by new technology, by the Internet and by the steady growth in consumer demand. Without the Bill, problem gambling is likely to increase. The safeguards will allow the regulator&amp;#x2014;the proposed new Gambling Commission&amp;#x2014;and the Government to keep the position firmly under control and to act swiftly to cut back the supply of gambling opportunities, should that prove necessary.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0668P0-05316"&gt;Our intention, subject to parliamentary approval, is that we protect as many individuals as we can, from as&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;WS 28&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;early a date as possible. In order to do this we need to carry out essential activities to set up the Gambling Commission, which will require some expenditure in advance of the legislation achieving Royal Assent. Delay in funding the setting up of the Gambling Commission would undermine good progress being made in this area and would be contrary to the public interest.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0668P0-05317"&gt;An advance from the Contingencies Fund has therefore been sought and approved. Without this advance, work on the technology to support the commission&apos;s operation, accommodation and appointment of certain senior staff would suffer. This would set back plans to introduce the new safeguards that are urgently required.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0668P0-05318"&gt;Parliamentary approval for additional resources will be sought in a supplementary estimate for the Department for Culture, Media and Sport following Royal Assent of the Gambling Bill. Pending that approval, urgent cash expenditure of &amp;#x00A3;367,533 will be met by a repayable cash advance from the Contingencies Fund.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Gambling Commission: Contingencies Fund Advance' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2005/jan/19/gambling-commission-contingencies-fund'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='2557082'>
      <outline id='2557084' text='Lord Bassam of Brighton&lt;p id="S5LV0668P0-05319"&gt;A revised edition of the list of ministerial responsibilities (January 2005) has been published today and copies placed in the Library. It can also be obtained electronically at www.knowledgenetwork.gov.uk/elmr/minister.nsf.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Ministerial Responsibilities' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2005/jan/19/ministerial-responsibilities'></outline>
    </outline>
  </body>
</opml>
