<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Lords Report of 9 December 1924</title>
    <dateCreated>Tue, 09 Dec 1924 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='2280649' text='The Lord Fisherwick (&lt;i&gt;M. Donegall&lt;/i&gt;)&amp;#x2014;Sat first in Parliament after the death of his grandfather.' title='Preamble' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1924/dec/09/preamble'></outline>
    <outline id='2280650' text='The LORD CHANCELLOR&lt;member&gt;The LORD CHANCELLOR&lt;/member&gt; acquainted the House that the Clerk of the Parliaments had received (by post) from the Lord Clerk Register of Scotland, Minutes of the meeting held on the 3rd of November last of the Peers of Scotland for the election of their representatives to sit and vote in the ensuing Parliament of the United Kingdom; and also, Return by the Lord Clerk Register of Scotland concerning titles of Peerages called at the said meeting, in right of which respectively no vote had been received and counted for fifty years last past as at the date of the said meeting: Ordered, That the said Minutes of Election, etc. be printed.' title='REPRESENTATIVE PEERS FOR SCOTLAND.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1924/dec/09/representative-peers-for-scotland'></outline>
    <outline id='2280658' text='A witness ordered to attend the Committee for Privileges to-morrow, and to produce documents.' title='DUKEDOM OF SOMERSET.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1924/dec/09/dukedom-of-somerset'></outline>
    <outline id='2280659' text='Report made from the Lord Chancellor that the right of Henry Frederick, Baron Hotham, in the Peerage of Ireland, to vote at the elections of Representative Peers for Ireland has been established to the satisfaction of the Lord Chancellor; read, and ordered to lie on the Table.&lt;br/&gt;Ordered, That the Report of the Lord Chancellor be sent to the Clerk of the Crown in Ireland, together with a certificate stating that such Report has been made, and that the House has ordered it to be sent to the said Clerk of the Crown in Ireland.' title='LORD HOTHAM.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1924/dec/09/lord-hotham'></outline>
    <outline id='2280660' text='Report made from the Lord Chancellor that the right of William Chambre, Baron Langford, in the Peerage of Ireland, to vote at the elections of Representative Peers for Ireland, has been established to the satisfaction of the Lord Chancellor; read, and ordered to lie on the Table.&lt;br/&gt;Ordered, That the Report of the Lord Chancellor be sent to the Clerk of the Crown in Ireland, together with a certificate stating that such Report has been made, and that the House has ordered it to be sent to the said Clerk of the Crown in Ireland.' title='LORD LANGFORD.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1924/dec/09/lord-langford'></outline>
    <outline id='2280661' text='Petition of Arthur William Eveleigh De Moleyns, Baron Ventry, in the Peerage of Ireland, claiming a right to vote at the elections of Representative Peers for Ireland; read, and referred to the Lord Chancellor to consider and report thereupon to the House.' title='LORD VENTRY.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1924/dec/09/lord-ventry'></outline>
    <outline id='2280662' text='The CHAIRMAN OF COMMITTEES acquainted the House, That (pursuant, to the Resolutions of the 9th of October last respecting Private and Provisional Order Confirmation Bills) the Bill had been lodged in the Private Bill Office, together with the declaration of an officer of the Scottish Office: Bill presented, read 1&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;, and to be read 2&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt; to-morrow (The Lord Privy Seal (&lt;i&gt;M. Salisbury&lt;/i&gt;)).' title='GLASGOW CORPORATION ORDER CONFIRMATION BILL. [H.L.]' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1924/dec/09/glasgow-corporation-order-confirmation'></outline>
    <outline id='2280663' text='The CHAIRMAN OF COMMITTEES acquainted the House, That (pursuant to the Resolutions of the 9th of October last respecting Private and Provisional Order Confirmation Bills) the Bill had been lodged in the Private Bill Office, together with the declaration of an officer of the Ministry of Health: Bill presented, read 1&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt; and 2&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;: Committee negatived: Bill read 3&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;, and passed, and sent to the Commons.' title='MINISTRY OF HEALTH PROVISIONAL ORDER CONFIRMATION (BLACKPOOL) ORDER BILL. [H.L.]' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1924/dec/09/ministry-of-health-provisional-order'></outline>
    <outline id='2280665' text='A Bill to confirm a Provisional Order relating to Aberdeen Harbour (Rates)&amp;#x2014;Was presented by the Lord Privy Seal (&lt;i&gt;M. Salisbury&lt;/i&gt;): Read 1&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;; to be printed: and (pursuant to the Private Legislation Procedure (Scotland) Act, 1899), deemed to have been read 2&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;; reported from the Committee, and to be read 3&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt; on Thursday next.' title='ABERDEEN HARBOUR (RATES) ORDER CONFIRMATION BILL. [H.L.]' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1924/dec/09/aberdeen-harbour-rates-order'></outline>
    <outline id='2280666' text='A Bill to confirm a Provisional Order relating to the Edinburgh Chartered Accountants Annuity, etc., Fund&amp;#x2014;Was presented by the Lord Privy Seal (&lt;i&gt;M. Salisbury&lt;/i&gt;): Read 1&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;; to be printed; and (pursuant to the Private Legislation Procedure (Scotland) Act, 1899), deemed to have been read 2&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;, reported from the Committee, and to be read 3&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt; on Thursday next.' title='EDINBURGH CHARTERED ACCOUNTANTS ANNUITY, ETC., FUND ORDER CONFIRMATION BILL. [H.L.]' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1924/dec/09/edinburgh-chartered-accountants-annuity'></outline>
    <outline id='2280667' text='A Bill to confirm a Provisional Order relating to Scrabster Harbour&amp;#x2014;Was presented by the Lord Privy Seal (&lt;i&gt;M. Salisbury&lt;/i&gt;): Read 1&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;; to be printed; and (pursuant to the Private Legislation Procedure (Scotland) Act, 1899), deemed to have been read 2&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;, reported from the Committee, and to be read 3&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt; on Thursday next.' title='SCRABSTER HARBOUR ORDER CONFIRMATION BILL. [H.L.]' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1924/dec/09/scrabster-harbour-order-confirmation'></outline>
  </body>
</opml>
