<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Lords Report of 2 April 1940</title>
    <dateCreated>Tue, 02 Apr 1940 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='2307856' text="The LORD CHANCELLOR&lt;member&gt;The LORD CHANCELLOR&lt;/member&gt; acquainted the House, That the Clerk of the Parliaments had laid upon the Table the Certificate from the Examiners that the further Standing Orders applicable to the following Bill have been complied with:&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Newcastle and Gateshead Waterworks.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Also the Certificate that the Standing Orders have not been complied with in respect of the Petition for the following Bill:&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Monmouthshire and South Wales Employers' Mutual Indemnity Society, Limited.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br/&gt;And also the Certificates that the Standing Orders have not been complied with in respect of the Petitions for additional Provisions in the following Bills:&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Birmingham Corporation.&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Christchurch Corporation.&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The same were ordered to lie on the Table." title='Preamble' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1940/apr/02/preamble'></outline>
    <outline id='2307860' text='Order, dated 30th March, 1940, made by the Treasury under Sections 1 and 3 of the Debts Clearing Offices and Import Restrictions Act, 1934:&lt;br/&gt;Laid before the House (pursuant to Act) for affirmative Resolution and referred to the Special Orders Committee.' title='CLEARING OFFICE (SPAIN) AMENDMENT ORDER, 1940.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1940/apr/02/clearing-office-spain-amendment-order'></outline>
    <outline id='2307861' text='Report from the Special Orders Committee, That they have examined the Order as required by the Standing Orders of the House; that in their opinion the provisions of the Order raise important questions of policy and principle&amp;#x2014;they comply with the terms of the Unemployment Assistance Act, 1935, under which the Order is submitted for approval&amp;#x2014;that the Order is founded on precedent inasmuch as analagous Orders have already been approved by the House; that in the opinion of the Committee the Scheme cannot be passed by the House without special attention, but that no further inquiry is necessary before the House proceeds to a decision on the Resolution to approve the said Scheme:&lt;br/&gt;Read, and ordered to lie on the Table.' title='DRAFT UNEMPLOYMENT INSURANCE (INCREASE OF BENEFIT IN RESPECT OF DEPENDENT CHILDREN) ORDER, 1940.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1940/apr/02/draft-unemployment-insurance-increase-of'></outline>
  </body>
</opml>
