<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Lords Report of 20 February 1936</title>
    <dateCreated>Thu, 20 Feb 1936 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='2293761' text='Report from, That the Standing Orders not complied with in respect of the following Bill ought to be dispensed with:&lt;br/&gt;Cirencester Gas.&lt;br/&gt;And that the Standing Orders not complied with in respect of the petition for the following Bill ought to be dispensed with, and leave given to introduce the Bill:&lt;br/&gt;Yorkshire Electric Power.&lt;br/&gt;Read, and agreed to.' title='STANDING ORDERS COMMITTEE.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1936/feb/20/standing-orders-committee'></outline>
    <outline id='2293769' text='Presented (pursuant to leave given this day); read 1&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;, and referred to the Examiners.' title='YORKSHIRE ELECTRIC POWER BILL. [H.L.]' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1936/feb/20/yorkshire-electric-power-bill-hl'></outline>
    <outline id='2293770' text='IMPERIAL CONTINENTAL GAS ASSOCIATION BILL. [H.L.]'>
      <outline id='2293771' text='ROYAL NATIONAL PENSION FUND FOR NURSES BILL. [H.L.]'>
        
      </outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='2293773' text='CORNWALL ELECTRIC POWER BILL. [H.L.]'>
      <outline id='2293774' text='GRAVESEND AND MILTON WATERWORKS BILL. [H.L.]'>
        <outline id='2293775' text="&lt;b&gt;RICKMANSWORTH AND UXBRIDGE VALLEY WATER BILL. [H.L.]&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;SWANSEA AND 'DISTRICT TRANSPORT BILL. [H.L.]&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Committed: The Committees to be proposed by the Committee of Selection." title='NORTH METROPOLITAN ELECTRIC POWER SUPPLY BILL. [H.L.]' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1936/feb/20/north-metropolitan-electric-power-supply'></outline>
      </outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='2293776' text='HUDDERSFIELD CORPORATION (TROLLEY VEHICLES) BILL. [H.L.]'>
      <outline id='2293777' text='SWANSEA CORPORATION BILL. [H.L.]'>
        <outline id='2293778' text="&lt;b&gt;WINCHESTER CORPORATION BILL [H.L.]&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;HORNCHURCH URBAN DISTRICT COUNCIL BILL. [H.L.]&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;MANCHESTER CORPORATION BILL. [H.L.]&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Report from the Committee of Selection, That the following Lords be proposed to the House to form the Select Committee for the consideration of the said Bills; namely:&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;E. Mount Edgcumbe,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;E. Cawdor,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Annaly,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Mamhead.&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Milne (Chairman).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Agreed to; and the said Lords appointed accordingly. The Committee to meet on Tuesday, the 3rd of March next, at eleven o'clock; and all Petitions referred to the Committee, with leave to the Petitioners praying to be heard by Counsel against the Bills to be heard as desired, as also Counsel for the Bills." title='SWANSEA AND DISTRICT TRANS PORT BILL. [H.L.]' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1936/feb/20/swansea-and-district-trans-port-bill-hl'></outline>
      </outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='2293779' text='Report from the Special Orders Committee, That they have examined the Special Order as required by the Standing Orders of the House; that in their opinion the Order raises questions of policy and principle similar to those agreed to by the House when approving two previous Orders relating to the importation of bacon made under the Agricultural Marketing Act, 1933; that the Order is founded on precedent, in so far as Amendments to Schemes have already been submitted for the approval of Parliament under the Agricultural Marketing Acts, 1931 and 1933; that in the opinion of the Committee the Order cannot be passed without special attention, but that no further inquiry is necessary before the House proceeds to a decision on the Resolution to approve the said Order.&lt;br/&gt;Read, and ordered to lie on the Table.' title='BACON (IMPORT REGULATION) AMENDMENT ORDER, 1935.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1936/feb/20/bacon-import-regulation-amendment-order'></outline>
    <outline id='2293780' text='Report from the Special Orders Committee, That they have examined the Special Order as required by the Standing Orders of the House; that in their opinion the provisions of the Order raise questions of policy and principle which have been accepted already by the House&#x000A;&lt;image src="S5LV0099P0I0396"/&gt;&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;731&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;when passing the Debts Clearing Offices and Import Restrictions Act, 1934, under which the Order is submitted for approval; that the Order is not founded on precedent inasmuch as no other Order has been submitted for the approval of Parliament under that Act; that in the opinion of the Committee the Order cannot be passed by the House without special attention, but that no further inquiry is necessary before the House proceeds to a decision on the Resolution to approve the said Order.&lt;br/&gt;Read, and ordered to lie on the Table.' title='CLEARING OFFICE (SPAIN) ORDER, 1936.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1936/feb/20/clearing-office-spain-order-1936'></outline>
    <outline id='2293781' text='DEAL AND WALMER GAS ORDER, 1936.'>
      <outline id='2293782' text='DUNSTABLE GAS ORDER, 1936.'>
        <outline id='2293783' text='&lt;b&gt;LEEDS GAS ORDER, 1936.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;NEWTON IN MACKERFIELD GAS ORDER, 1936.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;BRIGHTON ELECTRICITY (GENERATING STATION EXTENSION) ORDER, 1936.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;MANCHESTER ELECTRICITY (EXTENSION) ORDER, 1936.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;WOODBRIDGE AND DISTRICT ELECTRICITY ORDER, 1936.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Report from the Special Orders Committee, That no Petition has been presented praying to be heard against the Special Orders, and that there is nothing in these Orders to which they think it necessary to call the attention of the House: Read, and ordered to lie on the Table.' title='FOLKESTONE GAS ORDER, 1936.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1936/feb/20/folkestone-gas-order-1936'></outline>
      </outline>
    </outline>
  </body>
</opml>
