<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Written Statement of 27 April 2004</title>
    <dateCreated>Tue, 27 Apr 2004 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='3615807' text='ENVIRONMENT, FOOD AND RURAL AFFAIRS'>
      <outline id='3615808' text='The Secretary of State for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs (Margaret Beckett)&lt;p&gt;The Government published yesterday "Energy Efficiency&amp;#x2014;The Government&apos;s Plan for Action". This fulfils our commitment in the February 2003 energy White Paper to set out our delivery plan for the energy efficiency strategy contained in the White Paper. Copies of the plan were placed in the House Libraries yesterday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the document "Energy Efficiency&amp;#x2014;The Government&apos;s Plan for Action", I have designated an energy efficiency aim in accordance with the duty set out in section 2(1) of the Sustainable Energy Act 2003; such aim relates to the energy efficiency of residential accommodation in England and is compatible with Community obligations and any another international obligations of the United Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Government yesterday also published the first annual report on the energy White Paper, the Strategy for Combined Heat and Power to 2010, and the second fuel poverty annual report. Copies of these documents were also placed in the House Libraries yesterday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In her written statement to the House of Commons on 3 February 2004, the Secretary of State for Trade and Industry said that the Government envisaged publication of the fuel poverty implementation plan with the above documents. The Government now envisage publication of the fuel poverty implementation plan in the summer.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Energy Efficiency Implementation Plan' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/apr/27/energy-efficiency-implementation-plan'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3615809' text='NORTHERN IRELAND'>
      <outline id='3615810' text="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Northern Ireland (Mr. Ian Pearson)&lt;p&gt;I have today laid before this House a copy of the oversight commissioner's first statutory report for the year 2004, which is being published today, in accordance with section 68(4)(a) of the Police (Northern Ireland) Act 2000.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the first report compiled by Al Hutchinson as oversight commissioner and the 10th in the series of oversight reports published since 2001.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I would like to take this opportunity to welcome the new oversight commissioner to this very important post.&lt;/p&gt;" title="Oversight Commissioner's Report" type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/apr/27/oversight-commissioners-report'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3615811' text='DEFENCE'>
      <outline id='3615812' text="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Defence (Mr. Ivor Caplin)&lt;p&gt;The following key targets have been set for the Chief Executive of the Defence Medical Education and Training Agency (DMETA) for the Financial Year 2004&amp;#x2013;05:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Key Target 1&amp;#x2014;Deployable Personnel&lt;/i&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;To meet 100 per cent. of the Commander in Chief's requirements for secondary care personnel under DMETA command for operational deployments.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Key Target 2&amp;#x2014;Military Training&lt;/i&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;To ensure that 80 per cent. of all DMETA personnel, whose medical category permits, achieve their service's annual mandatory individual military training.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Key Targets 3&amp;#x2014;Training Success&lt;/i&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;(a) Initial Training (Phase 2)&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;To provide Initial Training (Phase 2) that meets the requirements, professional standards and timescales defined by the single services.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;(b) Career, Professional and Continuation Training (Phase 3)&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;To provide career, professional and continuation training (Phase 3) that meets the requirements, professional standards and timescales defined by the single services.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Key Targets 4&amp;#x2014;Efficiency and Cost Management&lt;/i&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;(a) DMETA Estate&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Ensure the rationalisation and efficient usage of the current DMETA estate, reducing the balance sheet value of the estate as at 1 April 2003 by at least 50 per cent. by 2010, thereby reducing the cost of training.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;(b) Cost Measurement&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;To develop an output cost based methodology for efficiency and unit cost performance measurement for implementation by April 2005.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Key Target 5&amp;#x2014;Customer Focus&lt;/i&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;To develop and implement by 1 April 2005 a measure of the extent to which customers value the quality of DMETA outputs.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;" title='Medical Education and Training Agency' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/apr/27/medical-education-and-training-agency'></outline>
      <outline id='3615813' text="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Defence (Mr. Ivor Caplin)&lt;p&gt;The following key targets have been set for the chief executive of the Defence Dental Agency for the financial year 2004&amp;#x2013;05:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Key Target 1&amp;#x2013;Meeting Operational Manpower Requirements&lt;/i&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;To meet 100 per cent. of the Commander in Chief's requirements for DDA manpower to support operations.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Key Target 2&amp;#x2014;Dental Risk&lt;/i&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;To achieve 90 per cent. of all Service personnel in dental risk categories A and B by 31 March 2005.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Key Targets 3&amp;#x2014;Treatment Needs&lt;/i&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;To reduce the Treatment Needs Index for each Service to the following: RN at or below 375;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Army at or below 600; RAF at or below 375 by 31 March 2005.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Key Targets 4&amp;#x2014;Military Training&lt;/i&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;To ensure that 80 per cent. of all DDA personnel, whose medical category permits, achieve their Service's annual mandatory individual military training.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;" title='Defence Dental Agency' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/apr/27/defence-dental-agency'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3615814' text='DEPUTY PRIME MINISTER'>
      <outline id='3615815' text="The Minister for Housing and Planning (Keith Hill)&lt;p&gt;My right hon. Friend the Deputy Prime Minister has published for public consultation proposed changes to the Ashford growth area section of chapter XII of regional planning guidance for the South East (RPG9). They follow the public examination into the draft in December 2003 and the panel report in February 2004.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Growth areas are an integral part of regional planning guidance (RPG) and the draft chapter represents a revision to RPG9, as published in March 2001.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Other partial reviews of RPG9 are at various stages in the process. In particular, a public examination into the Milton Keynes and South Midlands sub-regional strategy is under way, and the Secretary of State's proposed changes for the regional transport strategy are out for consultation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;col&gt;40WS&lt;/col&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ashford is both a center for regional economic development and a gateway to Europe. Growth must bring real benefits to the whole community, which is why our proposed policies promote the right development in the right place at the right time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The regional planning guidance needs to define new policies that will not only support the projected growth of housing and jobs in Ashford but will guide the growth in a sustainable way.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Office of the Deputy Prime Minister proposes accepting all the recommendations of the independent panel that held the public examination into the proposed alterations, with minor modifications.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have written to the regional assembly with the proposed changes. There will now be a public consultation period on the proposed changes, which will end on 17 June.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Copies of the relevant documents are available in the Libraries of both Houses and have been provided for all of the region's MPs, MEPs and local authorities.&lt;/p&gt;" title='Ashford Growth Area' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/apr/27/ashford-growth-area'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='2542722'>
      <outline id='2542723' text='The Lord President of the Council (Baroness Amos)&lt;p id="S5LV0660P0-05403"&gt;My honourable friend the Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Northern Ireland has made the following Ministerial Statement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0660P0-05404"&gt;I have today laid before this House a copy of the Oversight Commissioner&apos;s first statutory report for 2004 which is being published today, in accordance with Section 68(4)(a) of the Police (Northern Ireland) Act 2000.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0660P0-05405"&gt;This is the first report compiled by A1 Hutchinson as Oversight Commissioner and the 10th in the series of oversight reports published since 2001.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0660P0-05406"&gt;I would like to take this opportunity to welcome the new Oversight Commissioner to this very important post.&lt;/p&gt;' title="Northern Ireland: Oversight Commissioner's Report" type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/apr/27/northern-ireland-oversight-commissioners'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='2542726'>
      <outline id='2542727' text='The Minister of State, Office of the Deputy Prime Minister (Lord Rooker)&lt;p id="S5LV0660P0-05407"&gt;My right honourable friend the Minister for Housing and Planning has made the following Written Ministerial Statement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;col&gt;WS 26&lt;/col&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0660P0-05408"&gt;My right honourable friend the Deputy Prime Minister has published for public consultation proposed changes to the Ashford growth area section of Chapter 12 of regional planning guidance for the southeast (RPG9). They follow the public examination into the draft in December 2003 and the panel report in February 2004.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0660P0-05409"&gt;Growth areas are an integral part of regional planning guidance (RPG) and the draft chapter represents a revision to RPG9, as published in March 2001.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0660P0-05410"&gt;Other partial reviews of RPG9 are at various stages in the process. In particular, a public examination into the Milton Keynes and south Midlands sub-regional strategy is under way, and the Secretary of State&apos;s proposed changes for the regional transport strategy are out for consultation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0660P0-05411"&gt;Ashford is both a centre for regional economic development and a gateway to Europe. Growth must bring real benefits to the whole community, which is why our proposed policies promote the right development in the right place at the right time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0660P0-05412"&gt;The regional planning guidance needs to define new policies which will not only support the projected growth of housing and jobs in Ashford but guide this growth in a sustainable way.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0660P0-05413"&gt;The Office of the Deputy Prime Minister proposes accepting all the recommendations of the independent panel that held the public examination into the proposed alterations, with minor modifications.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0660P0-05414"&gt;I have written to the regional assembly with the proposed changes. There will now be a public consultation period on the proposed changes, which will end on 17 June.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0660P0-05415"&gt;Copies of the relevant documents are available in the Libraries of the House and have been provided for all of the region&apos;s MPs, MEPs and local authorities.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Regional Planning Guidance: Ashford Growth Area' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/apr/27/regional-planning-guidance-ashford'></outline>
    </outline>
  </body>
</opml>
