<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Written Statement of 15 July 2003</title>
    <dateCreated>Tue, 15 Jul 2003 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='3551934' text='ENVIRONMENT, FOOD AND RURAL AFFAIRS'>
      <outline id='3551935' text='The Minister for the Environment (Mr. Elliot Morley)&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02287"&gt;Today, the DEFRA-funded UK Climate Impacts Programme (UKCIP) is publishing its report Climate change and local communities&amp;#x2014;how prepared are you? The report informs local authorities of the key implications of climate change for their business functions and offers them guidance to help them adapt. It has been produced for local authorities by UKCIP in partnership with the Local Government Association and the Improvement and Development Agency. Copies of the report have been placed in the Libraries of both Houses.&lt;/p&gt;' title='UK Climate Impacts Programme' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jul/15/uk-climate-impacts-programme'></outline>
      <outline id='3551945' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs (Mr. Ben Bradshaw)&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02288"&gt;I have arranged for copies of the Government&apos;s Animal Health and Welfare Strategy for Great Britain to be made available in the Libraries of both Houses. Produced jointly by DEFRA, the Scottish Executive and the Welsh Assembly, the outline strategy is being circulated for public consultation, with a deadline for comments of 31 October.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02289"&gt;Copies are also available on the DEFRA website at &lt;u&gt;http://www.defra.gov.uk/animalh&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/p&gt;' title='Animal Health and Welfare Strategy' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jul/15/animal-health-and-welfare-strategy'></outline>
      <outline id='3551946' text='The Minister for the Environment (Mr. Elliot Morley)&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02290"&gt;I am pleased to announce to the House awards under a new funding scheme forming part of DEFRA&apos;s Darwin Initiative.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02291"&gt;The Darwin Initiative is an annual small grants programme which uses UK expertise working with local partners to help countries rich in biodiversity but poor in resources to conserve and use their biodiversity sustainably. Launched at the Rio summit in 1992, the initiative has committed more than &amp;#x00A3;30 million to over 300 projects in around 100 countries. More than 100 projects are currently running. The Prime Minister announced an increase in the Darwin Initiative budget in his speech on WSSD in September. The budget increased from &amp;#x00A3;3 million to &amp;#x00A3;4 million in 2003&amp;#x2013;04 and will rise to &amp;#x00A3;5 million in 2004&amp;#x2013;05, and &amp;#x00A3;7 million a year from 2005&amp;#x2013;06. Three new Darwin Initiative schemes have been launched as part of Phase II of the Initiative: Darwin Initiative scholarships, pre-project awards and post-project funding. Together these will help to help embed the core aims of capacity building, partnership and legacy. I announced the Scholarship awards at the annual Darwin lecture on 21 May.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;col&gt;12WS&lt;/col&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02292"&gt;The awards of pre-project funding are as follows: (Annex B)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02293"&gt;&#x000A;&lt;table&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Organisation&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Project Title&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Country&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Award &amp;#x00A3;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Society for Environmental Exploration&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Capacity building for sustainable management in the&#x000A;Nicaraguan Pacific Region&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Nicaragua&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;1,790&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Macauley Land Use Research Institute&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Community conservation action plan for the threatened long-tailed chinchilla in Chile&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Chile&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;1,792&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Foundation for International Environmental Law and Development&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Conservation and sustainable use of Agriculture Biodiversity in Costa Rica&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Costa Rica&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;1,425&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Global Diversity Foundation&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Conservation status of botanical resources in protected areas of Sabah, Malaysia&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Sabah, Malaysia&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;1,600&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;University of Southampton&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Control of Alien Species: the Red-Bellied Beautiful Squirrel in Argentina&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Argentina&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;1,205&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;University of Wales, Bangor&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;In Situ conservation of Indigenous tree species in Southern Cameroon&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Cameroon&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;1,520&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;British Trust for Ornithology&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Meeting biodiversity and socio-ecnomic targets in Ugandan agricultural development&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Uganda&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;2,650&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Plymouth Marine Laboratory&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Namibia Marine Biodiversity Baseline&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Namibia&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;2,400&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Centre for Ecology and Hydrology&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Selection, propagation, multiplication and distribution of indigenous tree species&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Sierra Leone&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;1,705&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;University of Oxford&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Sustainable Management of Forest Medicinal Plants by Peruvian Indigenous Communities&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Peru&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;3,000&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Royal Holloway Institute for Environmental Research&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The macroinvertebrates of riverine wetlands in Ghana&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Ghana&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;2,861&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Tree Council&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Tomsk Forestry and Biodiversity Action Planning&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Russia&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;2,188&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The Natural History Museum&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Training the next generation of Papua New Guinea&apos;s conservation biologists&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Papua New Guinea&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;3,000&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Game Conservancy Trust&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Sustainable management of burrowing mammals on the Tibetan Plateau&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;China&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;3,000&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Cranfield University&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Functional roles of soil microbial diversity in logged ecosystems in Malaysia&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Malaysia&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;2,900&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;33,037&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/table&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/p&gt;' title='Darwin Initiative' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jul/15/darwin-initiative'></outline>
      <outline id='3551947' text='The Minister for the Environment (Mr. Elliot Morley)&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02294"&gt;On 24 July 2003, on behalf of the British-Irish Council (BIG) Environment Group, my Department is publishing the report scenarios of climate change for islands within the BIC region. The report builds on the climate change scenarios for the UK published by my Department last year and provides new detail on how climate is likely to change for the islands of the BIC region&amp;#x2014;Channel Islands, Isle of Man, Western Isles, Orkney Islands, and Shetland Islands. There is now considerable interest in climate change impacts and adaptation in the island administrations following awareness-raising workshops at the end of last year, and the scenarios will provide a sound basis for further work in this area. These new scenarios represent a concrete example of how BIC can foster co-operation between the UK, Ireland and the island administrations on environmental issues of common interest like climate change.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02295"&gt;Copies of the report will be placed in the Libraries of both Houses on the day of the launch.&lt;/p&gt;' title='British-Irish Council Report of Climate Change' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jul/15/british-irish-council-report-of-climate'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3551948' text='NORTHERN IRELAND'>
      <outline id='3551949' text='The Minister of State, Northern Ireland Office (Mr. John Spellar)&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02296"&gt;I have today published the Forensic Science Northern Ireland Annual Report and Accounts 2002&amp;#x2013;03. The annual report sets out the performance of the agency against key targets. Copies of the report have today been laid in the House of Commons.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Forensic Science Northern Ireland' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jul/15/forensic-science-northern-ireland'></outline>
      <outline id='3551950' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Northern Ireland (Angela Smith)&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02297"&gt;I have today arranged for the Ordnance Survey of Northern Ireland Corporate Plan 2003&amp;#x2013;06 and Business Plan 2003&amp;#x2013;04 document to be placed in the House Libraries. This document will also be made available on the Ordnance Survey of Northern Ireland website at&lt;u&gt;http://www.osni.gov.uk/&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/p&gt;' title='Ordnance Survey of Northern Ireland' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jul/15/ordnance-survey-of-northern-ireland'></outline>
      <outline id='3551952' text='The Secretary of State for Northern Ireland (Mr. Paul Murphy)&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02298"&gt;I am announcing today the publication of the Northern Ireland Assembly Elections (Registered Parties and Candidates) Reimbursement Scheme 2003 in accordance with section 3 of the Northern Ireland Assembly (Elections and Periods of Suspension) Act 2003. The scheme has been finalised following the submission to me of a number of recommendations by the Electoral Commission. I am pleased to say that all the recommendations meet the provisions of the Act.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02299"&gt;I have the authority under Section 3 of the Act to make payments, in the form of a scheme, to registered political parties, in connection with their campaign expenditure and candidates, in connection with their election expenses. These parties and candidates would have contested the Northern Ireland Assembly election due on 29 May 2003 but postponed by the Act.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;col&gt;14WS&lt;/col&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02300"&gt;I will be writing to the Northern Ireland political parties today to inform them that I have published a scheme. The Electoral Commission will also write to the parties to give them full details of the scheme including clear explanatory notes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02301"&gt;Although I will be responsible for making payments to parties and candidates following recommendations made by the Electoral Commission, it will be the Commission who will have day-to-day responsibility for operating the scheme. The Commission will only recommend that a payment be made once it is satisfied that a party or candidate would have contested the May election and that the expenditure or expenses being claimed are in accordance with the requirements of the scheme. Claims will only be considered if they are sent to the Commission by 30 September 2003 at the latest and accompanied by the declarations required by the scheme and evidence to support the value of the claim. The Commission will also have the authority to verify all claims by asking for further information, explanations or inspections of documents or goods and property.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02302"&gt;I am very grateful to the Commission for its help in putting the scheme together.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02303"&gt;I have placed copies of the scheme in both Libraries.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Northern Ireland Assembly Elections (Registered Parties and Candidates) Reimbursement Scheme' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jul/15/northern-ireland-assembly-elections'></outline>
      <outline id='3551953' text='The Minister of State, Northern Ireland Office (Jane Kennedy)&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02304"&gt;I have published today the Accounts of the Staff Commission for Education and Library Boards for the period 1 April 2001 to 31 March 2002. Copies have been placed in the Libraries of both Houses.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Accounts (2001–02) Staff Commission for Education and Library Boards' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jul/15/accounts-2001-02-staff-commission-for'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3551955' text='DEFENCE'>
      <outline id='3551956' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Defence (Mr. Ivor Caplin)&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02305"&gt;The Ministry of Defence is announcing today that it plans to allocate up to &amp;#x00A3;2 million for veterans&apos; projects over the next 3 years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02306"&gt;The new Challenge Fund will be used in co-operation with partners in the ex-Service organisations, Non Government Organisations and public sector to pump-prime new projects or research or buy into existing activities in order to give them a veterans-related dimension.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02307"&gt;The Government want this fund to be used to help address the identifiable gaps in existing activity or knowledge that will need to be filled if we are to deliver the agreed Strategy for Veterans. The Strategy for Veterans identifies 3 key areas for further work: ensuring that as many Service personnel as possible make the transition from Service to civilian life successfully, that those who do not make a successful transition receive appropriate support, and that the contribution of the Services and veterans to national and international security is properly understood in wider society. The Government would like the Fund to be used to support a few projects in each area.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;image src="S6CV0409P0I0375"/&gt;&lt;col&gt;15WS&lt;/col&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02308"&gt;Five hundred thousand pounds has been made available for the remainder of this Financial Year and up to &amp;#x00A3;750,000 is planned for each of the next two Financial Years. Arrangements for the longer term will depend on the success of the Fund over this initial three-year period.&lt;/p&gt;' title="Veterans' Challenge Fund" type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jul/15/veterans-challenge-fund'></outline>
      <outline id='3551958' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Defence (Mr. Ivor Caplin)&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02309"&gt;Mortality figures for the United Kingdom veterans of the 1990&amp;#x2013;91 Gulf Conflict from 1 April 1991 to 31 December 2002 were published on 27 January 2003,&lt;i&gt;Official Report&lt;/i&gt;, columns 28-30WS. The latest data, as at 30 June 2003, are shown in Table 1 below. As before, the data for Gulf veterans are compared to that of a control group, known as the Era cohort, which is made up of Armed Forces personnel of a similar size, age, gender, Service, regular/reservist status and rank who were not deployed. Table 2 provides a detailed breakdown of deaths from cancer (neoplasm) by anatomical site.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02310"&gt;On 23 July 2002,&lt;i&gt;Official Report&lt;/i&gt;, column 910W, it was announced that the Ministry of Defence was discussing with the University of Manchester a detailed study of the factors underlying the figures for road traffic accident deaths. There are indications that the excess of motor vehicle accident deaths among Gulf veterans occurred principally during the first six years after the cessation of hostilities (to 31 March 1997) and that this trend has reversed in the following six years to 31 March 2003. Furthermore, the numbers of incidents are relatively small, the information on each accident is insufficiently detailed to allow meaningful analysis and a considerable amount of time has elapsed since 1 April 1991. Therefore, following the advice of the experts that have been consulted, we have decided not to commission the proposed study.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02311"&gt;&#x000A;&lt;table&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td colspan="5" align="right"&gt;&lt;b&gt;Table 1&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td colspan="5"&gt;&lt;b&gt;Deaths to UK Gulf veterans (Note: 1) 1 April 1991 to 30 June 2003 Causes (coded to ICD-9) (Note: 2)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;ICD Chapter&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Cause of death&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Gulf&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Era&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Mortality Rate Ratio&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;All deaths&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;600&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;613&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;0.97&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;All cause coded deaths&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;586&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;599&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;0.97&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;I-XVI&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Disease-related causes&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;243&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;300&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;0.81&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;I&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Infectious and parasitic diseases&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;1.99&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;II&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Cancers&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;105&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;124&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;0.84&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;III&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Endocrine and immune disorders&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;0.20&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;V&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Mental orders&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;13&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;0.86&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;VI&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Diseases of the nervous system and sense organs (Note 5)&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;11&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;0.90&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;VII&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Diseases of the circulatory system&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;82&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;106&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;0.77&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;VIII&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Diseases of the respiratory system&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;11&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;1.82&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;IX&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Diseases of the digestive system&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;18&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;0.83&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;IV, X-XVI&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;All other disease-related causes (Note 6)&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;0.17&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;EXVII&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;External causes of injury and poisoning&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;343&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;299&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;1.14&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/table&gt;&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;16WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;&lt;table&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;ICD Chapter&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Cause of death&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Gulf&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Era&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Mortality Rate Ratio&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Railway accidents&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;3.98&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Motor vehicle accidents&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;118&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;100&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;1.17&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Water transport accidents&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;4.98&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Air and space accidents&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;25&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;19&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;1.31&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Other vehicle accidents&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;0.00&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Accidental poisoning&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;14&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;0.93&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Accidental falls&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;1.00&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Accidents due to fire/flames&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;0.00&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Accidents due to natural environmental factors&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;1.00&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Accidents due to submersion/suffocation/foreign bodies&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;17&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;2.42&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Other accidents&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;31&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;29&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;1.06&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Late effects of accident/injury&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;0.00&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Suicide and injury undetermined whether accidentally or purposely inflicted&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;110&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;103&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;1.06&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Homicide&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;1.19&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Injury resulting from the operations of war&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;0.75&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;Other deaths for which coded cause data are not yet available&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;&lt;b&gt;11&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;&lt;b&gt;10&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;Overseas deaths for which cause data are not available&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;&lt;b&gt;3&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;&lt;b&gt;4&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/table&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02312"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Notes:&lt;/i&gt;&#x000A;&lt;ol&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;1. Service and Ex-Service personnel only.&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;2. World Health Organisation&apos;s International Classification of&#x000A;Diseases 9th revision, 1997.&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;3. The Era group comprises 53,143 personnel, randomly sampled from all UK Armed Forces personnel in service on 1 January 1991 and who did not deploy to the Gulf. This group is matched to the 53,409 Gulf veterans to reflect the socio-demographic and military composition of the Gulf cohort in terms of age, gender, Service (Army, Royal Navy, Royal Air Force), officer/other rank status, regular/reservist status, and a proxy measure for fitness.&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;4. Mortality rate ratios differ marginally from the crude deaths ratio owing to some small differences between the Gulf and Era cohorts.&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;5. These figures include four deaths from Motor Neurone Disease amongst the Gulf cohort and three in the Era group.&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;6. Includes cases with insufficient information on the death certificate to provide a known cause of death.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02313"&gt;&#x000A;&lt;table&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td colspan="4" align="right"&gt;&lt;b&gt;Table 2&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td colspan="4"&gt;&lt;b&gt;Deaths due to neoplasms among UK veterans: 1 April to 30 June 2003&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;ICD 9&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Site&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Gulf&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Era&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;140&amp;#x2013;239&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;All neoplasms&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;105&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;124&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;140&amp;#x2013;149&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Malignant neoplasm of lip, oral cavity and pharynx&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;150&amp;#x2013;159&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Malignant neoplasm of digestive organs and peritoneum&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;22&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;30&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;160&amp;#x2013;165&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Malignant neoplasm of respiratory and intrathoracic organs&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;17&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;25&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/table&gt;&#x000A;&lt;image src="S6CV0409P0I0376"/&gt;&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;17WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;&lt;table&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;ICD 9&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Site&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Gulf&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Era&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;170&amp;#x2013;175&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Malignant neoplasm of bone, connective tissue, skin and breast&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;14&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;13&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;179&amp;#x2013;189&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Malignant neoplasm of genitourinary organs&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;190&amp;#x2013;199&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Malignant neoplasm of other and unspecified site&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;21&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;29&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;200&amp;#x2013;208&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Malignant neoplasm of lymphatic and haematopoietic tissue&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;19&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;14&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;239&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Unspecified nature&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/table&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/p&gt;' title="UK Gulf Veterans' Mortality Data" type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jul/15/uk-gulf-veterans-mortality-data'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3551960' text='TRADE AND INDUSTRY'>
      <outline id='3551961' text='The Secretary of State for Trade and Industry and Minister for Women and Equality (Ms Patricia Hewitt)&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02314"&gt;I visited Baghdad on Wednesday 9 July 2003.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02315"&gt;The purpose of the visit was to support Iraqi women to become properly involved in the political process and to ensure that British business expertise does not get overlooked in the reconstruction work in Iraq.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02316"&gt;I addressed the plenary session of the "Voice of Women of Iraq" conference. This was an important event, organised, run and managed by Iraqi women but with the backing and support of the Coalition Provisional Authority (CPA), especially a secondee to the CPA from my Department&apos;s Women and Equality Unit. In addition to speaking at the plenary session, I participated in one of the workshops looking at constitutional and democracy issues, had lunch with the attendees and private discussions with the steering group who had led the conference.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02317"&gt;Paula Dobriansky, the Under Secretary for Global Affairs at the US State Department also addressed the conference.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02318"&gt;The turnout was impressive in numbers, quality and diversity of participants. This was, of course, only the start of the process of ensuring that women are fully engaged in the reconstruction of Iraq and the political process.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02319"&gt;In the afternoon I met with Ambassador Paul Bremer, administrator of the CPA, and pressed him to ensure substantial women&apos;s representation on the Governing Council. In the event, only 3 women have actually been appointed to the Council which will be a disappointment to the in-country and exiled Iraq women who had expected and asked for a stronger voice. The UK Government will continue to press for substantial women&apos;s representation in future political structures. It will also be important to ensure that those women who are appointed continue to be given support so that they are not marginalised in the political process.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02320"&gt;For part of my visit I was joined by a business scoping mission from British Trade International&apos;s Iraq Industry Working Group. Together we visited the CPA&apos;s Business Support and Facilitation Centre (the brainchild of a UK secondee) and had discussions with senior officials of the Ministries of Industry and Trade about trade and investment promotion and economic reform. We will be following up that visit with offers of&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;18WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;further practical support. The Iraqi senior officials were also keen to make use of UK experience and expertise in economic reform and privatisation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02321"&gt;The scoping mission joined me for discussions with US members of the CPA economics team where I was able to press for the interim budget to be finalised. I also discussed the handling of vested/seized assets and the procurement process, and reiterated the need for there to be a level playing field on the role of the private sector in reconstruction. I also used the visit to highlight the value and quality that the UK private sector can bring to Iraq&apos;s reconstruction.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02322"&gt;In my meeting with Ambassador Bremer, I also discussed the ways in which UK companies might contribute to the reconstruction work in Iraq.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Baghdad Visit (9 July 2003)' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jul/15/baghdad-visit-9-july-2003'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3551962' text='TREASURY'>
      <outline id='3551963' text='The Economic Secretary to the Treasury (John Healey)&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02323"&gt;Further to my written statement to the House on 4 July 2003,&lt;i&gt;Official Report&lt;/i&gt;, column 4OWS, I can announce that today the Government are publishing in full the independent report, its summary and recommendations, of the hon. Mr. Justice Butterfield following the completion of his review.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02324"&gt;The Attorney General and I asked Mr. Justice Butterfield to examine the circumstances that led to the termination of the London City Bond (LCB) prosecutions in Liverpool Crown Court on 25 November 2002, the changes in practice within HM Customs and Excise (HMCE) since the time of the cases to which those prosecutions related, and HMCE&apos;s compliance with best practice in the use of investigation techniques. The full terms of reference for this review were announced in the written statement I made to the House on 26 November 2002, &lt;i&gt;Official Report&lt;/i&gt;, column 9WS. In addition the House will be aware that the Government are looking at the links between law enforcement agencies which investigate serious crime, alongside the review the Chancellor has announced on the future of the tax institutions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02325"&gt;The Government welcome the report, and are grateful to Mr. Justice Butterfield and his team for completing the study so promptly and for the extensive research that underpins his conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02326"&gt;The Review&apos;s main findings are:&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;that there were major failings in the investigation into and prosecution of the LCB cases, investigated by HMCE from 1995 to 1998;&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;but that, since then, there have been significant changes, including:&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;far-reaching improvements in management, structure and culture within HMCE;&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;changes to the legal framework controlling the regulation of Excise warehouses, which have closed the loopholes used by the criminals in the LCB frauds; and&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;following the Gower/Hammond Review, the separation of responsibility for the conduct of prosecutions from responsibility for the conduct of investigations, by making the Customs and Excise Prosecutions Office&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;image src="S6CV0409P0I0377"/&gt;&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;19WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;(CEPO) accountable to the Attorney General, and not to the Commissioners of Customs &amp;#x0026; Excise, since April 2002;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;that these changes have gone a long way towards dealing with the problems within HMCE underlying the LCB cases, and Mr. Justice Butterfield makes a number of recommendations designed to reinforce this change process.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02327"&gt;Mr. Justice Butterfield also identifies three important areas of concern in criminal law and practice highlighted by the LCB cases, all of which have a wider application than HMCE cases. These are:&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;the use of "abuse of process" in trials as a mechanism for attacking investigation processes;&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;the challenges investigators and prosecutors face in complex cases in meeting their disclosure obligations under the Criminal Procedure and Investigations Act 1996; and&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;aspects of informant handling.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;' title='Butterfield Review' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jul/15/butterfield-review'></outline>
      <outline id='3551963' text='Butterfield Review'>
        <outline id='3551964' text='The Government welcome Mr. Justice Butterfield&apos;s conclusion that significant progress has already been made by HMCE in dealing with the issues underlying the failure of the LCB cases, and the unequivocal finding that there is no evidence in the LCB cases of improper enticement or encouragement to commit crimes or of entrapment.&lt;br/&gt;Most importantly, the Government welcome Mr. Justice Butterfield&apos;s conclusion that&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;"HMCE should now put the events of the London City Bond cases behind them and move forward, but not in a spirit of complacency",&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;and the recommendations he makes on how this process, already substantially underway, can be reinforced.&lt;br/&gt;Mr. Justice Butterfield makes a number of important recommendations that encourage HMCE and the CEPO to continue the programme of reform underway in the department. These recommendations relate to:&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;HMCE&apos;s role as an independent investigating force&amp;#x2014;the Government accept Mr. Justice Butterfield&apos;s finding that, under the current arrangements, HMCE should continue in its present role;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;the handling of human intelligence sources&amp;#x2014;the Government accept these recommendations, and HMCE will promptly implement the new guidelines and procedures which are outlined in the Report;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;training for investigators&amp;#x2014;the Government accept these recommendations, and HMCE will incorporate them into an improved training programme for specialist investigators;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;external scrutiny of investigations work&amp;#x2014;the Government accept the principle of external scrutiny of HMCE investigations work, and HMCE has been asked to undertake a study to identify how additional external scrutiny can best be introduced; and&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;HMCE&apos;s regional structure, and in particular expertise in Scottish law&amp;#x2014;the Government agree with the analysis in the Review, and has asked HMCE to ensure that proper and informed legal advice is available to Scottish investigators and intelligence officers.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;In addition, the Review recognises that CEPO has been revitalised since the Gower/Hammond Review and welcomes the changes that have taken place, in particular the increased independence that followed the transfer of accountability for HMCE&apos;s prosecution&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;20WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;function to the Attorney General in April 2002. However, Mr. Justice Butterfield draws a number of conclusions, which include recommendations:&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;that, in order to make its independence from HMCE even more transparent, CEPO should become an entirely separate prosecuting authority accountable to the Attorney General;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;that there should be an increase in the number of Investigation Legal Advisers employed within Customs, who play no part in the prosecution process but are available to provide advice to investigators; and&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;that a more systematic dialogue between HMCE and other Government Departments responsible for related practical and policy issues would be desirable.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Government strongly agree that the ability of prosecutors to exercise their decision making and other prosecution functions independently should be ensured.&lt;br/&gt;The Government will be considering the full practical implications of these recommendations, and in particular how the independence of the prosecutors in CEPO can best be strengthened further. The Government will provide a detailed response to all these recommendations in the autumn.' title='HMCE INVESTIGATION AND PROSECUTION' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jul/15/hmce-investigation-and-prosecution'></outline>
        <outline id='3551965' text='The Review concludes that the criminal justice system does not work as effectively as it should, but recognises that some of the problems identified are being addressed in the Criminal Justice Bill currently before Parliament. The Review recommends that consideration is given to:&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;reforming the operation and rules of the disclosure regime in complex criminal cases;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;the power of judges to control proceedings before them relating to abuse of process; and&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;the operation of the Regulation of Investigatory Powers Act 2000.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;br/&gt;These recommendations have potential implications across the criminal justice agencies and departments. While accepting that they highlight important areas of concern, the Government will give them further detailed consideration before deciding whether to accept them.' title='CRIMINAL JUSTICE SYSTEM' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jul/15/criminal-justice-system'></outline>
      </outline>
      <outline id='3551966' text='The Chief Secretary to the Treasury (Mr. Paul Boateng)&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02335"&gt;The Treasury has today published the document "PFI: Meeting the Investment Challenge". Copies are available in the Vote Office and the Library of the House. The Government&apos;s objective is to deliver world-class public services. To achieve this, sustained increase in investment and matching reforms are needed to deliver efficient and responsive public services. PFI has an important role to play in delivering this investment. The Government have already significantly increased investment to schools, hospitals, public transport and other public services&amp;#x2014;total investment in public services now stands at over &amp;#x00A3;40 billion, up from &amp;#x00A3;23 billion in 1997, and it will continue to rise to over &amp;#x00A3;48 billion in 2005&amp;#x2013;06. While the overwhelming majority of public investment&amp;#x2014;over 85 per cent&amp;#x2014;is funded conventionally, PFI has an important role to play in delivering investment in public services.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;image src="S6CV0409P0I0378"/&gt;&lt;col&gt;21WS&lt;/col&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02336"&gt;The document gives a detailed picture of the role of PFI in delivering this investment and presents a rigorous examination of the performance of PFI based on the evidence drawn from research by Her Majesty&apos;s Treasury and other bodies, in particular the National Audit Office. This evidence shows that, where it is properly used, PFI has delivered better infrastructure, on time, on budget and to a high standard throughout its life. Of the projects studied almost 90 per cent. were completed on time, and in every case the public sector has paid what it expected to pay. The document also reaffirms the Government&apos;s commitment that value for money in PFI projects should not be obtained at the expense of employees&apos; terms and conditions. Drawing on the evidence presented, the document also outlines a series of measures designed to ensure that the public sector effectively captures the value for money benefits that PFI can deliver:&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;reforms to improve the assessment of value for money appraisal by the public sector, to continue to ensure there is no bias in favour of any one procurement option and the decisions are made on the basis of best value for money. These include reforms to the Public Sector Comparator to ensure consistency with the reforms made at last year&apos;s revision of the "Green Book" (the Treasury&apos;s guidance to departments on project appraisal). These changes mean that a value for money assessment of both PFI and conventional procurement options are fully taken into account prior to the procurement of a project, and that there is greater clarity on transferring soft services staff to ensure that application of value for money does not come at the expense of employee terms and conditions;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;measures to improve the efficiency of the procurement process, including more rigorous enforcement of standardisation, the accreditation of advisers, new models of procurement and greater transparency;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;proposals to revise the scope of PFI and focus its use on where it works best&amp;#x2014;exploring new applications for PFI where existing evidence suggests it could deliver benefits&amp;#x2014;as foreshadowed in the Chancellor&apos;s Social Market Foundation speech earlier this year&amp;#x2014;in social housing, urban regeneration and waste, but using conventional procurement methods in areas such as IT and small value projects where experience suggests that conventional methods are the best approach for driving more efficient procurement; and&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;investigating the potential for new methods of financing projects, for example, through "framework funding" for small PFI schemes bundled together and by piloting the potential for using credit guarantees as an additional means of funding PFI projects.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02337"&gt;With over 600 facilities, including 34 major hospitals and over 200 schools, now in operation, and good levels of satisfaction with their performance, this document demonstrates that an intelligent and productive partnership with the private sector can deliver high quality public infrastructure. The reforms set out in the document will help strengthen this partnership for the future.&lt;/p&gt;' title='PFI Review' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jul/15/pfi-review'></outline>
      <outline id='3551967' text='The Chief Secretary to the Treasury (Mr. Paul Boateng)&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02338"&gt;The Treasury and the Department for Work and Pensions are today publishing a Government response to their consultation paper "Proposed Product Specifications for Sandler &apos;Stakeholder&apos; Products", which was launched on 5 February. It takes forward one of the main recommendations of the Sandler review of&lt;col&gt;22WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;July 2002. Copies will be available in the Libraries of the House. The document is also available on the Treasury and Department for Work and Pensions websites.&lt;/p&gt;' title='"Stakeholder" Investment Products' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jul/15/stakeholder-investment-products'></outline>
      <outline id='3551969' text='The Economic Secretary to the Treasury (John Healey)&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02339"&gt;The Bank of England&apos;s Registrar&apos;s Department has conducted gilts registration services on behalf of Her Majesty&apos;s Treasury to date, but will cease to do so from March 2005. A new service provider will need to be appointed to take its place. In preparing for outsourcing this service, the Government have taken the opportunity to modernise the arrangements for the registration and transfer of gilts. The re-engineered model has now been finalised, taking into account comments received in response to a recent consultation exercise. Details of the model are being deposited in the Libraries of both Houses today.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02340"&gt;We plan to put the gilts registration service out to tender over the summer.&lt;/p&gt;' title='UK Gilts' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jul/15/uk-gilts'></outline>
      <outline id='3551971' text='The Chief Secretary to the Treasury (Mr. Paul Boateng)&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02341"&gt;The Strategy Unit report "Private Action, Public Benefit", published in September 2002, highlights some of the key challenges facing the voluntary and not-for-profit sector, and contains a number of recommendations for reform of this sector. Earlier this year the Department of Trade and Industry issued a consultation document on community interest companies, an alternative corporate form in this sector, in response to one of the recommendations in the report. The Government will issue an overall response to the report shortly. The Government now respond to the report&apos;s recommendations on industrial and provident societies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02342"&gt;The Government recognise the importance of industrial and provident societies and welcome their tradition of member engagement, contribution to the economy and service to the community. We are working hard to help support this sector to enable it to maximise the benefits it provides to members, the economy and society as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02343"&gt;The Government have closely analysed each of the recommendations in the report and reviewed the responses to the subsequent public consultation on these recommendations. The response to the report will form a significant contribution to the Government&apos;s agenda for reform in the industrial and provident society sector. The Government are supportive of the report&apos;s recommendations on the industrial and provident society sector. We have accepted in full or in part, six of the seven recommendations in the report. Several of these have already been implemented&amp;#x2014;either because they represent a continuation of existing policy, or they were taken forward by the 2002 Industrial and Provident Societies Act.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02344"&gt;My hon. Friend the Member for South Derbyshire (Mr. Todd) recently enacted Private Member&apos;s Bill gives the Treasury power to bring forward an asset lock-in regime for community benefit societies. Such a regime was a recommendation of this report, and the Treasury is committed to taking it forward. The Government&#x000A;&lt;image src="S6CV0409P0I0379"/&gt;&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;23WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;accept in principle a number of the recommendations, but will undertake further work before deciding how to bring them into effect. These include the recommendations on changing the name of industrial and provident societies to co-operatives and community benefit societies, easing member share capital limits and updating industrial and provident society legislation in line with company law.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02345"&gt;We do not accept one of the report&apos;s recommendations, on giving co-operatives a statutory definition in line with International Co-operative Alliance Principles. This is because giving co-operatives such a definition would risk restricting the development of this form of industrial and provident society in future.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02346"&gt;A detailed analysis to each of the report&apos;s recommendations on industrial and provident societies, together with a copy of this statement, is being deposited in the Library of the House and is accessible on the Treasury website &lt;u&gt;http://www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/p&gt;' title='Industrial and Provident Societies' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jul/15/industrial-and-provident-societies'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3551973' text='DEPUTY PRIME MINISTER'>
      <outline id='3551974' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State, Office of the Deputy Prime Minister (Phil Hope)&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02347"&gt;It was announced in a Written Statement on 10 April this year that preliminary analysis of the responses to the consultation on our proposals to introduce a requirement on electrical safety in dwellings into the Building Regulations had received broad support.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02348"&gt;Full analysis has confirmed this support and the arguments in the Regulatory Impact Assessment (RIA) show that such an introduction would be beneficial to health and safety in reducing the number of deaths, injuries and fires caused by defective electrical installations in homes. Overall the RIA estimates that there would be a net benefit over the first ten years of &amp;#x00A3;93 million at current prices. The RIA also makes it clear that for the introduction to be successful there would need to be schemes of registered competent installers who would be able to certify that their work was in compliance with all requirements of the Building Regulations. Following the advice of the Building Regulations Advisory Committee, I am therefore pleased to be able to announce that it is our intention to amend the Building Regulations to include a requirement on electrical safety in dwellings as soon as suitable competent person schemes are in place. I wish to do this as soon as possible and therefore urge any body intending to apply to run such a scheme to apply to my Department by 15 October this year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02349"&gt;Making householders aware of the need to protect themselves and their families from incompetent workmanship is in line with our drive for better, safer communities in which to live and work. The new measures will also raise industry standards and contribute towards our overall aim of creating a better-qualified workforce. They reinforce the emphasis in the Fire White Paper published on 30 June of greater prevention of fires.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Building Regulations (Electrical Safety)' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jul/15/building-regulations-electrical-safety'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3551975' text='WORK AND PENSIONS'>
      <outline id='3551976' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Work and Pensions (Maria Eagle)&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02350"&gt;&lt;table&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td colspan="3" align="center"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Remploy&apos;s achievement against its targets set by Government for 2002&amp;#x2013;03&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Target&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Achievement&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Gross Margin the Company will Achieve Gross Margin of &amp;#x00A3;53.7m&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;&amp;#x00A3;53.7m&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;&amp;#x00A3;52.7m&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Progressions from Remploy Factories to Interwork and to open employment&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;2,000&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;2,138&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Of which progressions to open employment&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;1,400&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;1,610&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Unit Cost&amp;#x2014;operating deficit per disabled worker&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;&amp;#x00A3;10,173&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;&amp;#x00A3;11,484&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Employee Development Time&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;5&amp;#x0025;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;5.7&amp;#x0025;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/table&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02351"&gt;Remploy will publish its Annual Report and Accounts in the Autumn giving further detail of its performance throughout 2002&amp;#x2013;03. Copies of the Annual Report and Accounts will be placed in the Libraries of both Houses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02352"&gt;In addition, I have, on behalf of my right hon. Friend the Secretary of State for Work and Pensions, written to the Chairman of Remploy approving the 2003&amp;#x2013;06 Performance and Resources Framework between the Department and the Company. The Performance and Resources Framework includes targets for the coming year. The agreement has been negotiated by the Chief Executive of Jobcentre Plus on behalf of my right hon. Friend the Secretary of State for Work and Pensions. The Targets for 2003&amp;#x2013;04 are:&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;a total of 1,650 progressions from Remploy factories or Interwork to mainstream unsupported employment;&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Remploy Ltd. will keep within an average cost per supported employee of &amp;#x00A3;10,400;&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;the Company will achieve a gross margin (sales less cost of materials) figure of &amp;#x00A3;55m;&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;the Company&apos;s Employee Development time will be at least 5 per cent. The full Agreement for 2003&amp;#x2013;04 will be placed in the Library.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/p&gt;' title='Remploy' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jul/15/remploy'></outline>
      <outline id='3551977' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Work and Pensions (Mr. Chris Pond)&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02353"&gt;The 90th Session of the International Labour Conference 2002 adopted a new protocol to the Occupational Safety and Health Convention 1981 (No. 155) and Recommendation 193 and Recommendation 194 on Promotion of Cooperatives. My right hon. Friend the Secretary of State has today laid before Parliament a White Paper entitled "International Labour Conference, proposed action on one Protocol and two Recommendations adopted at the 90th Session of the International Labour Conference 2002 (Cm 5870)", copies of which have been placed in the Library.&lt;/p&gt;' title='International Labour Organisation Conference 2002' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jul/15/international-labour-organisation'></outline>
      <outline id='3551980' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Work and Pensions (Mr. Chris Pond)&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02354"&gt;My right hon. Friend the Secretary of State&apos;s Report on the Standards of Decision Making in the Benefits Agency, Child Support Agency and Employment Service for 2001&amp;#x2013;02 has been laid before Parliament today (HC 880).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02355"&gt;This is the second report under the new decision making and appeals system introduced by the Social Security Act 1998. It covers the period 1 April 2001 to 31 March 2002, the second full year of operation of the new regime. Overall the report shows improvements compared with the previous year. However, some aspects continue to be disappointing, notably overpayment recoverability decisions, but significant remedial steps have been taken in the year since the period of this report to raise standards. Quality decision making is a core element of DWP business and we can assure our customers that raising standards is a priority matter.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Standards of Decision Making' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jul/15/standards-of-decision-making'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3551982' text='HEALTH'>
      <outline id='3551983' text='The Minister of State, Department of Health (Ms Rosie Winterton)&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02356"&gt;We are publishing today our response to the Isaacs Report, which followed an investigation by Her Majesty&apos;s Inspector of Anatomy, Dr Jeremy Metters CB. We advised the House about the publication of the Isaacs Report in a written Ministerial statement on 12 May.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02357"&gt;The Inspector&apos;s report addressed the case of the late Mr. Cyril Mark Isaacs and the retention of his brain for research purposes following a Coroner&apos;s post mortem in 1987 without the knowledge or consent of his widow, Mrs. Elaine Isaacs. Mr. Isaacs&apos;s case proved to be part of an arrangement whereby the&apos; coroner&apos;s office in north Manchester would identify brains suitable for a research programme at Manchester university. The Inspector also found evidence that brains were used following post mortems on adults in other locations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02358"&gt;The report made 34 specific recommendations that bear on the responsibilities of the Department, the Home Office and the Department for Education and Skills. We have considered these carefully and we are today publishing our joint response and copies have been placed in the Library.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02359"&gt;I pay tribute once again to Mrs. Elaine Isaacs for bringing her husband&apos;s case to public attention and to Dr. Metters for his thorough investigation and report. We are very grateful to the Retained Organs Commission and to National Health Service trusts for the arrangements they put in place to deal with inquiries from the public arising from the publication of the report. I understand that the Commission&apos;s helpline has&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;26WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;taken over 860 calls and, of these, some 580 were specific inquiries about organ retention from a deceased person which are being passed to the relevant NHS trusts for investigation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02360"&gt;While there is still work to be done, the programme of action on the removal, retention and use of human organs and tissue that we have put in hand since we accepted recommendations by the Chief Medical Officer in 2001 has already achieved significant improvements. Following extensive consultation, we published on 25 April a comprehensive, interim framework of guidance and other materials to reflect transparent new systems founded on consent. The interim framework comprises: a statement on the use of human tissue and organs under the current law, a code of practice &apos;Families and Post-mortems&apos;, post-mortem consent forms and leaflets, a code of practice on import/export of human body parts and a summary report on the responses to the consultation document "Human Bodies Human Choices". Steps have also been taken to modernise the practice of pathology and to improve the management of joint NHS and academic posts. In addition, the inquiry findings will be taken into account in the development of relevant policy initiatives bearing on death investigation and coronial services which are currently being taken forward by the Home Office.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02361"&gt;We also intend to bring forward legislation establishing a comprehensive new framework for the removal retention and use of organs and tissue from both adults and children as soon as parliamentary time allows.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Isaacs Report (Government Response)' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jul/15/isaacs-report-government-response'></outline>
      <outline id='3551984' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Health (Dr. Stephen Ladyman)&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02362"&gt;We have received the annual report and accounts of the Medicines Control Agency for 2002&amp;#x2013;03 which has been laid before Parliament today in accordance with the requirements of sections 5(2) and 5(3) of the Exchequer and Audit Departments Act 1921. Copies have also been placed in the Library.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Medicines Control Agency' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jul/15/medicines-control-agency'></outline>
      <outline id='3551987' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Health (Dr. Stephen Ladyman)&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02363"&gt;We have received the annual report of the Medicines Commission for 2002, which has been laid before Parliament today in accordance with the requirements of section 5(2) of the Medicines Act 1968.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02364"&gt;Bound volumes have been placed in the Library containing the 2002 reports of the medicines commission, the Committee on Safety of Medicines, the advisory board on the registration of homoeopathic products, the British Pharmacopoeia Commission, the independent review panel on advertising, the independent panel for borderline products and the Veterinary Products Committee.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02365"&gt;We are glad to acknowledge the valuable work done by the distinguished members of the Medicines Act advisory bodies and thank them for the time and effort dedicated in the public interest to this important work.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Medicines Commission' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jul/15/medicines-commission'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3551989' text='FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH AFFAIRS'>
      <outline id='3551991' text='The Minister for Trade and Investment (Mr. Mike O&apos;Brien)&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02366"&gt;The British Government oppose all unwarranted assertions of extra-territorial jurisdiction in commercial cases. Such assertions infringe on the sovereign right of states to regulate activities within their own territory, interfere with the freedom of states to conduct their own economic policies, place an unwarranted burden on businesses, and can create a climate of uncertainty which may affect the trading and investment conditions of British companies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02367"&gt;A number of cases have been brought under the United States Alien Tort Statute against British companies and others in relation to their activities in third countries. Of particular concern are cases brought in the US against British companies in relation to their activities in South Africa during the Apartheid era, alleging that their presence in South Africa at the time made them complicit in human rights abuses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02368"&gt;The British Government have expressed to the US Government their concerns over the extra-territorial use of the Alien Tort Statute in these commercial cases. The US Government have filed an amicus brief in a related case brought under the Statute, seeking to address this issue among others.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02369"&gt;The British Government remain committed to combating impunity for human rights violations wherever they occur. We believe that the most effective means of achieving this goal is the strengthening and developing of credible national justice mechanisms that conform to international human rights standards. We believe that, in the first instance, legal remedies in the country where the act allegedly took place should be exhausted. In the Apartheid cases this does not appear to have happened. Moreover, South Africa is engaged in an ongoing post-Apartheid reconciliation process, the complexities of which should not be under-estimated. We believe that the South African Government are best placed and best capable of dealing with the issue of reparations for crimes under Apartheid.&lt;/p&gt;' title='United States Alien Tort Statute' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jul/15/united-states-alien-tort-statute'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3551992' text='TRANSPORT'>
      <outline id='3551994' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Transport (Mr. Tony McNulty)&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02370"&gt;I have today placed a list in the Libraries of both Houses, which details all the major land assets that Transport for London inherited from London Regional Transport today.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Transport for London' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jul/15/transport-for-london'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3551996' text='CULTURE, MEDIA AND SPORT'>
      <outline id='3551997' text='The Secretary of State for Culture, Media and Sport (Tessa Jowell)&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02371"&gt;I have today published for consultation a set of draft clauses that we intend to be part of a wider Gambling Bill.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;col&gt;28WS&lt;/col&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02372"&gt;The Bill will make major changes to the way in which gambling is regulated and controlled in Great Britain. It will build on the work undertaken by Sir Alan Budd and the Gambling Review Body that he led.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02373"&gt;It is based on the three key principles.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02374"&gt;First, the principle that the system of gambling law and regulation must keep the gambling industry free of crime. Our industry has a high international reputation for integrity, which must not be put at risk.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02375"&gt;Second, the law must ensure that gambling is conducted fairly, so that players know what to expect.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02376"&gt;Third, there must be effective protection for children and the vulnerable.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02377"&gt;The controls we have on gambling today date from the 1960s and 1970s. They have served us well, but have failed to keep up with society&apos;s attitudes to gambling and developments in technology and the leisure industries. They need to be modernised.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02378"&gt;But modernisation must not be allowed to generate an upsurge in problem gambling. I am determined that we will maintain the highest standards of social responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02379"&gt;Sir Alan recommended the establishment of a new national regulator for all forms of gambling. It was proposed that this regulator, the Gambling Commission, should license gambling operators and key individuals involved in the provision of gambling, and that local authorities should license gambling premises.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02380"&gt;In A Safe Bet for Success (published in March 2002, Cmnd 5397) we accepted the vast majority of the Gambling Review&apos;s recommendations. We have been working closely with the interested industries, representatives of groups encouraging responsible gambling, local authorities, consumer groups, other Government Departments and the devolved administrations to prepare draft legislation that would give effect to this new system of regulation, which will be centred on the creation of a new national regulator&amp;#x2014;the Gambling Commission.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02381"&gt;The proposals published today allow for the establishment of a Gambling Commission, transforming the Gaming Board for Great Britain into a new body with wider functions, greater flexibility to act and stronger enforcement powers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02382"&gt;The clauses describe the three purposes of gambling regulation, which will guide the work of the Commission.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02383"&gt;They outline the ways in which the Commission will be able to use codes of practice to ensure best practice across each sector of the gambling industry. Codes of practice issued by the Commission will be an important feature of the new legislation, giving the regulator more flexibility to respond to changing circumstances that may raise issues of consumer protection or threats to vulnerable people.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02384"&gt;The draft Bill goes on to describe the principal function of the Gambling Commission&amp;#x2014;the licensing of gambling operations and key personnel. The Commission will have flexibility to impose licence&#x000A;&lt;image src="S6CV0409P0I0382"/&gt;&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;29WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;conditions on categories of licences and, where necessary, on specific operators. It will also have powers to review licences where it believes conditions have been breached or where there is some other threat to the three objectives of regulation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02385"&gt;Local authorities are to be responsible for the licensing of gambling premises. Details of these proposals will be published later this year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02386"&gt;The Government remain committed also to the sale of the Totalisator Board and the abolition of the Horserace Betting Levy Board. We will bring forward legislation to achieve these objectives as soon as parliamentary time becomes available. Should parliamentary time become available prior to the introduction of a Gambling Bill, we will leave open the option of pursuing our horseracing proposals in a smaller, separate measure.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02387"&gt;I understand that a Joint Committee of both Houses is to be convened to examine the Government&apos;s draft proposals. The draft Gambling Bill is precisely the sort of legislation, cutting across party lines but with some potential for controversy, that will benefit from pre-legislative scrutiny by both Houses. Such scrutiny will improve the legislation and build parliamentary understanding and public confidence, enabling us to strike the right balance between deregulation and the protection of young and vulnerable people.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02388"&gt;The text of the publication can be found at &lt;u&gt;www.culture.gov.uk&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02389"&gt;I will publish the draft Bill in full later this year.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Draft Gambling Bill' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jul/15/draft-gambling-bill'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3552000' text='HOME DEPARTMENT'>
      <outline id='3552001' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for the Home Department (Paul Goggins)&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02390"&gt;The Prison Service&apos;s latest annual report and accounts, setting out the service&apos;s performance during 2002&amp;#x2013;03 is published today and copies have been placed in the Library.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Prison Service Annual Report and Accounts 2002–03' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jul/15/prison-service-annual-report-and'></outline>
      <outline id='3552003' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for the Home Department (Paul Goggins)&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02391"&gt;The Youth Justice Board&apos;s annual review for 2002&amp;#x2013;03 has today been laid before Parliament. Copies have been placed in the Library.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02392"&gt;The Youth Justice Board for England &amp;#x0026; Wales is an executive non-departmental public body established under the Crime and Disorder Act 1998 to monitor the operation and performance of the youth justice system and to identify and disseminate good practice to prevent offending by children and young people. Since April 2000, the Board has been responsible for commissioning services for young people under 18 who are sentenced and remanded to secure facilities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02393"&gt;The Annual Review for 2002&amp;#x2013;03 reports on the continuing progress in implementing reforms to the youth justice system including a successful reduction in juvenile non-custodial reconviction rates and the&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;30WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;continuing delivery of the Government&apos;s pledge to halve the time from arrest to sentence for persistent young offenders.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02394"&gt;The review outlines a year in which new orders and programmes have been successfully introduced&amp;#x2014;most notably the extension of Intensive Supervision and Surveillance Programmes to 80 per cent. national coverage (ISSPs) targeting persistent and serious offenders and the nationwide roll-out of referral orders and youth offender panels for offenders convicted for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Youth Justice Board Annual Report' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jul/15/youth-justice-board-annual-report'></outline>
      <outline id='3552005' text='The Minister for Citizenship and Immigration (Beverley Hughes)&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02395"&gt;I am pleased to inform the House that I have today published the key findings from the report of the independent review of the operation of the National Asylum Support Service (NASS). The review was established in March this year to consider the ways in which NASS operates and provide me with recommendations to improve its performance. I am grateful to the review team for the work they have undertaken. The review team found that NASS was established to undertake a much simpler role than the complex one which they now perform. That role is made even more complicated by being a very visible part of the asylum system. Despite that, the review team found that NASS was showing signs of improvement in its operational performance, strategic planning and relationships with partner organisations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02396"&gt;However, they also found that some key issues still need to be addressed. They found that NASS had faced real difficulties in getting on top of its job. External pressures such as Sangatte, an upsurge in asylum applications in 2001 and significant ongoing recruitment and training gaps contributed significantly to NASS&apos;s current problems and it had failed to establish a clear strategy to provide purpose, direction and governance of its activities. It had been established as a distinct part of the Immigration and Nationality Department, something which had contributed to a lack of proper integration with other parts of the asylum process and unrealistic expectations surrounding issues such as social integration.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02397"&gt;The review team found that there were still considerable gaps in NASS&apos;s ability to deal effectively with its external partners such as local authorities or the voluntary sector. Partly, this was a lack of understanding of the roles of these other organisations, but also a simple lack of effective and agreed processes to ensure that issues ran smoothly. The review team also found weaknesses within some of NASS&apos;s core operations. IT was critical to the business but was neither fully exploited, nor was it properly integrated with the IT used elsewhere in IND. The Review Team said that specific improvements to processes or resolution of long-standing policy impasses were possible which would provide much needed service improvements. The basic customer service provided to NASS&apos;s wide range of stakeholders needed to improve. Within this were concerns such as the difficulties with telephone contact with NASS. The review team supported NASS&apos;s regionalisation project and pointed&#x000A;&lt;image src="S6CV0409P0I0383"/&gt;&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;31WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;to a need for many more aspects of NASS&apos;s business to be handled at a local level. Looking across the range of issues covered, the review team said that for NASS to perform at its best it needs to:&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;be clear what is expected of it and how its success will be judged;&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;have the financial and managerial resources to do the job;&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;have a thorough understanding of its own strengths and weaknesses;&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;have a clear view of what it needs to do to improve its performance;&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;understand its impact on the whole end to end asylum process;&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;sort out some of its key business processes and procedures;&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;get better at working with the rest of IND in a fully joined up operation.&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02398"&gt;Since completion of the review NASS&apos;s senior management team has been strengthened, as has the Immigration and Nationality Department&apos;s ability to deal more effectively with social integration issues. More widely, NASS and other IND staff are currently analysing the proposals contained in the report and will submit an action plan to me shortly. This action plan will form the basis of a major programme of work designed to improve NASS&apos;s performance. I shall make a further statement about the action taken in the light of the review in due course.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Independent Review of the National Asylum Support Service' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jul/15/independent-review-of-the-national'></outline>
      <outline id='3552007' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for the Home Department (Caroline Flint)&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02399"&gt;I have today placed in the Libraries of both Houses details of what was handed in to police forces during the recent firearms amnesty (31 March to 30 April).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;col&gt;32WS&lt;/col&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02400"&gt;A total of 43,908 guns and 1,039,358 rounds of ammunition were handed in. This compares to 22,939 guns and 695,197 rounds of ammunition during the previous amnesty in June 1996.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02401"&gt;I am particularly pleased to see the high volume of hand-ins of all types of gun and ammunition. The amnesty was a great success and these items are no longer at risk of falling into the hands of criminals.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02402"&gt;The guns figure includes 6,529 prohibited firearms (including 5,734 handguns), 10,513 shot guns, 13,974 air weapons, 9,480 imitations and 3,412 assorted rifles and other guns. In addition, a total of 7,093 other weapons, including knives, swords and crossbows, were handed in.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Firearms Amnesty' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jul/15/firearms-amnesty'></outline>
      <outline id='3552009' text='The Minister for Citizenship and Immigration (Beverley Hughes)&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02403"&gt;I am pleased to announce the publication of the independent Complaints Audit Committee (CAC) annual report for 2002&amp;#x2013;03. Copies are available in the Library of the House and on the Immigration and Nationality Directorate&apos;s website.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02404"&gt;This is the CAC&apos;s 9th annual report. Their role is to monitor the effectiveness of IND&apos;s procedures for investigating formal complaints about the conduct and efficiency of staff in IND. Their findings are a very valuable contribution to the process of continuous improvement within IND.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0409P0-02405"&gt;The annual report highlights a number of areas where IND could improve, together with useful recommendations. IND will use these recommendations to help inform their wider change and reform strategy, one of the key elements of which is to make it a more customer-focused organisation.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Immigration And Nationality Directorate' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jul/15/immigration-and-nationality-directorate'></outline>
    </outline>
  </body>
</opml>
