<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Lords Report of 6 May 1937</title>
    <dateCreated>Thu, 06 May 1937 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='2270097' text='Petition of the Lord Mayor, aldermen and burgesses of the City of Bristol and of the Bristol Tramways and Carriage Company Limited, under their Common Seals praying for leave to introduce a Bill to confirm an agreement between the Bristol Corporation and the Bristol Tramways and Carriage Company Limited, for the transfer to the said Corporation of the tramway and light railway undertaking of the said Company and for the provision and joint working of stage carriages and express carriages by the said Corporation and the said Company; to confer powers upon the said Corporation in connection with the operating and abandonment of tramways and light railways and the running of stage carriages and express carriages; to empower the said Corporation to borrow money; and for other purposes; together with a copy of the proposed Bill annexed thereto:&lt;br/&gt;Read, and referred to the Examiners.&lt;br/&gt;HASTINGS CORPORATION GENERAL POWERS BILL.&lt;br/&gt;LONDON PASSENGER TRANSPORT BOARD BILL.&lt;br/&gt;TORQUAY CORPORATION BILL.&lt;br/&gt;Committed: The Committees to be proposed by the Committee of Selection.' title='BRISTOL TRANSPORT.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1937/may/06/bristol-transport'></outline>
    <outline id='2270098' text="Report from the Committee of Selection, That the following Lords be proposed to the House to form the Select Committee for the consideration of the said Bill; namely:&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;E. Hardwicke,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Ellenborough,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. O'Hagan,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Cozens-Hardy (Chairman),&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Woodbridge:&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/ul&gt;&#x000A;Agreed to; and the said Lords appointed accordingly. The Committee to meet on Tuesday, the 8th of June next, at eleven o'clock; and all Petitions referred to the Committee, with leave to the Petitioners praying to be heard by Counsel against the Bill to be heard as desired, as also Counsel for the Bill." title='LONDON PASSENGER TRANSPORT BOARD BILL.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1937/may/06/london-passenger-transport-board-bill'></outline>
    <outline id='2270099' text='Special Order proposed to be made on the application of the Northampton Gaslight Company:&lt;br/&gt;Laid before the House (pursuant to Act) for affirmative Resolution and referred to the Special Orders Committee.' title='NORTHAMPTON GAS ORDER, 1937.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1937/may/06/northampton-gas-order-1937'></outline>
  </body>
</opml>
