<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Lords Report of 10 March 1936</title>
    <dateCreated>Tue, 10 Mar 1936 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='2293846' text='Report made from the LORD CHANCELLOR that Richard Frederick John Donough, Earl of Clancarty, in the Peerage of Ireland, and Viscount Clancarty, in the Peerage of the United Kingdom, has established his succession to the Earldom of Clancarty, and his right to vote at any Elections of Representative Peers for Ireland which may be held in future under the statutes in force relating thereto, to the satisfaction of the Lord Chancellor: Read, and ordered to lie on the Table.&lt;br/&gt;Ordered, That the Report of the Lord. Chancellor made to the House of Lords this day, that Richard Frederick John Donough, Earl of Clancarty, in the Peerage of Ireland, and Viscount Clancarty, in the Peerage of the United Kingdom, has established his succession to the Earldom of Clancarty, and his right to vote at any Elections of Representative Peers for Ireland which may be held in future under the statutes in force relating thereto, to his satisfaction, be sent to the Clerk of the Crown in Ireland, together with a certificate stating that such Report has been made, and that the House has ordered it to be sent to the said Clerk of the Crown in Ireland.&lt;br/&gt;The LORD CHANCELLORacquainted the House, That the Clerk of the Parliaments had laid upon the Table the Certificates from the Examiners that no Standing Orders are applicable to the following Bills:&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Ministry of Health Provisional Order (Bedford Joint Hospital District),&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Ministry of Health Provisional Order (Bury and District Joint Hospital District),&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Ministry of Health Provisional Order (Chester and Derby),&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Ministry of Health Provisional Order (Mid-Sussex Joint Hospital District),&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Ministry of Health Provisional Order (North. East Lindsey Joint Hospital District),&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Ministry of Health Provisional Order (St. Albans Joint Hospital District),&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;958&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Ministry of Health Provisional Order (South Staffordshire Joint Smallpox Hospital District).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&#x000A;And also the Certificate that the Standing Orders have not been complied with in respect of the Petition for additional provision in the following Bill:&lt;br/&gt;Coventry Corporation.&lt;br/&gt;The same were ordered to lie on the Table.' title='EARL OF CLANCARTY.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1936/mar/10/earl-of-clancarty'></outline>
    <outline id='2293865' text='ROCHESTER CORPORATION BILL. [H.L.]'>
      <outline id='2293866' text='The Order made on Wednesday last appointing certain Lords to the Select Committee to consider the Bills, discharged.' title='NORTH WEST KENT JOINT WATER BILL. [H.L.]' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1936/mar/10/north-west-kent-joint-water-bill-hl'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='2293867' text='The CHAIRMAN OF COMMITTEES informed the House that the opposition to the Bill was withdrawn. The Orders made on the 12th and 26th of February last discharged, and Bill committed.' title='EPSOM AND WALTON DOWNS REGULATION BILL. [H.L.]' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1936/mar/10/epsom-and-walton-downs-regulation-bill-hl'></outline>
    <outline id='2293868' text='The CHAIRMAN OF COMMITTEES informed the House that the opposition to the Bill was withdrawn. The Orders made on the 12th and 27th of February discharged, and Bill committed.' title='KINGSTON-UPON-HULL CORPORA TION BILL. [H.L.]' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1936/mar/10/kingston-upon-hull-corpora-tion-bill-hl'></outline>
    <outline id='2293869' text='SOUTH METROPOLITAN GAS BILL. [H.L.]'>
      <outline id='2293870' text='The CHAIRMAN OF COMMITTEES informed the House that in pursuance of the powers given him by Standing Order No. 112 he had appointed the Lord Doverdale as a member of the Select Committee on the said Bills in the place of the Lord Alvingham.' title='EPSOM AND WALTON DOWNS REGULATION BILL. [H.L.]' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1936/mar/10/epsom-and-walton-downs-regulation-bill-hl-1'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='2293871' text='Special Order in respect of the urban districts of Prescot and Huyton-with-Roby, part of the County Borough of St. Helens, and part of the rural district of Whiston in the County Palatine of Lancaster:&lt;br/&gt;Laid before the House (pursuant to Act) for affirmative Resolution, and ordered to lie on the Table.' title='LIVERPOOL ELECTRICITY (EXTEN SION) ORDER, 1936.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1936/mar/10/liverpool-electricity-exten-sion-order'></outline>
  </body>
</opml>
