<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Lords Report of 25 March 1936</title>
    <dateCreated>Wed, 25 Mar 1936 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='2302643' text='&lt;b&gt;GRAVESEND AND MILTON WATERWORKS BILL. [H.L.]&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;YORKSHIRE ELECTRIC POWER BILL. [H.L.]&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Reported, with Amendments.' title='EPSOM AND WALTON DOWNS REGULATION BILL. [H.L.]' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1936/mar/25/epsom-and-walton-downs-regulation-bill-hl'></outline>
    <outline id='2302644' text='Reported, without amendment.' title='ROYAL NATIONAL PENSION FUND FOR NURSES BILL. [H.L.]' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1936/mar/25/royal-national-pension-fund-for-nurses'></outline>
    <outline id='2302645' text="The King's consent signified; and Bill reported, with Amendments." title='SOUTH STAFFORDSHIRE WATER BILL. [H.L.]' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1936/mar/25/south-staffordshire-water-bill-hl'></outline>
    <outline id='2302646' text='Report from the Committee of Selection, That the Lords following be proposed to the House as members of the panel of Lords to act as Commissioners under the Acts, namely:&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;V. Chelmsford,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Carnock.&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Agreed to; and the said Lords appointed accordingly.' title='PRIVATE LEGISLATION PROCEDURE (SCOTLAND) ACTS, 1899 AND 1933.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1936/mar/25/private-legislation-procedure-scotland'></outline>
    <outline id='2302647' text='Report from the Special Orders Committee, That they have examined the Scheme as required by the Standing Orders of the House; that they have received and considered a Report by the Secretary of State for Scotland made in accordance with the terms of Section 1 (9) (&lt;i&gt;a&lt;/i&gt;) of the Agricultural Marketing Act, 1931; that in their opinion the provisions of the Scheme raise questions of policy and principle which have been accepted already by the House when passing the Agricultural Marketing Acts, 1931 and 1933; that the provisions of the Scheme are founded on precedent; that in their opinion the Scheme can be passed without special attention, and that no further inquiry is necessary before the House proceeds to a decision on the&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;286&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;Resolution to approve the said Scheme:&lt;br/&gt;Read, and ordered to lie on the Table.' title='SCOTTISH RASPBERRY MARKETING SCHEME, 1936.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1936/mar/25/scottish-raspberry-marketing-scheme-1936'></outline>
    <outline id='2302648' text='Report from the Special Orders Committee, That no Petition has been presented praying to be heard against the Special Order, and that there is nothing in this Order to which they think it necessary to call the attention of the House:&lt;br/&gt;Read, and ordered to lie on the Table.' title='LIVERPOOL ELECTRICITY (EXTENSION) ORDER, 1936.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1936/mar/25/liverpool-electricity-extension-order'></outline>
    <outline id='2302649' text='Report from the Special Orders Committee, That no Petition has been presented praying to be heard against the Special Order; that they have received and considered a Report from the Board of Trade upon the Order, and that there is nothing in this Order to which they think it necessary to call the attention of the House:&lt;br/&gt;Read, and ordered to lie on the Table.' title='BASLOW AND DISTRICT GAS ORDER, 1936.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1936/mar/25/baslow-and-district-gas-order-1936'></outline>
    <outline id='2302650' text='Report from the Special Orders Committee, That they have examined the Special Order as required by the Standing Orders of the House; that they have considered the Report, dated the 7th February, 1936, of the Unemployment Insurance Statutory Committee made in accordance with Section 59 of the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1935; that in their opinion the provisions of the Order raise important questions of policy and principle; that they comply with the terms of Section 59 of the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1935, under which the Order is submitted for approval; that the Order is founded on precedent inasmuch as an Order has already been submitted for the approval of Parliament under Section 59 of the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1935; that in the opinion of the Committee the Order cannot be passed by the House without special attention, but that no further inquiry is necessary before the House proceeds to a decision on the Resolution to approve the said Order:&lt;br/&gt;Read, and ordered to lie on the Table.' title='DRAFT UNEMPLOYMENT INSUR ANCE (REDUCTION IN WEEKLY RATES OF CONTRIBUTIONS) ORDER, 1936.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1936/mar/25/draft-unemployment-insur-ance-reduction'></outline>
  </body>
</opml>
