<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Lords Report of 30 July 1935</title>
    <dateCreated>Tue, 30 Jul 1935 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='2248489' text='&lt;b&gt;BIRKENHEAD ELECTRICITY (EXTENSION) ORDER, 1935.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;BIRKENHEAD ELECTRICITY (EXTENSION) (No. 2) ORDER, 1935.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt; PORTSMOUTH ELECTRICITY (EXTENSION) ORDER, 1935.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt; DUNDEE ELECTRICITY (EXTENSION) ORDER, 1935.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt; BURNLEY ELECTRICITY (EXTENSION) ORDER, 1935.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Report from the Special Orders Committee, That no Petition has been presented praying to be heard against the Special Orders, and that there is nothing in these Orders to which they think it necessary to call the attention of the House: Read, and ordered to lie on the Table.' title='SMETHWICK GAS ORDER, 1935.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1935/jul/30/smethwick-gas-order-1935'></outline>
    <outline id='2248490' text='Report by the Special Orders Committee, That they have examined the Special Order as required by the Standing&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;958&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;Orders of the House; that they have considered a statement by the Minister of Labour made in accordance with the provisions of Section 55 (8) of the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1935; that in their opinion the provisions of the Order raise important questions of policy and principle; that they comply with the terms of the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1935, under which the Order is submitted for approval; that the Order is founded on precedent in that it re-enacts, with certain additional benefits to the employed person, the Regulations made under the Unemployment Insurance (No. 3) Act, 1931; that in the opinion of the Committee the Order cannot be passed by the House without special attention, but that no further inquiry is necessary before the House proceeds to a decision on the Resolution to approve the said Order:&lt;br/&gt;Read, and ordered to lie on the Table.' title='DRAFT UNEMPLOYMENT INSUR ANCE (ANOMALIES) (SEASONAL WORKERS) ORDER, 1935.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1935/jul/30/draft-unemployment-insur-ance-anomalies'></outline>
    <outline id='2248491' text="&lt;b&gt;BRIDGWATER CORPORATION BILL. [H.L]&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;NOTTINGHAM CORPORATION BILL. [H.L.]&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Returned from the Common's, agreed to, with Amendments. The said Amendments considered, and agreed to." title='BIRMINGHAM CORPORATION BILL. [H.L.]' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1935/jul/30/birmingham-corporation-bill-hl'></outline>
  </body>
</opml>
