<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Lords Report of 27 February 1935</title>
    <dateCreated>Wed, 27 Feb 1935 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='2301512' text='Committed: The Committee to be proposed by the Committee of Selection.&lt;br/&gt;Report from the Committee of Selection, That the five Lords appointed a Select Committee on the Norwich Electric Tramways Bill [H.L.], and other Bills do form the Select Committee for the consideration of the Marlow Water Bill [H.L.]: Read, and agreed to. All Petitions referred to the Committee, with leave to the Petitioners praying to be heard by Counsel against the Bill to be heard as desired, as also Counsel for the Bill.' title='MARLOW WATER BILL. [H.L.]' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1935/feb/27/marlow-water-bill-hl'></outline>
    <outline id='2301513' text='Committed: The Committee to be proposed by the Committee of Selection.' title='SOUTH SUBURBAN GAS BILL. [H.L.]' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1935/feb/27/south-suburban-gas-bill-hl'></outline>
    <outline id='2301514' text='Report from the Special Orders Committee, That no Petition has been presented praying to be heard against the Special Order; that they have considered a Special Report by the Electricity Commissioners under Section 1 of the Electric Lighting Act, 1888, dispensing with the consent of the Bideford Rural District Council; and that there is nothing in this Order to which they think&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;1120&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;it necessary to call the attention of the House: Read, and ordered to lie on the Table.' title='WEST DEVON ELECTRICITY (EXTENSION) ORDER, 1934.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1935/feb/27/west-devon-electricity-extension-order'></outline>
    <outline id='2301515' text='FALMOUTH GAS ORDER, 1935.'>
      <outline id='2301516' text='WIMBLEDON ELECTRICITY (AMENDMENT) ORDER, 1935.'>
        <outline id='2301517' text='&lt;b&gt;PONTYPOOL GAS ORDER, 1935.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Report from the Special Orders Committee, That no Petition has been presented praying to be heard against the Special Orders, and that there is nothing in these Orders to which they think it necessary to call the attention of the House: Read, and ordered to lie on the Table.' title='ANDOVER GAS ORDER, 1935.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1935/feb/27/andover-gas-order-1935'></outline>
      </outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='2301518' text='MINISTRY OF HEALTH PROVISIONAL ORDER (LEICESTER AND WARWICK) BILL.'>
      <outline id='2301520' text='MINISTRY OF HEALTH PROVISIONAL ORDER (CUMBERLAND AND LANCASTER) BILL.'>
        <outline id='2301522' text='&lt;b&gt;MINISTRY OF HEALTH PROVISIONAL ORDER (HOLLAND AND KESTEVEN) BILL.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;b&gt;MINISTRY OF HEALTH PROVISIONAL ORDER (HOLLAND AND LINDSEY) BILL.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Reported, without amendment, and re-committed to a Committee of the Whole House.' title='MINISTRY OF HEALTH PROVISIONAL ORDER (GLOUCESTER AND WARWICK) BILL.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1935/feb/27/ministry-of-health-provisional-order-2'></outline>
      </outline>
    </outline>
  </body>
</opml>
