<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Written Statement of 8 June 2004</title>
    <dateCreated>Tue, 08 Jun 2004 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='3618904' text='NORTHERN IRELAND'>
      <outline id='3618905' text="The Secretary of State for Northern Ireland (Mr. Paul Murphy)&lt;p&gt;I have today published the Probation Board for Northern Ireland business plan for 2004&amp;#x2013;05. The plan sets out the board's key objectives and performance targets for the year. Copies of the plan have today been placed in the Libraries of both Houses.&lt;/p&gt;" title='Probation Board' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/jun/08/probation-board'></outline>
      <outline id='3618906' text="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Northern Ireland (Angela Smith)&lt;p&gt;Stage two of the quinquennial review of the Northern Ireland Health and Social Services Estates Agency has been completed. The report has been made available in the House of Commons, the House of Lords and the Northern Ireland Assembly's Libraries and on the Department of Health, Social Services and Public Safety's website.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The conclusion of the stage one report, published on 4 June 2003, was that the Northern Ireland Health and Social Services Estates Agency should remain in being as an agency.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Stage two examined how the agency operated and looked at the potential for improving its future performance. The consultants invited views from a range of respondents, including Northern Ireland Public Service Alliance (NIPSA), HPSS boards trusts, and agencies and departmental staff. Their report makes recommendations to improve the agency's effectiveness and efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The report's overall conclusion is that much has already been done to address areas for improvement identified in the stage one report. The report recommends, however, more:&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;monitoring of compliance with policy standards;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;consultation and engagement in formulating and monitoring standards;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;practically oriented advice to the Department which can influence capital plans;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;early engagement with the Department on estate-related policy issues with wider implications for capital planning;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;early involvement of the agency in the development and approval of capital plans and business cases;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;involvement in the development of policy which may have capital implications;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;communication and integration across all parts of the agency.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Implementation of the report's recommendations will improve the effectiveness of the agency and will enhance its ability to contribute to improvements in the quality of care to patients.&lt;/p&gt;" title='Health and Social Services Estates Agency' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/jun/08/health-and-social-services-estates-agency'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3618907' text='CONSTITUTIONAL AFFAIRS'>
      <outline id='3618908' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Constitutional Affairs (Mr. Christopher Leslie)&lt;p&gt;My noble Friend the Secretary of State, the Lord Falconer of Thoroton, has made the following written ministerial statement.&lt;quote&gt;"The Queen has agreed that the new courts agency will be named Her Majesty&apos;s Courts Service when it is established in April 2005. The Courts Act 2003 allows the Lord Chancellor to create a new executive agency responsible for the administration of the magistrates&apos; courts and the higher courts".&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;' title='Courts Agency' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/jun/08/courts-agency'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3618909' text='DEFENCE'>
      <outline id='3618910' text="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Defence (Mr. Ivor Caplin)&lt;p&gt;As part of the Ministry of Defence strategy to modernise and improve defence mental health services, I can announce today that the Ministry of Defence has awarded a contract to King's College London, widely recognised as a leader in this field, to establish, in partnership with Defence Medical Services, a Department of Defence Mental Health.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This Department, which will come under the auspices of the Royal College of Defence Medicine, will be based in London as part of the King's College centre for military health research. It will have a small permanent staff, consisting of a senior lecturer in military health studies, who will be appointed by King's, and a clinical senior lecturer and nurse senior lecturer, who will be Defence Medical Services staff. Administrative support and accommodation will be provided by King's.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This department will become a centre of excellence for the study of service mental health conditions, enabling us to develop a better understanding of their causes, treatment and prevention. It will greatly enhance the level of training available to our mental health specialists, and provide invaluable support to our newly enhanced community-based teams of mental health specialists.&lt;/p&gt;" title='Department of Defence Mental Health' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/jun/08/department-of-defence-mental-health'></outline>
      <outline id='3618911' text='The Minister of State, Ministry of Defence (Mr. Adam Ingram)&lt;p&gt;On 4 May, I told the House that 33 cases of civilian deaths, injuries or alleged ill-treatment in Iraq have been investigated by Service Police. The Secretary of State repeated this figure in the House on 10 May, as did the Prime Minister on 12 May.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A detailed verification exercise was put in place to ensure that all cases were being properly investigated and centrally reported. As a result of this continuing exercise it has come to light that the figure given on 4 May failed to incorporate details of investigations from all branches of the Service Police.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The correct number of investigations into civilian deaths, injuries or alleged ill-treatment undertaken at 4 May was 61. Of these 23 were still in progress, 31 had&#x000A;&lt;image src="S6CV0422P2I0010"/&gt;&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;5WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;concluded with no further action being taken and seven were pending a decision whether to prosecute. None of these additional 28 cases relates to detention facilities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have initiated a further 14 investigations since 4 May. These new investigations can principally be attributed to the high operational tempo over the last month, and a small number of new allegations made by Iraqi civilians relating to earlier incidents.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Steps have been taken to ensure that information on all Service Police investigations into incidents in Iraq are now held centrally. I will continue to update the House on significant developments as appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Iraq' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/jun/08/iraq'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3618912' text='WORK AND PENSIONS'>
      <outline id='3618913' text='The Secretary of State for Work and Pensions (Mr. Andrew Smith)&lt;p&gt;Today I have published the Government response to the Work and Pensions Committee Second Report of Session 2003&amp;#x2013;04 [HC 85&amp;#x2013;1] "Inquiry into Child Poverty in the UK" (CM 6200). Copies have been placed in the Library and are available for the Vote Office.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am grateful to the Select Committee for their report which is detailed, comprehensive and helpful.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Child Poverty' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/jun/08/child-poverty'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='2604580'>
      <outline id='2604581' text='The Lord President of the Council (Baroness Amos)&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-06987"&gt;My honourable friend the Parliamentary Under&amp;#x2014;Secretary of State has made the following Ministerial Statement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-06988"&gt;Stage two of the Quinquennial Review for the Northern Ireland Health and Social Services Estates Agency has been completed. The report has been made available in the House of Commons, the House of Lords and the Northern Ireland Assembly&apos;s Libraries and on the Department of Health, Social Services and Public Safety&apos;s website.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-06989"&gt;The conclusion of the stage one report, published on 4 June 2003, was that the Northern Ireland Health and Social Services Estates Agency should remain in being as an agency.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-06990"&gt;Stage two examined how the agency operated and looked at the potential for improving the agency&apos;s future performance. The consultants invited views from a range of respondents, including the Northern Ireland Public Service Alliance (NIPSA), HPSS boards trusts and agencies and departmental staff. Their report makes recommendations to improve the agency&apos;s effectiveness and efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-06991"&gt;The report&apos;s overall conclusion is that much has already been done to address areas for improvement identified in the stage one report. The report recommends, however, more: monitoring of compliance with policy standards; consultation engagement in formulating and monitoring standards; practically oriented advice to the department which can influence capital plans; early engagement with the department on estate&amp;#x2014;related policy issues with wider implications for capital planning; early involvement of the agency in the development and approval of capital plans and business cases; involvement in the development of policy which may have capital implications; communication and integration across all parts of the agency.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-06992"&gt;Implementation of the report recommendations will improve the effectiveness of the agency and will enhance the agency&apos;s ability to contribute to improvements in the quality of care to patients.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Northern Ireland Health and Social Services Estates Agency: Quinquennial Review' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/jun/08/northern-ireland-health-and-social'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='2604595'>
      <outline id='2604596' text='Baroness Amos&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-06993"&gt;My right honourable friend the Secretary of State for Northern Ireland has made the following Ministerial Statement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;col&gt;WS 4&lt;/col&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-06994"&gt;I have today published the Probation Board for Northern Ireland&apos;s business plan for 2004&amp;#x2013;05. The plan sets out the board&apos;s key objectives and performance targets for the year. Copies of the plan have today been placed in the libraries of both Houses.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Probation Board for Northern Ireland: Business Plan 2004–05' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/jun/08/probation-board-for-northern-ireland'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='2604597'>
      <outline id='2604598' text='The Secretary of State for Constitutional Affairs and Lord Chancellor (Lord Falconer of Thoroton)&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-06995"&gt;The Queen has agreed that the new courts agency will be named Her Majesty&apos;s Courts Service when it is established in April 2005. The Courts Act 2003 allows the Lord Chancellor to create a new executive agency responsible for the administration of the magistrates&apos; courts and the higher courts.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Courts Agency' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/jun/08/courts-agency'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='2604600'>
      <outline id='2604602' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State, Ministry of Defence (Lord Bach)&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-06996"&gt;I am pleased to update the House on the events planned, both in France and in the United Kingdom, to commemorate the 60th Anniversary of&#x000A;D-Day.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-06997"&gt;The main events in Normandy on 5 June are the Normandy Veterans&apos; Association Parade and Homage to Field Marshal Montgomery in Colleville-Montgomery; a service held by the 3rd Parachute Brigade at Bavent-le-Mesnil; a tree-planting ceremony at the Royal Naval and Royal Marine Memorial in Ouistreham organised by the RN/RM Landing Craft Association; the inauguration by HRH the Prince of Wales at the Pegasus Museum of a HORSA replica glider; a parachute drop by soldiers of 1st Battalion The Parachute Regiment; the inauguration of the British Garden of Remembrance at Caen; a poppy drop to the Royal British Legion&apos;s chartered vessel the MV "Van Gogh"; and a symbolic crossing of ships from Portsmouth to Ouistreham. Also travelling with veterans will be the winning school from our nationwide competition who will be collecting experiences from veterans before and after the events.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-06998"&gt;On 6 June, there will be a service at Bayeux Cathedral organised by the Calvados Branch of the Royal British Legion; a bi-national ceremony at the Commonwealth War Graves Commission Cemetery in Bayeux, attended by HM The Queen and President Chirac, a landing craft exhibition on GOLD Beach at Asnelles; the international event on the cliff-top above Arromanches, attended by 17 Heads of State, including a naval review, march past and fly past; the Normandy Veterans&apos; Association Final Parade and March Past in Arromanches, attended by HM The Queen, the Duke of Gloucester, the Prime Minister, the Defence Secretary and myself, and a commemorative concert at the Abbaye Aux Hommes in Caen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-06999"&gt;Several commemorative events will take place in the United Kingdom, including a full programme organised by the City of Portsmouth during the weekend, and on 6 June a service at the National&#x000A;&lt;image src="S5LV0662P0I0881"/&gt;&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;WS 5&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;Memorial Arboretum near Lichfield reflecting the event being held at Bayeux Cemetery.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-07000"&gt;The Government recognise the huge significance of this anniversary to the D-Day veterans, around 8,000 of whom plan to travel to Normandy to play their part once again. We have experienced very constructive co-operation with the French authorities and the Normandy Veterans&apos; Association. There is an extremely high level of interest in these events and limited space, especially in Arromanches town centre and Bayeux. We are working with the French authorities to alleviate any problems that may occur. Veterans, of course, will be given first priority.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-07001"&gt;There are several schemes in place to assist those veterans who wish to return to the areas where they saw active service during the Second World War. As I announced to the House on 9 February, the New Opportunities Fund has made available &amp;#x00A3;10 million of National Lottery funding to help with travel costs. The Home Office has provided free one-year passports to veterans travelling for the 60th anniversary commemorations scheme. P&amp;amp;O Ferries has generously offered a 50 per cent reduction in ferry fares to Normandy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-07002"&gt;The role of other government departments, the Imperial War Museum and the National Lottery means that this important commemoration offers a real opportunity to pass on the baton of remembrance to future generations. A commemorative booklet (the third in a series) is being produced and will be sent to all Members of the House early next week.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-07003"&gt;Despite heavy commitments in Iraq and elsewhere, around 1,000 troops will be in Normandy. Our Armed Forces today are proud to be able to offer support to the veterans and their associations of yesterday as they commemorate this important anniversary.&lt;/p&gt;' title='D-Day: 60th Anniversary Commemoration' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/jun/08/d-day-60th-anniversary-commemoration'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='2604603'>
      <outline id='2604604' text='Lord Bach&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-07004"&gt;My honourable friend the Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Defence (Mr Ivor Caplin) has made the following Written Ministerial Statement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-07005"&gt;As part of the Ministry of Defence strategy to modernise and improve defence mental health services, I can announce today that the Ministry of Defence has awarded a contract to King&apos;s College London, widely recognised as a leader in this field, to establish, in partnership with Defence Medical Services, a Department of Defence Mental Health.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;col&gt;WS 6&lt;/col&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-07006"&gt;This department, which will come under the auspices of the Royal College of Defence Medicine, will be based in London as part of the King&apos;s College Centre for Military Health Research. It will have a small permanent staff, consisting of a senior lecturer in Military Health Studies, who will be appointed by King&apos;s, and a clinical senior lecturer and nurse senior lecturer, who will be Defence Medical Services staff. Administrative support and accommodation will be provided by King&apos;s.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-07007"&gt;This department will become a centre of excellence for the study of service mental health conditions, enabling us to develop a better understanding of their causes, treatment and prevention. It will greatly enhance the level of training available to our mental health specialists, and provide invaluable support to our newly enhanced community-based teams of mental health specialists.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Department of Defence Mental Health' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/jun/08/department-of-defence-mental-health'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='2604605'>
      <outline id='2604606' text='Lord Bach&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-07008"&gt;My honourable friend the Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Defence (Mr Ivor Caplin) has made the following Written Ministerial Statement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-07009"&gt;The key targets that I have set the chief executive of the Pay and Personnel Agency for 2004&amp;#x2013;05 are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-07010"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Customer Service and Satisfaction&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-07011"&gt;Key Target 1: Achieve 99.0 per cent average timeliness and 96.8 per cent average accuracy for salary payments, expenses payments and pension awards.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-07012"&gt;Key Target 2: Achieve 90 per cent average responsiveness against key service standards.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-07013"&gt;Key Target 3: Improve customer satisfaction index score from 72.6 per cent in 2002&amp;#x2013;03 to 75 per cent.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-07014"&gt;Key Target 4: Achieve Charter Mark accreditation by December 2004.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-07015"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Processes&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-07016"&gt;Key Target 5: Achieve Main Gate approval for the future pay system by September 2004.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-07017"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Efficiency&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-07018"&gt;Key Target 6: Achieve unit costs of no more than: salary payments &amp;#x00A3;10.60; expenses payments &amp;#x00A3;4.50; pension awards &amp;#x00A3;125.00.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Pay and Personnel Agency: Key Targets 2004–05' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/jun/08/pay-and-personnel-agency-key-targets'></outline>
    </outline>
  </body>
</opml>
