<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Written Statement of 10 June 2004</title>
    <dateCreated>Thu, 10 Jun 2004 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='3618935' text='CULTURE, MEDIA AND SPORT'>
      <outline id='3618936' text="The Secretary of State for Culture, Media and Sport (Tessa Jowell)&lt;p&gt;The provision for the Government indemnity scheme is made by the National Heritage Act 1980. The scheme facilitates public access to loans of works of art and other objects for public display made to museums, galleries and other such institutions by private owners and non-national institutions. It does this by indemnifying lenders against loss or damage to their loan. Loans covered by the scheme must be for public benefit. The scheme also covers loans of such objects for study purposes within borrowing institutions where this would contribute materially to the public's understanding or appreciation of the loan. Examples of this are enhancing interpretation or explanation to the public of objects, or bringing into the public domain the conclusions of any study.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the six month period ending 31 March, the following undertakings to indemnify were given under section 16 by the relevant Departments for objects on loan to national and non-national institutions. The Department for Culture, Media and Sport issued 687 undertakings, the Scottish Executive Education Department issued 179 undertakings and the National Assembly for Wales issued 229.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;col&gt;16WS&lt;/col&gt;&lt;p&gt;The value of contingent liabilities in respect of undertakings given at any time under section 16 and which remained outstanding as of 31 March for the Department for Culture, Media and Sport are &amp;#x00A3;3,177,492,071. The value of section 16 contingent liabilities as of 31 March for the Scottish Executive Education Department are &amp;#x00A3;607,547,273 and &amp;#x00A3;76,817,843 for the National Assembly for Wales.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The value of non-statutory Government indemnities to cover loans handled by the Government art collection and which remained outstanding as of 31 March are &amp;#x00A3;4,975,000.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The value of non-statutory undertakings given to Her Majesty in respect of loans from the royal collection and which remained outstanding as of 31 March are &amp;#x00A3;170,937,987.&lt;/p&gt;" title='Indemnity Scheme' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/jun/10/indemnity-scheme'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3618937' text='FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH AFFAIRS'>
      <outline id='3618938' text='The Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs (Mr. Jack Straw)&lt;p&gt;The FCO has today published a booklet entitled "Inclusive Government: Mainstreaming Gender into Foreign Policy", prepared by its Gender Advisory Group. Copies of this booklet have been placed in the Library of the House. From 23 June it will also be available on the FCO&apos;s website at&lt;u&gt;www.fco.gov.uk.&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mainstreaming gender is about considering fully the impact on men and women of a particular policy, project or service, and taking steps to ensure that those impacts are positive for both sexes. Mainstreaming gender is crucial to the work of the FCO.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This booklet draws together the work the FCO is already doing on gender, and serves as a toolkit for FCO staff to mainstream gender more fully into their work. I hope it will help to ensure that the FCO can devise more effective policies, and make better use of resources, leading to positive outcomes for the UK.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Mainstreaming Gender' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/jun/10/mainstreaming-gender'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='2604436'>
      <outline id='2604438' text='The Minister of State, Foreign and Commonwealth Office (Baroness Symons of Vernham Dean)&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-07030"&gt;The FCO has today published a booklet entitled&lt;i&gt;Inclusive Government: Mainstreaming gender into foreign policy&lt;/i&gt;, prepared by its Gender Advisory Group. Copies of this booklet have been placed in the Library of the House. From 23 June it will also be available on the FCO&apos;s website at &lt;u&gt;www.fco.gov.uk.&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-07031"&gt;Mainstreaming gender is about considering fully the impact on men and women of a particular policy, project or service, and taking steps to ensure that those impacts are positive for both sexes. Mainstreaming gender is crucial to the work of the FCO.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-07032"&gt;This booklet draws together the work the FCO is already doing on gender, and serves as a toolkit for FCO staff to mainstream gender more fully into their work. I hope it will help to ensure that the FCO can devise more effective policies, and make better use of resources, leading to positive outcomes for the UK.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Mainstreaming Gender into Foreign Policy' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/jun/10/mainstreaming-gender-into-foreign-policy'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='2604453'>
      <outline id='2604455' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State, Ministry of Defence (Lord Bach)&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-07033"&gt;My right honourable friend the Minister of State for Defence (Mr Adam Ingram) has made the following Written Ministerial Statement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-07034"&gt;On 4 May, I told the House that 33 cases of civilian deaths, injuries or alleged ill treatment in Iraq have been investigated by Service police. The Secretary of State repeated this figure in the House on 10 May as did the Prime Minister on 12 May.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-07035"&gt;A detailed verification exercise was put in place to ensure that all cases were being properly investigated and centrally reported. As a result of this continuing exercise it has come to light that the figure given on 4 May failed to incorporate details of investigations from all branches of the Service police.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-07036"&gt;The correct number of investigations into civilian deaths, injuries or alleged ill treatment undertaken at 4 May was 61. Of these 23 were still in progress, 31 had concluded with no further action being taken and seven were pending a decision whether to prosecute. None of these additional 28 cases relates to detention facilities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-07037"&gt;We have initiated a further 14 investigations since 4 May. These new investigations can principally be attributed to the high operational tempo over the past&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;WS 16&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;month, and a small number of new allegations made by Iraqi civilians relating to earlier incidents.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-07038"&gt;Steps have been taken to ensure that information on all Service police investigations into incidents in Iraq are now held centrally. I will continue to update the House on significant developments as appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Iraq: Service Police Investigations' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/jun/10/iraq-service-police-investigations'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='2604457'>
      <outline id='2604458' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State, Department for Culture, Media and Sport (Lord McIntosh of Haringey)&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-07039"&gt;My right honourable friend the Secretary of State for Culture, Media and Sport (Tessa Jowell) has made the following Written Ministerial Statement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-07040"&gt;The provision for the Government Indemnity Scheme is made by the National Heritage Act 1980. The scheme facilitates public access to loans of works of art and other objects for public display made to museums, galleries and other such institutions by private owners and non-national institutions. It does this by indemnifying lenders against loss or damage to their loan. Loans covered by the scheme must be for public benefit. The scheme also covers loans of such objects for study purposes within borrowing institutions where this would contribute materially to the public&apos;s understanding or appreciation of the loan. Examples of this are enhancing interpretation or explanation to the public of objects or bringing into the public domain the conclusions of any study.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-07041"&gt;In the six-month period ended 31 March, the following undertakings to indemnify were given under Section 16 by the relevant departments for objects on loan to national and non-national institutions:&#x000A;&lt;table&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Numbers&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Department for Culture, Media and Sport&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;687&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Scottish Executive Education Department&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;179&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The National Assembly for Wales&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;229&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-07042"&gt;The value of contingent liabilities in respect of undertakings given at any time under Section 16 and which remained outstanding as at 31 March is:&#x000A;&lt;table&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Department for Culture, Media and Sport&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;3,177,492,071&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Scottish Executive Education Department&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;607,547,273&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;The National Assembly for Wales&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;76,817,843&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-07043"&gt;The value of non-statutory government indemnities to cover loans handled by the Government Art Collection and which remained outstanding as at 31 March is &amp;#x00A3;4,975,000.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S5LV0662P0-07044"&gt;The value of non-statutory undertakings given to Her Majesty in respect of loans from the Royal Collection and which remained outstanding as at 31 March is &amp;#x00A3;170,937,987.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Government Indemnity Scheme' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2004/jun/10/government-indemnity-scheme'></outline>
    </outline>
  </body>
</opml>
