<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Lords Report of 19 October 1920</title>
    <dateCreated>Tue, 19 Oct 1920 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='2278670' text="Petition of Edith Maud, in her own right Countess of Loudoun, the wife of Reginald Mowbray Chichester Huddleston (now Abney-Hastings), and of Elizabeth Frances, the wife of John Wynford, Viscount St. Davids, claiming to be co-heirs to the Baronies of Botreaux, Hungerford, de Moleyns and Hastings, to His Majesty praying His Majesty (1) to determine in favour of the said Edith Maud, Countess of Loudoun, the abeyances now existing in the Baronies of Botreaux and Hastings, together with the rights, privileges, pre-eminences, immunities and advantages and the places and precedences due and belonging thereto, to hold the same for her and the heirs of her body lawfully begotten and to be begotten for ever; and (2) to determine in favour of the said Elizabeth Frances, Viscountess St. Davids, the abeyances now existing in the Baronies of Hungerford and de Moleyns, together with the rights, privileges, pre-eminences, immunities and advantages and the places and precedences due and belonging thereto, to hold the same for her and the heirs of her body lawfully begotten and to be begotten for ever; together with His Majesty's reference thereof to this House, and the report of the Attorney-General thereon thereunto annexed: &lt;i&gt;Presented&lt;/i&gt; (by command); read, and &lt;i&gt;referred&lt;/i&gt; to the Committee for Privileges to consider and report." title='BARONIES OF BOTREAUX, HUNGERFORD, DE MOLEYNS AND HASTINGS.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1920/oct/19/baronies-of-botreaux-hungerford-de'></outline>
    <outline id='2278671' text="Petition of Edith Maud, in her own right Countess of Loudoun, the wife of Reginald Mowbray Chichester Huddleston (now Abney-Hastings), and of Elizabeth Frances, the wife of John Wynford, Viscount St. Davids, claiming to be co-heirs to the Baronies of Strange of Knokin and Stanley, to His Majesty, praying His Majesty (1) to determine in favour of the said Edith Maud, Countess of Loudoun, the abeyance now existing in the Barony of Stanley, together with the rights, privileges, pre-eminences, immunities and advantages, and the place and precedence due and belonging thereto, to hold the same for&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;4&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;her arid the heirs of her body lawfully begotten and to be begotten for ever; and (2) to determine in favour of the said Elizabeth Frances, Viscountess St. Davids, the abeyance now existing in the Barony of Strange of Knokin, together with the rights, privileges, pre-eminences, immunities and advantages, and the place and precedence due and belonging thereto, to hold the same to her and the heirs of her body lawfully begotten and to be begotten for ever; together with His Majesty's reference thereof to this House, and the report of the Attorney-General thereon thereunto annexed: &lt;i&gt;Presented&lt;/i&gt; (by command); read, and &lt;i&gt;referred&lt;/i&gt; to the Committee for Privileges to consider and report." title='BARONIES OF STRANGE OF KNOKIN AND STANLEY.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1920/oct/19/baronies-of-strange-of-knokin-and-stanley'></outline>
    <outline id='2278672' text="Petition of Selina Frances Bewicke-Copley, wife of Robert Calverley Alington Bewicke-Copley (formerly Bewicke), of Sprotborough Hall, Doncaster, and Coulby Manor, Marton, both in the County of York, to His Majesty, praying His Majesty to determine in favour of the said Selina Frances Bewicke-Copley the abeyance now existing in the Barony of Cromwell, together with the rights, privileges, pre-eminences, immunities, and advantages, and the place and precedence due and belonging thereto, to hold the same to her and the heirs of her body lawfully begotten and to be begotten for ever; together with His Majesty's reference thereof to this House, and the report of the Attorney-General thereon thereunto annexed: &lt;i&gt;Presented&lt;/i&gt; (by command); read, and &lt;i&gt;referred&lt;/i&gt; to the Committee for Privileges to consider and report." title='BARONY OF CROMWELL.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1920/oct/19/barony-of-cromwell'></outline>
    <outline id='2278673' text="Petition of Vernon Henry St. John of Lydiard Tregoze, in the County of Wilts, to His Majesty, praying His Majesty to be graciously pleased to direct a writ to be issued to summon the Petitioner to Parliament by the name and style of Viscount Bolingbroke, Viscount Saint John, Baron Saint john of Lydiard Tregoze and Baron Saint John of Battersea, together with His Majesty's reference thereof to this House, and the report of the Attorney-General thereon thereunto annexed: &lt;i&gt;Presented&lt;/i&gt; (by command); read, and &lt;i&gt;referred&lt;/i&gt; to the Committee for Privileges to consider and report." title='BOLINGBROKE PEERAGE.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1920/oct/19/bolingbroke-peerage'></outline>
    <outline id='2278674' text="Petition of John William Rivallon de la Poer, of Gurteen le Poer, in the County of Waterford (claiming to be Baron of Le Power and Coroghmore in the Peerage of Ireland), to His Majesty, praying that His Majesty may be graciously pleased to give directions that the Petitioner's pedigree and his right to the succession to the dignity and honour of Baron of Le Power and Coroghmore in the Peerage of Ireland may be investigated; as also the outlawry against John Power in or about the year 1091, in order that the same may be reversed if found to affect the Petitioner, and that if the Petitioner be not so affected, he may he admitted to the full enjoyment of the ancient dignity and honour of his ancestors as Baron Le Power and Coroghmore, with all the rights, privileges, pre-eminences, immunities and advantages, and the place and precedence due and belonging thereto, to hold the same to him and the heirs of his body lawfully begotten and to be begotten for ever; or to make such other order in the premises as in His Majesty's wisdom may be deemed expedient, together with His Majesty's reference thereof to this House, and the report of the Attorney-General thereon there into annexed: &lt;i&gt;Presented&lt;/i&gt; (by command); read, and &lt;i&gt;referred&lt;/i&gt; to the Committee for Privileges to consider and report." title='BARONY OF LE, POWER AND COROGHMORE.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1920/oct/19/barony-of-le-power-and-coroghmore'></outline>
    <outline id='2278675' text='A Bill to confirm a Provisional Order relating to Aberdeen Harbour&amp;#x2014;Was presented by Lord Stanmore; read l&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;; to be printed; and (pursuant to the Private Legislation Procedure (Scotland) Act, 1899, Section 7) deemed to have been read 2&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;, and reported from the Committee.' title='ABERDEEN HARBOUR ORDER CONFIRMATION BILL. [H.L.]' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1920/oct/19/aberdeen-harbour-order-confirmation-bill'></outline>
  </body>
</opml>
