<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Written Statement of 7 January 2003</title>
    <dateCreated>Tue, 07 Jan 2003 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='3519306' text='ENVIRONMENT, FOOD &amp; RURAL AFFAIRS'>
      <outline id='3519307' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs (Mr. Elliot Morley)&lt;p id="S6CV0397P0-04012"&gt;One hundred and thirty Parties attended the Conference in Santiago, which took place in a very positive atmosphere in the excellent facilities provided by the Chilean Government.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0397P0-04013"&gt;The Conference considered 60 proposals to amend the species covered by CITES, which are listed in three Appendices. Appendix I lists highly endangered species which are prohibited in international trade. Appendix II lists species in which trade is permitted only under licence. Appendix III contains species which are listed for monitoring purposes only.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0397P0-04014"&gt;I attended the Conference during its second week and presented the UK&apos;s proposal to list the basking shark on Appendix II. Our first attempt&amp;#x2014;made at the 11th Conference in Nairobi in April 2000&amp;#x2014;failed to gain the two thirds majority needed. Since then we have worked hard to produce a stronger proposal based on sound science. This time, following a narrow defeat in an initial vote, we were eventually successful when we took the issue back to the final Plenary session, where we achieved a resounding 82 votes in favour, 36 against and 3 abstentions. I am delighted that our second listing attempt at Santiago has succeeded, providing much needed protection through proper CITES regulation and monitoring of trade. We also welcomed the successful bid by the Philippines to list the whale shark, the world&apos;s biggest fish, on Appendix II.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0397P0-04015"&gt;Another significant success was the Conference decision to support the proposal from Nicaragua and Guatemala to list bigleaf mahogany on Appendix II. We lobbied hard in support of this proposal, and very much welcome the outcome which will help enormously in properly regulating trade in this much sought after timber.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0397P0-04016"&gt;We also lobbied against certain proposals and were particularly pleased that the Parties rejected Japan&apos;s proposals to downlist Minke and Bryde&apos;s whales from Appendix I to Appendix II. We are opposed to all forms of whaling other than subsistence whaling by indigenous people and all EU Member States opposed these proposals at the Conference.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0397P0-04017"&gt;There has been considerable public interest in the elephant proposals. We believe that the outcome of the elephant proposals was fair and reasonable.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0397P0-04018"&gt;The proposals from Zambia and Zimbabwe for a limited trade in products from their elephant populations were rejected, whilst those from Botswana,&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;2WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;Namibia and South Africa were adopted with significant amendments to ensure that adequate safeguards are in place before a one-off sale takes place. Under the terms of the agreement reached in Santiago, Botswana, Namibia and South Africa may conduct one-off sales of their raw ivory stockpiles, but not before May 2004 and only provided that a number of strict conditions relating to trade controls, monitoring and the use of the funds raised for elephant conservation have first been met. The sale will not take place if any of these conditions are not met. Under the agreement, the only trade which may go ahead will be in:&#x000A;&lt;ol&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;a) hunting trophies for non-commercial purposes;&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;b) live animals for in-situ conservation programmes;&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;c) hides;&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;d) leather goods for non commercial purposes;&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;e) registered raw ivory (whole tusks and pieces) subject to the following:&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0397P0-04019"&gt;i. Only registered government-owned stocks, originating in [Botswana/Namibia/South Africa] (excluding seized ivory and ivory of unknown origin);&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0397P0-04020"&gt;ii. Only to trading partners that have been verified by the Secretariat, in consultation with the Standing Committee, to have sufficient national legislation and domestic trade controls to ensure that the imported ivory will not be re-exported and will be managed in accordance with all requirements of CITES Resolution Conf. 10.10 (Rev.) concerning domestic manufacturing and trade;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0397P0-04021"&gt;iii. Not before May 2004, and in any event not before the Secretariat has verified the prospective importing countries, and MIKE (the &apos;Monitoring of Illegal Killing of Elephants&apos; programme) has reported to the Secretariat on the baseline information (e.g. elephant population numbers, incidence of illegal killing);&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0397P0-04022"&gt;iv. A maximum amount of [20,000kg/10,000kg/30.000kg] of ivory may be traded, and despatched in a single shipment under strict supervision of the Secretariat;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0397P0-04023"&gt;v. The proceeds of the trade are used exclusively for elephant conservation and community conservation and development programs within or adjacent to the elephant range;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0397P0-04024"&gt;vi. Only after the Standing Committee has agreed that the above conditions have been met.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0397P0-04025"&gt;On a proposal from the Secretariat, the Standing Committee can decide to cause this trade to partially or completely cease in the event of non-compliance by exporting or importing countries, or in the case of proven detrimental impacts of the trade on other elephant populations. All specimens that are not allowed to be traded under the above provisions shall be deemed to be specimens of species included in Appendix I and the trade in them shall be regulated accordingly."&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0397P0-04026"&gt;In addition to the 60 species listing proposals the Conference considered 71 Resolutions relating to implementation of the Convention. These included a Resolution to address conservation of and trade in tigers and other Asian big cat species such as the leopard, snow leopard, clouded leopard and Asiatic lion; and another agreeing to continue the work of the CITES Bushmeat Working Group for the intersessional period to the next Conference. The Conference rejected a proposal by Switzerland to exempt synthetically derived material from the requirements of the&#x000A;&lt;image src="S6CV0397P0I0658"/&gt;&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;3WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;Convention, but adopted a Resolution outlining simplified procedures for issuing permits and certificates for time sensitive biological samples which will reduce the administrative burden on those transmitting DMA or other diagnostic samples for example.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0397P0-04027"&gt;The UK&apos;s application on behalf of the Cayman Islands to register the Cayman Turtle Farm narrowly failed to obtain the necessary two thirds majority for approval, despite support from the CITES Secretariat and many Parties. The main concerns were over the lack of proof of legality of the founder stock, and possible mixing with and contamination of wild stocks. The Farm will now seek to address the concerns which emerged in debate, with a view to resubmitting this application under the CITES postal procedure.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0397P0-04028"&gt;I believe that this represents an excellent outcome overall, not only for the UK but also for the CITES process itself, which has demonstrated that countries all over the world can unite to provide effective conservation measures to protect a wide range of commercially exploited species.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species (12th Conference)' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jan/07/convention-on-international-trade-in'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3519319' text='FOREIGN &amp; COMMONWEALTH'>
      <outline id='3519320' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs (Mr. Mike O&apos;Brien)&lt;p id="S6CV0397P0-04029"&gt;The Government has recently issued a licence for the export of synchros to be used as an inspection tool on Tay 650 engines used to power Fokker 100 aircraft. These synchros were made as military electronic equipment. However, the Government is satisfied that these synchros are to be used only for the upkeep of the Fokker 100, a civil aircraft. The risk of these goods being diverted for use by the Iranian military is minimal.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Arms Embargo (Iran)' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jan/07/arms-embargo-iran'></outline>
      <outline id='3519322' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs (Mr. Mike O&apos;Brien)&lt;p id="S6CV0397P0-04030"&gt;The Foreign and Commonwealth Office (FCO) travel advice for Indonesia was today changed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0397P0-04031"&gt;Previously it advised against all travel to the country. It now advises against all non-essential travel to Indonesia. The FCO continues to assess that the threat to British nationals and British interests from terrorism throughout Indonesia remains high and that British nationals already in Indonesia should consider leaving if their presence is not essential.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0397P0-04032"&gt;The decision to change the advice was taken after careful consideration of the latest information, including intelligence. It also brings it into line with the latest advice of the Australian Government. The terrorist threat in Indonesia remains real, and further attacks cannot be ruled out. But account has also been taken of the strengthened Indonesian commitment and actions since Bali to confront the terrorists.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0397P0-04033"&gt;Since Bali there has been only one significant attack, at a McDonalds restaurant and a car showroom in Makassar, Sulawesi, in December, which killed three Indonesian nationals. A number of anti-terrorist decrees have been passed and some important arrests&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;4WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;made in respect of the Bali bombings and previous terrorist incidents. The Muslim mass movements are now speaking out against terrorism. The radical cleric Abu Bakar Bashir has been held for police questioning. The Indonesians have also provided more security than before to diplomatic missions and international schools, as well as other non-specifically Western targets, such as shopping malls, entertainment centres and churches.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0397P0-04034"&gt;A copy of the latest advice can be found on the FCO web site www.fco.gov.uk.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Indonesia (Travel Advice)' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jan/07/indonesia-travel-advice'></outline>
      <outline id='3519325' text='The Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs (Mr. Jack Straw)&lt;p id="S6CV0397P0-04035"&gt;As I have made clear to the House on a number of occasions, our policy on Iraq is to ensure Iraq complies with its obligations under relevant United Nations Security Council resolutions (UNSCRs), including by giving up its weapons of mass destruction. I thought, however, that the House would now appreciate a more detailed statement of the Government&apos;s objectives on Iraq.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0397P0-04036"&gt;Our prime objective is to rid Iraq of its weapons of mass destruction (WMD) and their associated programmes and means of delivery, including prohibited ballistic missiles (BM), as set out in UNSCRs. This would reduce Iraq&apos;s ability to threaten its neighbours and the region, and prevent Iraq using WMD against its own people. UNSCRs also require Iraq to renounce terrorism, and return captured Kuwaitis and property taken from Kuwait.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0397P0-04037"&gt;These UNSCRs are an expression of the will of the international community, with which Iraq has persistently failed to comply, thereby perpetuating the threat to international peace and security.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0397P0-04038"&gt;A further objective is to maintain the authority of the United Nations by demonstrating the Security Council&apos;s effective response to the challenge posed by Iraq&apos;s non-compliance. Success in achieving our prime objective should help deter the proliferation of WMD and BM more generally.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0397P0-04039"&gt;We have pursued these objectives through the United Nations, culminating in the unanimous adoption by the Security Council of UNSCR 1441 (2002) on 8 November 2002.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0397P0-04040"&gt;Our immediate priorities are to:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0397P0-04041"&gt;a) Support the work of the UNMOVIC/IAEA inspectors in Iraq;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0397P0-04042"&gt;b) Enable UNMOVIC/IAEA to institute long-term measures to ensure compliance as part of their Ongoing Monitoring and Verification regime;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0397P0-04043"&gt;c) Maintain international solidarity behind the United Nations Security Council and support for effective UN MOVIC/IAEA action;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0397P0-04044"&gt;d) Preserve regional stability;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0397P0-04045"&gt;e) Continue to make military plans and preparations in case military action is required to enforce compliance by Iraq with its WMD/BM obligations under UNSCRs;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0397P0-04046"&gt;f) Continue to support humanitarian efforts to relieve the suffering of the Iraqi people.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0397P0-04047"&gt;We would like Iraq to become a stable, united and law abiding state, within its present borders, co-operating with the international community, no longer posing a&#x000A;&lt;image src="S6CV0397P0I0659"/&gt;&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;5WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;threat to its neighbours or to international security, abiding by all its international obligations and providing effective and representative government for its own people.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0397P0-04048"&gt;These objectives are consistent with wider government policy, which includes:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0397P0-04049"&gt;a) Efforts to resolve other causes of regional instability, including the Middle East Peace Process;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0397P0-04050"&gt;b) Wider political engagement with Arab countries and the Islamic world;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0397P0-04051"&gt;c) Efforts to counter the proliferation of WMD; and&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0397P0-04052"&gt;d) The elimination of terrorism as a force in international affairs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0397P0-04053"&gt;To achieve our objectives we will act in conformity with international law, including the United Nations Charter and international humanitarian law.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;col&gt;6WS&lt;/col&gt;&lt;p id="S6CV0397P0-04054"&gt;Consistent with the above, we are working intensively with our allies and partners to secure the peaceful disarmament of Iraq&apos;s WMD by means of UNMOVIC/IAEA inspections. But as SCR 1441 makes clear, if the Iraqi regime does not comply, it will face serious consequences.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Iraq' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jan/07/iraq'></outline>
      <outline id='3519327' text='The Minister for Europe (Mr. Denis MacShane)&lt;p id="S6CV0397P0-04055"&gt;I am pleased to announce that I have today appointed Professor Anthony Bradley as the Alternate UK Member of the European Commission for Democracy through Law (the Venice Commission). The Venice Commission is a Council of Europe body, which is made up of constitutional experts who provide member states with advice on constitutions and democratic institutions furthering human rights and the rule of law.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Venice Commission (Alternate UK Member)' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jan/07/venice-commission-alternate-uk-member'></outline>
    </outline>
  </body>
</opml>
