<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Written Statement of 31 January 2003</title>
    <dateCreated>Fri, 31 Jan 2003 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='3516024' text='CABINET OFFICE'>
      <outline id='3516025' text="The Minister of State, Cabinet Office (Mr. Douglas Alexander)&lt;p&gt;I have today placed in the Libraries of the House, the latest edition of the annual Cabinet Office publication,&lt;i&gt;Public Bodies.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Public Bodies 2002&lt;/i&gt; is the latest in a series of publications providing information on public bodies sponsored by government.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition to giving details about the remit and expenditure of public bodies, the publication also gives information about the number of women, people from minority ethnic backgrounds and people with disabilities, who sit on the boards of public bodies. I am pleased to announce that the proportion of those from minority ethnic backgrounds and those with disabilities holding public appointments have increased from 4.8 per cent. to 6.2 per cent. and from 1.5 per cent. to 3.3 per cent. respectively, although it is disappointing that the percentage of women holding such appointments, 34 per cent., has remained static. Departments will continue to work hard to encourage increased participation of women on the boards of public bodies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Additionally, this year's publication includes information about the Government's task forces, ad hoc advisory groups and reviews. Previously these were reported on separately, and to a different timetable. Including this data in one publication gives a more complete picture of the extended bodies and groups working to deliver government objectives.&lt;/p&gt;" title='Public Bodies' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jan/31/public-bodies'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3516038' text='ENVIRONMENT, FOOD AND RURAL AFFAIRS'>
      <outline id='3516039' text='The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs (Mr. Elliot Morley)&lt;p&gt;With the consent of the Treasury, the schedule of fees for registration, retention and restoration of&lt;col&gt;52WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;agricultural merchants and saddlers with the Royal Pharmaceutical Society of Great Britain has been determined. This is given in the table:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&#x000A;&lt;table&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td colspan="3"&gt;&lt;i&gt;FEES&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Application in respect of each premises&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Previous fee &amp;#x00A3;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;&lt;i&gt;New fee &amp;#x00A3;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Agricultural Merchants&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;For registration under Article 5&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;232&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;232&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;For retention of registration under Article 5&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;140&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;153&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;For restoration of registration under Article 5&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;197&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;197&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Saddlers&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;For registration under Article 5&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;127&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;127&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;For retention of registration under Article 5&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;76&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;83&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;For restoration of registration under Article 5&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;107&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td align="right"&gt;107&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/table&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/p&gt;' title="Agricultural Merchants and Saddlers' Fees" type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jan/31/agricultural-merchants-and-saddlers-fees'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3516041' text='HEALTH'>
      <outline id='3516042' text="The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Health (Mr. David Lammy)&lt;p&gt;I have announced today that Community Health Councils (CHCs) will be abolished on 1 September 2003. Abolition was announced in the NHS Plan and relevant legislation is in the NHS Reform and Health Care Professions Act 2002.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CHC staff have been sent details of the support arrangements for them in the run up to abolition and includes help and advice for them in finding alternative employment. These arrangements have been agreed with the trade unions. I have personally written to all staff and members of CHC acknowledging the service they have provided over the years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We are modernising the way patients and public are involved in the delivery and design of NHS services. Between now and September the functions that CHCs currently carry out will move across to one of the bodies that will replace them. The new arrangements have a number of key components that radically transform patient and public involvement. Already the Commission for Patient and Public Involvement in Health has been established and we are working with it to establish patients' forums for every NHS trust and primary care trust in England. Since the 1 January Overview and Scrutiny Committees across England have had the power to scrutinise health and there has been a new duty on the NHS to involve and consult the public. Patient advice and liaison services are supporting patients, their families and carers in most trusts in England.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Commission for Patient and Public Involvement in Health will make available more information about when and how patients' forums will be established later today.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Copies of the information that has been sent to CHC staff and members is available at www.doh.gov.uk/involvingpatients.&lt;/p&gt;" title='Community Health Councils' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/jan/31/community-health-councils'></outline>
    </outline>
  </body>
</opml>
