<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Lords Report of 9 March 1922</title>
    <dateCreated>Thu, 09 Mar 1922 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='2284554' text='Committee for Privileges met: Counsel heard to open the case on behalf of the Claimant: Witnesses examined: Evidence put in: Claim considered: Then it was resolved that the Petitioner, William Charles Arcedeckne, Baron Huntingfield, in the Peerage of Ireland, hath made out his claim to vote at the elections of representative Peers for Ireland; the report thereof to be made to the House.' title='HUNTINGFIELD (CLAIM TO VOTE).' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1922/mar/09/huntingfield-claim-to-vote'></outline>
    <outline id='2284555' text="Committee for Privileges met: Petitions of James Marquess of Salisbury and Earl of Salisbury, Viscount Cranborne and Baron Cecil, and of Francis, Earl Brooke of Warwick Castle, Earl of Warwick and Baron Brooke of Beauchamp's Court (presented on Friday last) considered, and Counsel heard thereon: Then the Committee resolved that the said James Marquess of Salisbury, and the said Francis, Earl Brooke of Warwick Castle should be allowed to appear jointly and be heard before the Committee for Privileges by their Counsel and Agents, in opposition to the claim of Edith Maud, Countess of Loudoun, and Elizabeth Frances, Viscountess St. Davids, and that they should be at liberty to cross-examine such witnesses as the said claimants may produce and to lodge jointly a printed case, and to produce such evidence in contradiction of any evidence that may be produced by the said claimants, and also such evidence as will support their right and title to the said Earldoms of Warwick and Salisbury as they may be advised to be material for the protection of their rights and interests; and that the said Marquess of Salisbury, and the said Earl of Warwick should be allowed to refer in their joint case to the documentary proofs produced in evidence by the Duke of Norfolk, in opposition to the claim of Charles Botolph Joseph, Lord Mowbray, to the dignity of Earl of Norfolk, and to the documentary proofs offered by the Duke of Atholl in his claim to the Earldom of Oxford; and the Committee further resolved that the said Marquess of Salisbury should not be required to prove that he is the rightful bolder of the title&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;460&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;of Earl of Salisbury, granted in 1605, and that the said Earl Brooke of Warwick should not be required to prove that he is the rightful holder of the title of Earl of Warwick, granted in 1759; and Report of the said Resolution to be made to the House: Committee adjourned sine die." title='EARLDOMS OF SALISBURY AND WARWICK.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1922/mar/09/earldoms-of-salisbury-and-warwick'></outline>
    <outline id='2284556' text="A Bill to dissolve the marriage of Violet Emily Crofts with Christopher Nason Crofts, her present husband, and to enable her to marry again, and for other purposes: Presented, on Petition, and a copy of the Proceedings in, and of the Decree of Divorce of, the King's Bench Matrimonial Division of the High Court of Justice in Ireland: Delivered (on oath): Bill read 1&amp;#x00AA;." title="CROFTS' DIVORCE BILL. [H.L.]" type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1922/mar/09/crofts-divorce-bill-hl'></outline>
    <outline id='2284557' text='To be read 2&amp;#x00AA; on Wednesday next, March 15.' title='IRISH FREE STATE (AGREEMENT) BILL.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1922/mar/09/irish-free-state-agreement-bill'></outline>
    <outline id='2284558' text='Brought from the Commons; to be printed; and referred to the Examiners.' title='MARRIAGES PROVISIONAL ORDER BILL.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1922/mar/09/marriages-provisional-order-bill'></outline>
    <outline id='2284559' text='Second Report from the Select Committee made, and to be printed.' title='HOUSE OF LORDS OFFICES.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1922/mar/09/house-of-lords-offices'></outline>
    <outline id='2284560' text='Report from the Committee of Selection, that the Lords following be proposed to the House as the panel of Lords to act as Commissioners under the Act, namely&amp;#x2014;&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Oranmore and Browne,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Meston:&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Agreed to; and the said Lords appointed accordingly.&lt;br/&gt;[&lt;i&gt;From Minutes of Judicial Sitting, March&lt;/i&gt; 10.]' title='PRIVATE LEGISLATION PROCEDURE (SCOTLAND) ACT, 1899.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1922/mar/09/private-legislation-procedure-scotland'></outline>
    <outline id='2284561' text='Consideration of the Report of the Committee for Privileges (which stands appointed for Wednesday next) put off to Wednesday, March 22.' title='RHONDDA (PETITION FOR WRIT OF SUMMONS).' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1922/mar/09/rhondda-petition-for-writ-of-summons'></outline>
    <outline id='2284562' text="Report made from the Committee for Privileges&amp;#x2014;&lt;br/&gt;That the Barony of Cromwell is an ancient Barony in fee.&lt;br/&gt;That it is proved by the Writ of Summons 28th December, in the 49th year of King Edward III. and by other evidence adduced by the Petitioner that Ralph de Cromwell, Lord Cromwell was summoned to Parliament and sat in Parliament as a Peer of the Realm.&lt;br/&gt;That the Barony of Cromwell fell into abeyance on the death without issue of Ralph, third Lord Cromwell about the year 1455 between his nieces and co-heirs Maud, widow of Robert, Lord Willoughby de Eresby and loan, wife of Sir Humphrey-Bourchier&lt;br/&gt;That after the death of Joan without issue 10th March, 1190, Maud succeeded in her own right as Baroness Cromwell and died without issue 30th August, 1497.&lt;br/&gt;That the Barony of Cromwell then fell into abeyance between co-heirs, being the heirs respectively of the daughters of Ralph, first Lord Cromwell.&lt;br/&gt;That William FitzWilliam of Sprotborough in the County of York was one of the aforesaid co-heirs being the sole heir of Maud, wife of Sir William FitzWilliam of Sprotborough and a daughter of Ralph first Lord Cromwell.&lt;br/&gt;That James Duke of Abercorn, Dame Selina Frances Bewicke-Copley of Sprotborough (the Petitioner), Charles john Peebles Chaplin, Mrs. Amabel Jemima Somers-Cocks, and the heir or heirs, if any, of Dame Elizabeth Savile, wife of Sir Henry Savile of Thornhill and Tankersley, are now the co-heirs of William FitzWilliam of Sprotborough, and are co-heirs of the Barony of Cromwell, now in abeyance.&lt;br/&gt;That the Barony of Cromwell is now in abeyance between the co-heirs aforesaid and the other co-heirs, if any, of Ralph first Lord Cromwell, and is now at His Majesty's disposal.&lt;br/&gt;Read; and agreed to; and resolved and adjudged accordingly; and Resolution and Judgment to be laid before His Majesty by the Lords with White Staves.&lt;br/&gt;Ordered, That all deeds, documents and papers produced on behalf of the Claimant by her agents, be delivered to the said agents." title='BARONY OF CROMWELL.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1922/mar/09/barony-of-cromwell'></outline>
    <outline id='2284563' text='Report made from the Committee for Privileges, That the Claimant, Vernon Henry St. John, has made out his claim to the titles, honours and dignities of Viscount Bolingbroke and Viscount St. John, Baron St. John of Lydiard Tregoze, and. Baron of Battersea, all in the Peerage of Great Britain: Bead, and agreed to; and resolved and adjudged accordingly and Resolution and Judgment to be laid before His Majesty by the Lords with White Staves.&lt;br/&gt;Ordered, That all deeds, documents and papers produced on behalf of the Claimant by his agents, be delivered to the said agents.' title='BOLINGBROKE PEERAGE.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1922/mar/09/bolingbroke-peerage'></outline>
    <outline id='2284564' text='Report made from the Committee for Privileges&amp;#x2014;&#x000A;&lt;ol&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;1. That Sir Richard Power, Knight, was in the year 1535 created by Letters Patent of King Henry VIII. Baron of Le Power and Coroghmore, in the Peerage of Ireland, to him and the heirs male of his body.&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;2. That the said Barony in the year 1704 devolved on John Power, who was then under outlawry and therefore incapable of succession, and that the said outlawry still subsists.&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;3. That the Petitioner, John William Rivallon de la Poer, is the heir male of the body of Sir Richard Power, Knight, first Baron Le Power and Coroglimore, and that there exists no corruption of blood in the direct line of his descent.&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;4. That but for the outlawry of John Power, the predecessor in title of the Petitioner, the Barony of Le Power and Coroghmore would now be vested in the Petitioner as the heir male of the body of Sir Richard Power, Knight, the first Baron.&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/ol&gt;&#x000A;&lt;image src="S5LV0049P0I0260"/&gt;&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;463&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;Read, and agreed to: and resolved and adjudged accordingly; and Resolution and Judgment to be laid before His Majesty by the Lords with White Staves.&lt;br/&gt;Ordered, That all deeds, documents and papers produced on behalf of the Claimant by his agents, be delivered to the said agents.' title='BARONY OF LE POWER AND COROGHAIORE.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1922/mar/09/barony-of-le-power-and-coroghaiore'></outline>
    <outline id='2284565' text='EARLDOMS OF SALISBURY AND WARWICK.'>
      <outline id='2284566' text='Report made from the Committee for Privileges: Read, and agreed to; and ordered to lie on the Table.' title='PETITIONS TO BE HEARD IN OPPOSITION.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1922/mar/09/petitions-to-be-heard-in-opposition'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='2284567' text='Report from the Committee for Privileges that William Charles Arcedeckne, Baron Huntingfield, in the Peerage of Ireland, has made out his claim to vote at the elections of Representative Peers for Ireland; read, and agreed to; and resolved and adjudged accordingly.&lt;br/&gt;Ordered, That all deeds, documents, and papers produced on behalf of the Petitioner by his agent, be delivered to the said agent.' title='HUNTINGFIELD (CLAIM TO VOTE).' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1922/mar/09/huntingfield-claim-to-vote-1'></outline>
    <outline id='2284569' text='To be read 2&amp;#x00AA; on Thursday, March 23: The usual Orders made.' title="CROFTS' DIVORCE BILL. [H.L.]" type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1922/mar/09/crofts-divorce-bill-hl-1'></outline>
    <outline id='2284571' text="The Lord Speaker acquainted the House that the Clerk of the Parliaments had received by post from the Lord Justice of the King's Bench Division of the High Court of Justice in Ireland, a Report of the Proceedings upon the inquiry before him in the case Babington &lt;i&gt;v.&lt;/i&gt; D'Alton. The same was ordered to lie on the Table." title="BABINGTON'S DIVORCE BILL. [H.L.]" type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1922/mar/09/babingtons-divorce-bill-hl'></outline>
  </body>
</opml>
