<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Lords Report of 9 September 1941</title>
    <dateCreated>Tue, 09 Sep 1941 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='2308644' text="Reported, without amendment, with a Report from the Chairman of Committees under Standing Order No.110, that in his opinion the Bill should be proceeded with as an opposed Bill.&lt;br/&gt;Bill re-committed: The Committee to be proposed by the Committee of Selection.&lt;br/&gt;Report from the Committee of Selection, That the following Lords be proposed to the House to form the Select Committee for the consideration of the said Bill; namely:&amp;#x2014;&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;E. Strafford,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Greville,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Faringdon,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Russell of Killowen,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;L. Romer (Chairman):&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Agreed to; and the said Lords appointed accordingly. The Committee to meet tomorrow, at eleven o'clock; with leave to the Promoters to be heard by Counsel if they see fit." title='SCARISBRICK ESTATE BILL. [H.L.]' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1941/sep/09/scarisbrick-estate-bill-hl'></outline>
    <outline id='2308645' text='Orders made by the Secretary of State for the Home Department, extending Section I of the Act to the&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;22&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;&lt;ul&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Borough of Crewe,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Borough of Crosby,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Borough of Barrow-in-Furness,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;City of Salford,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;Borough of Sudbury,&lt;/li&gt;&#x000A;&lt;li&gt;City of Wells (Somerset):&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Laid before the House (pursuant to Act), for affirmative Resolution and ordered to lie on the Table.' title='SUNDAY ENTERTAINMENTS ACT, 1932.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1941/sep/09/sunday-entertainments-act-1932'></outline>
    <outline id='2308646' text='Report from the Special Orders Committee, That they have examined the Special Order as required by the Standing Orders of the House; that in their opinion the Order raises important questions of policy and principle; that the Order is not founded on precedent, inasmuch as no proposal for the amendment of the First Schedule of the Prices of Goods Act, 1939, has hitherto been submitted to the House; that in the opinion of the Committee the Order cannot be passed by the House without special attention, but that no further inquiry is necessary before the House proceeds to a decision on the Resolution to approve the said Order:&lt;br/&gt;Read, and ordered to lie on the Table.' title='PRICES OF GOODS ACT, 1939 (AMENDMENT OF FIRST SCHEDULE) ORDER, 1941.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1941/sep/09/prices-of-goods-act-1939-amendment-of'></outline>
  </body>
</opml>
