<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Lords Report of 17 December 1920</title>
    <dateCreated>Fri, 17 Dec 1920 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='2280546' text="Report made from the Committee for Privileges&amp;#x2014;&lt;br/&gt;That on the 1st of August 1871 it was &lt;i&gt;Resolved&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Adjudged&lt;/i&gt; by this House that the Baronies of Botreaux, Hungerford, De Moleyns and Hastings are ancient Baronies in fee; that William Botreaux was first summoned to Parliament as Lord de Botereaux by Writ dated 24th of February in the 42nd year of King Edward III. (1368); that William 3rd Lord Botreaux the grandson of the said William Botreaux was present in Parliament on the 16th day of October in the 7th year of King Henry V. (1419); that Sir Walter Hungerford was first summoned to Parliament as Lord Hungerford by Writ dated the 7th January in the 4th year of King Henry VI. (1426) and was present in Parliament on the 22nd day of September in the 8th year of the said King (1429); that Robert Hungerford was first summoned to Parliament as Lord De Moleyns by Writ dated the 13th January in the 23rd year of Henry VI. (1445), and was present in Parliament as Lord De Moleyns on the 12th day of February in the 27th year of the said King (1449); that William Hastings was first summoned to Parliament by Writ dated the 26th July in the 1st year of King Edward IV. (1461) and was present in Parliament on the 4th day of November following (1461): That the late most Honourable Henry Weysford Charles Plantagenet, Marquess of Hastings, who died on the 10th November, 1868, was entitled to the said Baronies of Botreaux, Hungerford, De Moleyns and Hastings as the lineal heir of the said William Botreaux, Sir Walter Hungerford, Robert Hungerford, and William Hastings respectively; and that upon the death of the said most Honourable Henry Weysford Charles Plantagenet Marquess of Hastings, the said Baronies of Botreaux, Hungerford, De Moleyns, and Hastings fell into abeyance, among the four surviving sisters of the said Marquess; that is to say, 1st, Lady Edith Maud, Countess of Loudoun, the wife of Charles Frederick Abney Hastings, esquire; 2nd, Lady&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;562&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;Bertha Lelgarde, the wife of Captain, Augustus Wykeham Clifton; 3rd, Lady Victoria Mary Louisa, the wife of John Forbes Stratford Kirwan, Esquire; and, 4th, Lady Frances Augusta Constance, the wife of the Honourable Charles Marsham commonly called Viscount Marsham.&lt;br/&gt;That by Letters Patent dated the 6th day of November 1871 the abeyances existing in the said Baronies respectively were determined in favour of Edith Maud Countess of Loudoun.&lt;br/&gt;That Charles Edward Hastings Abney Hastings Earl of Loudoun in whom the said baronies were vested, died on the 17th day of May 1920 without issue and that the said Baronies thereupon fell into abeyance; that the Petitioner Edith Maud, Countess of Loudoun and the Petitioner Elizabeth Frances, Viscount St. Davids and the Lady Flora Ann Rawdon Hastings are the co-heirs to the said Baronies and that the said Baronies are accordingly now in abeyance between them.&lt;br/&gt;That the said Baronies of Botreaux, Hungerford, De Moleyns and Hastings are at His Majesty's disposal.&#x000A;Read, and &lt;i&gt;agreed to;&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;resolved&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;adjudged&lt;/i&gt; accordingly; and Resolution and Judgment to be laid before His Majesty by the Lords with White Staves." title='BARONIES OF BOTREAUX, HUNGERFORD, DE MOLEYNS AND HASTINGS.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1920/dec/17/baronies-of-botreaux-hungerford-de'></outline>
    <outline id='2280547' text="Report made from the Committee for Privileges&amp;#x2014;&lt;br/&gt;That the Barony of Strange of Knokin is an ancient Barony in fee.&lt;br/&gt;That it is proposed by the Writ of Summons addressed to John le Strange, the Ancestor of the Petitioners, in the 28th year of Edward 1st (1299) and by the other evidence adduced on behalf of the Petitioners, that the Barony of Strange of Knokin was in the reign of Edward 1st vested in the aforesaid John le Strange.&lt;br/&gt;That John, 8th Lord Strange of Knokin died leaving an only child and heir Joan, in her own right Baroness Strange of Knokin, who married Sir George Stanley, eldest son and heir apparent of Thomas, Earl of Derby and that the said Sir George Stanley was summoned to and sat in Parliament as Lord Strange of Knokin.&lt;br/&gt;That the Barony of Strange of Knokin descended to Ferdinando, 5th Earl of Derby, who died in the year 1594, when the said Barony fell into abeyance between his daughters and co-heirs, namely, the Ladies Anne, Frances and Elizabeth.&lt;br/&gt;That the Barony of Stanley is an ancient Barony in fee.&lt;br/&gt;That it is proved by the Writ of Summons addressed to Sir Thomas Stanley the Ancestor of the Petitioners in the 34th year of Henry VI (1456), and by the other evidence adduced on behalf of the Petitioners, that the Barony of Stanley was thereafter vested in the aforesaid Sir Thomas Stanley.&lt;br/&gt;That the Barony of Stanley descended to the aforesaid Ferdinando, 5th Earl of Derby, who died in the year 591, when the said Barony also fell into abeyance between his aforesaid daughters and co-heirs, namely, the Ladies Anne, Frances and Elizabeth.&lt;br/&gt;That the said Lady Anne married successively Grey Bridges, Lord Chandos, and Mervyn Tuchet, Earl of Castlehaven, and had issue but that it is not known that any descendant of hers now exists.&lt;br/&gt;That the said Lady Frances married John Egerton, Earl of Bridgwater and left issue and that George Henry Robert Child Child-Villiers, Earl of Jersey, and George Granville Sutherland Sutherland Leveson-Gower, Duke of Sutherland, and the heir or heirs, if any, of Diana, wife of Frederick Calvert, Lord Baltimore, are now her representatives and co-heirs.&lt;br/&gt;That the said Lady Elizabeth married Henry Hastings, Earl of Huntingdon and left issue and that Edith Maud Abney Hastings, in her own right Countess of Loudoun, one of the Petitioners, Elizabeth Frances, wife of John Wynford Philipps, Viscount St. Davids, the other of the Petitioners, the Lady Flora Anne Rawdon Hastings, Cecil&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;564&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;Talbot Clifton, Lord Grey de Ruthyn. Constantine Mary Joseph Bodenham Lubienski, May Flora Amy Kirwan, and Charles Marsham, Earl of Romney, are now her representatives and co-heirs.&lt;br/&gt;That the Baronies of Strange of Knokin and Stanley are now in abeyance between the said Earl of Jersey, the said Duke of Sutherland, the said Countess of Loudoun, the said Viscountess St. Davids, the said Lady Flora Anne Rawdon-Hastings, the said Lord Grey de Ruthyn, the said Constantine Mary Joseph Bodenham Lubienski, the said May Flora Amy Kirwan and the said Earl of Romney and the heir or heirs, if any, of the aforesaid Lady Anne, successively wife of the Lord Chandos and of the Earl of Castlehaven, and the heir or heirs, if any, of the afore-said Diana, wife of the Lord Baltimore.&lt;br/&gt;That the Baronies of Strange of Knokin and Stanley are at His Majesty's disposal.&#x000A;Read, and &lt;i&gt;agreed to:&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;resolved&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;adjudged&lt;/i&gt; accordingly; and Resolution and Judgment to be laid before His Majesty by the Lords with White Staves." title='BARONIES OF STRANGE OF KNOKIN AND STANLEY.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1920/dec/17/baronies-of-strange-of-knokin-and-stanley'></outline>
    <outline id='2280549' text="Ordered that all deed's, documents and papers produced on behalf of the claimants by their agents, to be delivered to the said agents.&lt;br/&gt;Proceedings and evidence taken before the Committee for Privileges, to be &lt;i&gt;printed&lt;/i&gt;" title='BARONIES OF BOTREAUX, HUNGERFORD, DE MOLKYNS AND HASTINGS.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1920/dec/17/baronies-of-botreaux-hungerford-de-1'></outline>
    <outline id='2280550' text='Ordered that all deeds, documents and papers produced on behalf of the claimants by their agents, be delivered to the said agents.&lt;br/&gt;Proceedings and evidence taken before the Committee for Privileges, to be &lt;i&gt;printed&lt;/i&gt;' title='BARONIES OF STRANGE, OF KNOKIN AND STANLEY.' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords_reports/1920/dec/17/baronies-of-strange-of-knokin-and-stanley-1'></outline>
  </body>
</opml>
