<?xml version="1/" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version='2/'>
  <head>
    <title>Written Statement of 16 December 2003</title>
    <dateCreated>Tue, 16 Dec 2003 00:00:00 +0000</dateCreated>
    <ownerName>UK Parliament</ownerName>
    <ownerEmail>mail@robertbrook.com</ownerEmail>
    <ownerId>http://www.parliament.uk</ownerId>
    <docs>http://www.opml.org/spec2</docs>
  </head>
  <body>
    <outline id='3515653' text='HOME DEPARTMENT'>
      <outline id='3515654' text='The Minister for Crime Reduction, Policing and Community Safety (Ms Hazel Blears)&lt;p&gt;I have today placed in the Libraries of both Houses copies of the Metropolitan Police Fund Accounts for 1998&amp;#x2013;99 and 1999&amp;#x2013;2000.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Metropolitan Police Fund' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/dec/16/metropolitan-police-fund'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3515666' text='TRADE AND INDUSTRY'>
      <outline id='3515667' text='The Minister for Energy, E-Commerce and Postal Services (Mr. Stephen Timms)&lt;p&gt;My right hon. Friend. now the Secretary of State, announced on 9 November 2000,&lt;i&gt;Official Report,&lt;/i&gt; columns 327&amp;#x2013;28, various measures to deal with interference from ADSL and similar systems, including interference regulations based on a standard, MPT 1570, to be implemented by regulations in due course. Since then, there has been only one reported and confirmed case of interference to medium wave broadcast reception and none to any other radio service. In view of this, I believe it would now be disproportionate to give statutory force to the standard. The operators of ADSL have made a voluntary commitment to take all reasonable steps to resolve any interference problems that do arise and I believe that is the pragmatic way forward for the time being. I expect that Ofcom, when it assumes responsibility for spectrum management matters on 2S December, will keep this matter under review.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The UK continues to contribute to work in Europe towards producing a harmonised approach to interference.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Radio Interference' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/dec/16/radio-interference'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3515669' text='CABINET OFFICE'>
      <outline id='3515670' text='The Minister for the Cabinet Office and Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster (Mr. Douglas Alexander)&lt;p&gt;An updated measurement of the level of compliance with the regulatory impact assessment process is today being placed on the website of the Cabinet Office regulatory impact unit. An exercise in November 2003 to establish a snapshot of the level of compliance provided a figure of 100 per cent. We will keep this under regular review.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Regulatory Impact Assessments' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/dec/16/regulatory-impact-assessments'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3515673' text='NORTHERN IRELAND'>
      <outline id='3515674' text="The Minister of State, Northern Ireland Office (Jane Kennedy)&lt;p&gt;On 8 September 2003, the Secretary of State formally accepted the recommendations of the Steele&lt;col&gt;130WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;Review of Safety at Maghaberry Prison. The review recommended that prisoners with paramilitary affiliations should be accommodated separately from each other, and from the rest of the prison population, on a voluntary basis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This major unforeseen change makes it now necessary to amend the Northern Ireland Prison Service Corporate and Business Plan 2003&amp;#x2013;06 to reflect the changing circumstances and priorities within the Service.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have approved the following amendments to the Corporate and Business Plan.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The planning assumptions will now include reference to the requirement to hold some prisoners with paramilitary affiliations in separated conditions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Amendments will also be made to reflect the extent to which the Service contributes generally to the NIO's objectives and PSA targets.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Three of the Service's twelve Key Targets for 2003&amp;#x2013;04 are adjusted as follows:&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Target 5: an average of at least 18 hours constructive activity per week for each sentenced prisoner (previously 20).&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Target 6: an average of at least 9 hours constructive activity per week for each remand prisoner (previously 12).&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Target 8: deliver at least 75&amp;#x0025; of the planned training days associated with the agreed corporate training priorities (previously 85&amp;#x0025;).&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;" title='Prison Service' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/dec/16/prison-service'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3515675' text='PRIME MINISTER'>
      <outline id='3515677' text="The Prime Minister (Mr. Tony Blair)&lt;p&gt;The United Kingdom delegation to the Parliamentary Assembly of the Council of Europe and the Assembly of Western European Union is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tony Lloyd MP (Leader)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&#x000A;&lt;table&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Full Representatives&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;i&gt;Substitute Representatives&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Mr David Atkinson MP&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Mr Tony Banks MP&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Mr Malcolm Bruce MP&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Baroness Billingham&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Sir Sydney Chapman MP&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Mr Peter Bottomley MP&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Mr Tom Cox MP&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Lord Burlison&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Right on. Terry Davies MP&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Right hon. George Foulkes MP&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Mr Bill Etherington MP&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Ms Jane Griffiths MP&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Mr Paul Flynn MP&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Mr Michael Hancock CBE MP&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Lord Judd&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Baroness Hooper&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Baroness Knight of Collingtree&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Right hon. Lord Kilclooney&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Christine McCafferty MP&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Mr Khalid Mahmood MP&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Mr Kevin McNamara MP&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Mr Humfrey Malins CBE MP&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Mr Jim Marshall MP&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Mr David Marshall MP&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Mr Edward O'Hara MP&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Mr Alan Meale MP&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Lord Russell-Johnston&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Mr Gordon Prentice MP&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Sir Teddy Taylor MP&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Miss Geraldine Smith MP&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Mr John Wilkinson MP&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Lord Tomlinson&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Mr Jimmy Wray MP&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Dr Rudolf Vis MP&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;td&gt;Mr Robert Walter MP&lt;/td&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/tr&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/table&gt;&#x000A;&lt;/p&gt;" title='Council of Europe and Western European Union' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/dec/16/council-of-europe-and-western-european'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3515679' text='TREASURY'>
      <outline id='3515681' text='The Chief Secretary to the Treasury (Mr. Paul Boateng)&lt;p&gt;Legislation governing public service pensions requires public service pensions to be increased annually by the same percentage as state earnings related pensions (additional pensions). My right hon. Friend the Secretary of State for Work and Pensions announced on 11 December 2003,&lt;i&gt;Official Report,&lt;/i&gt; columns 108&amp;#x2013;118WS, that benefits such as additional pensions will be increased by 2.8 per cent. in line with the annual increase in the Retail Prices Index up to September 2003. Public service pensions will therefore be increased by 2.8 per cent. from 12 April 2004, except those which have been in payment for less than a year, which will receive a pro-rata increase.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Public Service Pensions' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/dec/16/public-service-pensions'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3515682' text='WORK AND PENSIONS'>
      <outline id='3515684' text="The Secretary of State for Work and Pensions (Andrew Smith)&lt;p&gt;From January 2004, the Work and Pensions longitudinal study will link benefit and programme information held by the DWP on its customers, with employment records from the Inland Revenue.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This follows the Employment Act 2002 which introduced new data sharing provisions. This opened the way for the DWP to receive more data on employment from Inland Revenue and use the information for more purposes. The DWP and Inland Revenue have been working together to enable this data sharing to take place and to develop safeguards for the initiative.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Work and Pensions Longitudinal Study will be used to perform a range of statistical and research analyses, as well as being used for some limited operational purposes, to give the Department further opportunities to evaluate the effectiveness of its businesses. It will, for example:&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;provide statistics, management information and research on the success of Jobcentre Plus in helping people into work and keeping them in work;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;help to evaluate individual DWP policies and their impact in the short, medium and long-term;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;help to ensure that pensioners receive the money they're entitled to;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;aid in the investigation of benefit fraud; and&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;improve targeted information and marketing to clients.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The DWP have a legal and ethical responsibility to ensure that the Work and Pensions longitudinal study is used appropriately. We have, therefore, developed a set of safeguards around access rights, system monitoring, storage/retention of the information and vetting new uses. Information on this and a full range of the study's uses, has been placed in the Library and on the DWP website at http:/www.dwp.gov.uk/asd/ longitudinal&amp;#x2014;study/ic&amp;#x2014;longitudinal&amp;#x2014;study.asp&lt;/p&gt;" title='Longitudinal Study' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/dec/16/longitudinal-study'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3515685' text='FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH AFFAIRS'>
      <outline id='3515687' text='The Minister for Europe (Mr. Denis MacShane)&lt;p&gt;Members will wish to be aware of the outcome of the recent discussions in Geneva on national measures to reinforce the implementation of the Biological Weapons Convention (BWC). On the concluding day of the meeting of States Parties to the BWC, which took place from 10&amp;#x2013;14 November, there was agreement by consensus on a politically binding final document which enjoins all States Parties to the following actions:&lt;quote&gt;to review and, where necessary, enact or update national legal. including regulatory and penal, measures which ensure effective implementation of the prohibitions of the BWC and which enhance effective security of pathogens and toxins.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;co-operation between States Parties with differing legal and constitutional arrangements. States Parties in a position to do so may wish to provide legal and technical assistance to others who request it in framing and/or expanding their own legislation and controls in the area of national implementation and biosecurity.&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;comprehensive and concrete national measures to secure pathogen collections and the control of their use for peaceful purposes. There was a general recognition of the value of biosecurity measures and procedures, which will ensure that such dangerous materials are not accessible to persons who might or could misuse them for purposes contrary to the BWC.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There was also agreement that these measures are essential effort in facilitating more effective implementation and enforcement of the Convention, as well as providing the basis for an assessment of progress at the 2006 Review Conference.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As with the earlier meeting of BWC Experts in August, which had prepared the way for political decision-making, there was an impressive level of participation. Some 92 States Parties were represented and a total of 32 national statements were delivered, including one notably from Iraq which for the first time showed an open and positive engagement with its obligations under the Convention.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The United Kingdom was grateful to the Chair, Ambassador Toth of Hungary, for the efforts he made to achieve consensus on a Final Document that reflects the commonality of views and approaches that were demonstrated throughout. The commitment to assess progress at the Sixth Review Conference in 2006 on the extent to which States Parties have put in place the necessary legislation is, in our view, particularly important.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The outcome of the November meeting represents a very positive start to the work programme that lies ahead of us. Success was particularly important this year, as it is to be hoped that a precedent has now been set for agreement on effective action to emerge from the further meetings under the Biological Weapons Convention, scheduled to take place in 2004 and 2005.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The United Kingdom believes that the success of the meetings in 2003 has also helped to prove to the wider arms control community that this new process can be made to work. It has delivered a shared international analysis and a readiness to adopt practical measures. Most importantly, a co-operative spirit continued to prevail throughout the discussions in Geneva, which also augurs well for the future.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;image src="S6CV0415P2I0091"/&gt;&lt;col&gt;133WS&lt;/col&gt;&lt;p&gt;South Africa will chair the meetings next year on suspicious outbreaks of disease and the need for improved international surveillance. The UK takes over in 2005 with the task of examining a possible Code of Conduct for Scientists. Work has already begun on our preparations for both of these meetings. I will keep the House informed of developments and outcomes in 2004.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Biological Weapons Convention' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/dec/16/biological-weapons-convention'></outline>
      <outline id='3515688' text='The Minister for Europe (Mr. Denis MacShane)&lt;p&gt;At the meeting of States Parties to the Convention on Certain Conventional Weapons (CCW) in Geneva on 27/28 November, a new legally binding Protocol on Explosive Remnants of War (ERW) was adopted. The new Protocol (the 5&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; to the CCW) sets out obligations and best practice for the clearance of post-conflict ERW (munitions used during an armed conflict that should have exploded but failed to do so or munitions which have been abandoned during an armed conflict.) The principal obligations in the new Protocol are:&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;The State in control of the affected territory shall mark, clear, remove or destroy the ERW as soon as feasible and prioritise those affected areas posing a serious humanitarian risk;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;The user of munitions which have become ERW undertakes to provide assistance, where feasible, to the party in control of the affected territory to facilitate marking and clearance, removal or destruction of such ERW;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;The user of munitions which may become ERW undertakes to provide information on the use of such munitions (subject to legitimate security interests) to the party in control of the territory and to organisations undertaking clearance operations on the affected territory. The content of this information is provided on a voluntary, best practice basis;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Feasible precautions should be taken to warn civilians of the risks and effects of ERW;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;States shall take steps, to the extent feasible, to protect authorised humanitarian missions operating in the area under their control from the effects of ERW;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;States may provide assistance to deal with the threat posed by existing ERW;&lt;/quote&gt;&#x000A;&lt;quote&gt;Preventive measures, such as good practice in managing munitions to reduce the chance of their becoming unexploded, may be undertaken on a voluntary basis.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This Protocol is an important step in reducing humanitarian risks associated with ERW and fulfils a long-standing UK objective to secure agreement on a legally binding Instrument. The Government is looking&#x000A;&lt;col&gt;134WS&lt;/col&gt;&#x000A;into the necessary steps that may need to be taken to enable the Government to proceed to ratification of this Protocol.&lt;/p&gt;' title='Convention on Certain Conventional Weapons' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/dec/16/convention-on-certain-conventional'></outline>
    </outline>
    <outline id='3515691' text='DEFENCE'>
      <outline id='3515692' text="The Secretary of State for Defence (Mr. Geoffrey Hoon)&lt;p&gt;I am pleased to announce that I have appointed Mr Robert Burgin and Dr Peter Knight for a three year term of office as members of the Armed Forces' Pay Review Body commencing 4 February. Mr Neil Sherlock is also re-appointed for a second three-year term from 4 March. These appointments and re-appointment have been conducted in accordance with the guidance of the office of the Commissioner for Public Appointments. The Prime Minister has announced earlier today that he is appointing Professor David Greenaway as the next Chairman of the Armed Forces Pay Review Body.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Secretary of State for Defence (Mr. Geoffrey Hoon)&lt;p&gt;The Supplement to the 2003 Report of the Armed Forces Pay Review Body making final recommendations on the pay of Service Medical and Dental Officers has been published today. Copies of the Supplement are available in the Vote Office and the Library of the House.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Review Body recommends a final increase of 6.8 per cent. for all Regular and Reserve Defence Medical Services Medical and Dental Officers, in addition to the 3.2 per cent. interim award already implemented on 1 April 2003, representing a total increase of 10 per cent. The Review Body also recommends a pay increase of 3.225 per cent. for medical and dental cadets and an out-of-hours supplementary payment of &amp;#x00A3;8,500 to junior doctors. In addition, the Review Body recommends that there should be no further increase in the values of Sustained Quality Payments, Trainer pay and Distinction Awards, above the interim 3.2 per cent. increase already implemented.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The cost of these recommendations to the Defence Budget, including the interim award already implemented, will be some &amp;#x00A3;14.5M. This will be met within existing Departmental expenditure limits.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Review Body's final recommendations are to be accepted in full, with implementation effective from 1 April 2003.&lt;/p&gt;" title='Armed Forces Pay' type='link' url='http://hansard.millbanksystems.comhttp://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_statements/2003/dec/16/armed-forces-pay'></outline>
    </outline>
  </body>
</opml>
